<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The oath of allegiance and the national covenant proved to be non-obliging: or, three several papers on that subject; viz. 1. Two positions, with several reasons of them, and consequences flowing from thence. 2. An answer to the said positions. 3. A reply to the said answer, wherein the truth of the positions is vindicated, and the oath of allegiance, and the national covenant are made non-obliging. / By Samuel Eaton, teacher of the Church of Christ at Darkenfield in Chesshire.</title>
            <author>Eaton, Samuel, 1596?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82549</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E606_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E613_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865101</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865101</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165675</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82549)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165675)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 93:E606[2], 94:E613[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The oath of allegiance and the national covenant proved to be non-obliging: or, three several papers on that subject; viz. 1. Two positions, with several reasons of them, and consequences flowing from thence. 2. An answer to the said positions. 3. A reply to the said answer, wherein the truth of the positions is vindicated, and the oath of allegiance, and the national covenant are made non-obliging. / By Samuel Eaton, teacher of the Church of Christ at Darkenfield in Chesshire.</title>
                  <author>Eaton, Samuel, 1596?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 4, 23, [1], 51 [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Peter Cole, at the sign of the Printing-Press in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>'Two positions', and 'An answer to the said positions' have separate pagination. 'A reply to the said answer' has separate pagination and register.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy E.606[2]: "July 1st"; annotation on Thomason copy E.613[18]: "Octob: 4th".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oaths --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165675:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The OATH of ALLEGIANCE AND THE NATIONAL COVENANT PROVED To be NON-OBLIGING: <hi>OR,</hi> THREE SEVERAL PAPERS ON THAT SUBJECT; <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Two POSITIONS, with ſeveral <hi>REASONS</hi> of them, and <hi>CONSEQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ENCES</hi> flowing from thence.</item>
               <item>2. An ANSWER to the ſaid <hi>POSITIONS.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>A REPLY to the ſaid <hi>ANSWER,</hi> wherein the Truth of the <hi>Poſitions</hi> is Vindicated, and the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> and the <hi>National Covenant</hi> are made Non-Obliging.</p>
            <p>By SAMUEL EATON, Teacher of the Church of Chriſt at DARKEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FIELD in CHESSHIRE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Peter Cole,</hi> at the ſign of the Printing-Preſs in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange, 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:165675:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165675:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not many daies ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I was informed, that ſome <hi>Poſitions</hi> of mine, reſpecting <hi>the Oath of Allegiance,</hi> were made publick to the world, and that an <hi>Anſwer</hi> thereto was annexed, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Poſitions</hi> was printed, which at firſt I could hardly receive for truth: but for further ſatisfaction, the book was ſent me, and in the Title Leaf, I read, <hi>An Anſwer to ſome Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Mr.</hi> Samuel Eaton <hi>(diſperſed by him.)</hi> I am neceſſitated for the Vindication of my ſelf, to publiſh the bad dealings that I have met with in this buſineſs from Brethren, I will not call them falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brethren, though their proceedings do hold forth too much falſeneſs and baſeneſs.</p>
            <p>I had occaſion in the latter end of the laſt yeer, to be often times at a Gentlemans houſe of honorable note in <hi>Lancaſhire;</hi> he declared himſelf unſatisfied how the Oath of Allegiance could be Non-Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, which was ſo abſolutely taken by many of the Subjects, and by himſelf: I gave him ſuch Anſwers as were ſuitable to my preſent ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions: his requeſt was, That I would put down in writings what I had preſented in words, or any other conceptions of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, about that ſubject, and ſend them to him: I condeſcended, and in a free friendly way preſented him with my ſudden thoughts, and incloſed them in a letter to him, having had his promiſe not to communicate the ſame to any, ſave to one friend of his, whoſe private conceptions of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m he would entreat, and would ſhew them to me. But thus it fell out, there waas a piece of diſhoneſtly (I might put a worſe term upon it) acted by ſome, that would be better thought of. The letter ſent to this Gentleman was opened, a Copy was taken of the Poſitions conteined therein, and many Copies written out of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and diſperſed abroad, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver two Counties, before ever the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman
<pb facs="tcp:165675:3"/> (to whom I writ, and ſent the ſaid Poſitions) received his Letter. I wondred much at it, knowing that I had not given any Copy to any Creature, and had not ſo much as ſhewed it to any at that time, ſave to three perſons. The Gentleman diſcerning that the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had been opened, and hearing that Copies were got abroad, thought himſelf bound to ſearch it out, ſome pains was taken to diſcover it, at laſt it came to light. I could both name the place where, and the perſon by whom it was done, but for ſome ſpecial reaſons I forbear. The Gentleman when he had peruſed the Writing ſent it to his friend, and his friend inſtead of Anſwering it himſelf, (as I expected) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures an elaborate Anſwer unto it; which after the ſpace of ſix weeks or two months was ſent unto me, and therein my two Poſitions were ſpoken to, but nothing elſe that was contained in my Paper was med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with. And the Author of this Anſwer, at that time, thought to have proceeded no further in his Anſwer, but about ſix weeks after the receipt of the other, the ſecond part of his Anſwer was given to me, both which are now printed to the view of the world by means of ſome Brethren about <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> to whom a Copy of the Anſwer was ſent, without the knowledg, and unto the offence of the Author thereof, as I am credibly informed. I had ſent my Reply to that part of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer which firſt came to my hands, to be peruſed in a private way, before I knew that any thing was extent in print, but am now forced to expoſe it to Publick view. By all this it may appear that I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to engage in this Controverſie, but could not decline the giving of an Anſwer to a Queſtion propounded. If any ſatisfaction ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe to any by any thing which I repreſent, I ſhall be thankful to God. However I ſhall not repine, becauſe it was Gods Will, that my private conceptions muſt thus come to light. Notwithſtanding, wrong doers muſt give an account. I remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy friend in the Truth, SAM. EATON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="positions">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165675:3"/>
            <div n="1" type="position">
               <head>POSITION I.</head>
               <p>EVERY Oath to make it warran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able, and lawful, ought to be taken in Judgment and Righteouſneſs. <hi>Ier.</hi> 4. 2.</p>
               <p>The Oath then of Allegience, that it may be in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Judment muſt be,</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Conditional, not Abſolute; mutual, not ſingle: taken by both Parties, not by one onlie: by the Ruler or Governor, not alone by the Ruled; by the Prince, as well as by the Subject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is againſt the ground and reaſon of the Primitive Inſtitution of Government, which is the good of the Subject, That there ſhould be any Oath to hind the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject abſolutelie to Allegiance and Dutie, whether the Prince or Governour rule for the Subjects good or not; therefore ſuch an Oath cannot be taken by the Subject in judgment, or in righteouſneſs; therefore ſuch an Oath is not lawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So again it is againſt Equity, and Reaſon, and againſt the good of the Subject, that he ſhould be further or longer bound to the Prince, or Ruler, to ſubmit to him, then the Prince or Ruler is bound to the Subject, to rule well, and adminiſter ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice rightlie, if therefore the Obligation be not mutual, but ſingle, it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſequence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then (if the Oath of Allegiance taken to the late King, were in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and righteouſneſs, and ſo lawful) the King was, or ought to have been, as ſtrongly bound to all his Subjects by Oath, as any of them to him; then if he break his oath, all the Subjects are abſolved, if they will. Then at what time the King levyed War againſt his Subjects, they were diſcharged by that breach of oath in him, of their Allegiance, elſe the whole Parliament, and Parliamentary party were both perjured per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (as many of them as ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that Oath) and are Rebels, that have taken up Arms againſt the King.</p>
               <p>2 <hi>Not to Heires.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe who knoweth (as</hi> Solomon <hi>ſaith</hi> Eccleſ. 2. 19.) <hi>whether the Heir will be a Wiſe man, or a Fool: a juſt and righteous man, or a wicked man, and tyrant. Now if no man know this, then it is not an Oath in judgment, if any man ſwear Allegiance to an Heir, nor is it a righteous Oath, for the Subject may hind himſelf to his own hurt, yea ruin and deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:165675:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſequence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the oath of Allegiance was in that branch of it that reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heirs, an unlawful oath; for who knows what any of the late Kings Poſterity might have proved? Whether they would have upheld Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or have changed it? Whether they would have upheld the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Propriety of the Subject, or ſubverted it? We know what their Education was, Who then could take an oath in righteouſneſs and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in reference to them? It is good to know firſt, and to ſwear after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p>3 <hi>Not to any one kind of Government, Monarchical, or any other, to uphold it, and continue it, in a conſtant way, without changing of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe, though Civil Government in general be an Ordinance of God, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to mans good, therefore to reject it would be ſinful; yet this or that kind of Government is not an Ordinance of God, but an Ordinance of man,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 13. <hi>And if an Ordinance of man, then man may change it, for his own greateſt good, and benefit, and muſt change it, when he hath proved any kind of Government inconvenient, and hurtful. Then to ſwear not to change it, is ſinful, and in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and judgment may not be done, for all kinds of Government is not equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie good, uor are they equallie ſuitable to all people; and experience makes perſons wiſe to diſcern what is better, and what is worſe for themſelves: Therefore an Oath to uphold any one kind of Government, longer then it continues to be moſt ſafe and profitable, is unlawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſequence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the oath of allegiance ſerving to uphold Kingly. Government againſt all other, was an unlawful oath; for who knows not what a plague this kind of Government hath been to this Nation? and who knows not that the moſt of our Kings have been Tyran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s? and who knows not what a Bleſſing the change of Government hath brought to the United Provinces<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Objection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſuppoſe there was ſome unlawfulneſs in the taking of ſuch Oathes, yet is there not a neceſſity of keeping them being taken?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If that Oath taken againſt the life of one man, by <hi>Herod,</hi> becauſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, and cruel, was not only ſinfully taken, but more ſinfully kept; then ſuch oaths of allegiance which are abſolute, and not conditional, which are ſingle, and not mutual, which are to Heirs, whether wiſe-men or fools, whether juſt men or Tyrants, which are to uphold Monarchy, (the woful fruits whereof having been long taſted, and felt by this Nation) ſeeing they are dangerous, and may pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e (as often they have done) deſtructive to the lives of many men, they are not only unlawful to be taken, but unlawful to be kept.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="position">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:165675:4"/>
               <head>POSITION II.</head>
               <p>SUppoſe the Oath of Allegiance be a lawful Oath, yet the Subject is now abſolved from it, by them that have Power to abſolve from it.</p>
               <p>Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Repreſentatives of the People, which in reaſon are the Supream Power of the Nation, impoſed this Oath upon the Subject, by an Act for it, made in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, by which they obliged the Subject to Allegiance to the King, then in being, and to his Heirs. And this Act done by their Repreſentatives was their own vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie Act, to which they were not obliged by anie law of God, or Nature; for there is no rule requiring them to accept of ſuch a Perſon to be their Prince, and his Heirs after him, and to ſwear Allegiance to him and them; but this was the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects own free Act, in their Repreſentatives: Therefore if the Repreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntatives take away this Act and repeal it, they thereby ſet the Subjects at Libertie from ſuch Allegiance, and from that Oath by which they are bound to it.</hi> Abraham <hi>that impoſed the Oath upon his Servant, might acquit him of it, becauſe not bound by anie rule from God, but obliged by</hi> Abraham <hi>onlie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſequence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This preſent Parliament, having taken away that Oath of Allegiance, which was Enacted to be impoſed; there remains no more Conſcience of it, to ſuch who have taken it.</p>
               <p>But then it will come unto this,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether the Parliament be the Supream Power?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether the Repreſentatives of the People, be the Parliament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether the preſent Repreſentatives that now Sit in Parliament, be the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of the People?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>Firſt</hi> I ſay, 1 It is evident, That the Norman Kings coming in by Conqueſt had never any true Right to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> but what the Parliament gave them: Then the Power of the Parliament was greater then theirs; becauſe that Power, that is the Cauſe of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, is greater then that Power, that is the Effect of Power: 2 The Power of Parliament, is the Power of the People; now in Reaſon the Power of the People is the Supream Power, becauſe thence (as from the Root) all Power firſt ſprang, and proceeded.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>Second</hi> I ſay, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Parliaments Power be the Peoples Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and the Supream Power, then the Repreſentatives of the People, are the Parliament, and none elſe: for the Repreſentatives of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are the People in them, and there is the Root of Power, therefore they are a Parliament.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:165675:5"/>
               <p>To the <hi>Third</hi> I ſay, The preſent Repreſentatives that now Sit in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, are, 1 All of them Choſen by the People, therefore of Right they Sit in Parliament. 2 The preſent Repreſentatives are all that are left to Sit in Parliament; for the moſt of the reſt have Deſerted their Truſt, without any Force upon them; for though ſome were Secluded and Secured, yet the reſt were not at all interrupted, but have voluntarily Departed from the Houſe. 3 The Repreſentatives that Remained, and Continued to Sit in Parliament, were alwayes, when feweſt, and ſtill are above the Number allowed of by Law; and therefore they are a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
               <p>There is one Objection, which may be urged againſt the Parliaments Abſolving men from their Allegiance to the Kings Heirs, and againſt their Aboliſhing Kingly Government. It may be ſaid, That</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Kings have the ſame Right to their Kingdoms, Crowns, and Revenues, as others</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>have to their Mannors, and Demeſnes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such Right which Kings have had, they never juſtly came by it, but <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> by Force and Flattery have obtained it, and have Uſurped upon the Birth-right of the People, to whom it belongs to Chuſe them that muſt Rule over them: and Kingdoms with the Appurtenances thereto, were never intended for particular mens Advancements; to lift up ſuch Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies in Glory and Greatneſs; or that the Heraeditary Right of any ſhould be in them; but that Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, and Vertue was to lift up men unto them; and Crowns and Revenues were to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them in acting in ſuch Places; and men that were ſo Qualified, were to be Heirs, and Succeſſors, ſet up by the People, after them. And the People themſelves, nor their Repreſentatives, could neither Give, nor Sell away this Priviledge from their Poſterity, in which the welfare of the People is ſo mainly concerned, and without which a People are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up, and ſold to Ruine. This cannot be ſaid of Mannors and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnes which are things which fall under Commutative Juſtice, and are things vendible, and wherein particular men are concerned, and not the Common-Wealth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165675:5"/>
            <head>AN ANSVVER <hi>TO A</hi> PAPER Pretending to prove the OATH of ALLEGIANCE Void, and non-Obliging: <hi>Containing</hi> TWO POSITIONS, <hi>The Subſtance whereof is Repeated in the Proceſs of this ANSWER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE drift of the Firſt Poſition, and the proſecution thereof, (with which I begin) is to ſhew the ſaid Oath to have been unlawful and unwarrantable in the taking of it, and ſo void in the fact, or making.</p>
            <p>1 I ſhall premiſe for the cleering partly of what follows, That an<note place="margin">D. Sand. de Iuram. obl. pr. 2. §. 14</note> Oath may be unlawful, 1 Either in regard of the matter, or thing ſworn, as if a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſwear to do any impoſſible, or ſinful act. 2 Or in the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or Circumſtances of ſwearing; as if a man ſwear unadviſedly, or with a falſe intention or other-wayes unduly for manner. The former way of unlawfulneſs makes an Oath void in the taking, but not the Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: So that though a man ſwear an Oath (in ſome ſort) not in Truth, that is, not intending to be tyed to, or to keep it; or not in Judgment,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165675:6"/> that is, not conſideratly enough; yet if the Oath be in Righteouſneſs, that is, of a juſt, and lawful matter, or thing, it is of Force; otherwiſe no Oath could bind in <hi>foro externo,</hi> or be of any uſe for Confirmation, for who can diſcern with what mind another man Swears? Again, This evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appears by the validity of that unadviſed Oath of the Princes to the Gibe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nites, Joſhu. 9. 15. 18, 19. 2 Sam. 21. 2. And of that Oath of <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kiah,</hi> and his people to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> 2 Cron. 36. 13. Ezek. 17. 13 21. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. which they entred into treacherouſly, Hoſ. 104. <note n="‡" place="margin">Annotat of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mes &amp; Diodat. on Hoſ. 10 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>2 I obſerve what a groſs Imputation the firſt Poſition layeth upon the King, and Parliament that framed and Ordained the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and all other Parliaments ſince that have Continued, and the Succeſſive Houſes of Commons that have Sworn it, with thoſe multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and of other Profeſſions in the Kingdom that have taken, and ſtill hold themſelves bound by it (having had all the while ſo much Divine and Goſpel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> light ſhining forth to and in them) as if they had publiſhed, preſſed, taken, and juſtified (as againſt the Papiſts by writing) an Oath the matter of it unjuſt and ſinful. This man had need bring cleer Reaſons for what he here thus chargeth upon ſo many Worthyes, for place, piety, and judgment; and declare them<note place="margin">A Lye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Title, or the Title a Lye againſt this.</note> more publickly then by a <hi>Private Paper,</hi> that he may call to Repentance the whole Nation, that is (as he ſuppoſeth) involved in this impiety of an unlawful Oath. But let us firſt by the Tryal of his Reaſons, ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath not more need to repent of this his Charge.</p>
            <p>His general exception againſt the lawfulneſs of the Oath is, <hi>That it is not according to the rule</hi> Jer. 4. 2. <hi>in Iudgment and in Righteouſneſs.</hi> Were it defective [in judgment] that is (in deliberatneſs of taking) that would not be (as I have ſaid) a ground to invalidate its obligation <hi>ipſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acto:</hi> ſeeing it were but a failing in the manner, not a corruptneſs in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: a fault in the Perſon ſwearing, not in the Oath ſworn: and in the perſon a defect internal, or of the mind, not externally viſible in the act: and to be preſumed to be found only in ſome perſons ſwearing, not in all. That part therefore of the Allegation, were it true, might have been left out, and as often as it is brought in to prove the Oath unlawful ſo as not to bind, it addes no ſtrength to the Concluſion. But to deſcend to his particulars, 1 To manifeſt the Oath's diſagreement with the ſaid rule of <hi>Ieremiah.</hi> His firſt particular Exception is, <hi>That it ought to have been Conditional, not Abſolute; Mutual, not Single.</hi> His Argument in effect runs thus, <hi>That it may be in Iudgment and Righteouſneſs, it muſt be Conditional not Abſolute; Mutual, or taken both by Ruler, and Rulled; not Single, or taken onlie by one Partie. But this Oath is not ſo Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> That the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may underſtand us both, and I may more cleerly paſs on in my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, I muſt interpoſe a diſtinction or two upon the Terms.</p>
            <p>1 Saith he, <hi>The Oath muſt be Conditional, not Abſolute.</hi> 1 I conceive
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165675:6"/> the words [Conditional, and Abſolute] may be taken, 1 Either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the thing ſworn, which is Obedience, or Allegiance to the KING; thus the Oath muſt be Conditional, not Abſolute; that is, the obedience which we bind our ſelves to, muſt be with limitation, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndition, reſtraining it (as all obedience to men in any relation is to be, to juſt, honeſt, lawful things, or ſo as to Conſiſt with our obedience to God; not abſolute or illimited in that ſenſe. 2 Or in reference to the tye, or obligation of the oath, as the qualification thereof; and ſo I ſay it may be Abſolute, and muſt not of neceſſity be Conditional, that is, The ſubordinate and limited obedience which is due to the Prince or Magiſtrate, I may ſwear unto abſolutely, or withour any ſpecial Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion annexed to my Engagement. <hi>Special Condition</hi> I ſay, for I muſt once again diſtinguiſh, to wit, of Conditions. 1 Some are general, and ſuch as no promiſary oath that is lawful can be without, thoſe are (I think) all of them reduced to theſe two heads, namely that the thing ſworn be <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt</hi> and <hi>Poſſible.</hi> Theſe Conditions are preſuppoſed, and not wont to be expreſt, and notwithſtanding the including of them an oath may be ſaid to be Abſolute. 2 Others are <hi>Special,</hi> and <hi>Proper</hi> Conditions, which are ingredients in ſome oaths, the which are (by reaſon of them) termed Conditional. They are uſually either ſomewhat that is Contingent, as when a Merchant Covenants and Swears to give an hundred pounds to another man, or to a publick Uſe, if his Ship (that is gone to Sea) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home ſafe with her Merchandize; or, that which is Arbitrary, or in the choice of mans Will, his (commonly) to whom the oath is En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged; as if a Maſter Covenant and Swear to maintain his Servant with Meat, Drink, and ſuch Wages, if he be a true and diligent Servant to him. It is not the Former, but this Latter Conditionality which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires in the oath of Allegiance, to wit, That the Subject be only bound to his Duty of Allegiance if, and ſo long as the Prince obſerveth his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Government inviolate: and this in truth is not in that oath, nor is it neceſſary to make the oath lawful. The Major therefore of this <hi>Oath-impugners Syllogiſme</hi> I deny in that firſt part of it, viz. <hi>It muſt be Conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, not Abſolute:</hi> To make good my Denial, 1 I will Anſwer what he ſaith to prove it. 2 Bring in my Reaſons againſt it: and leave the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to judge betwixt us.</p>
            <p>1 All that he ſaith for proof of that Aſſertion is this, <hi>It is againſt the ground, and reaſon of the Primitive Inſtitution of Government, which is the good of the Subject, that there ſhould be any Oath to bind him Abſolutlie, whether the Prince Rule for the Subjects good, or not.</hi> This were ſomething if it were proved, but the Reader is left either to take it upon his word, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main unſatisfied both of it, and the concluſion which depends upon it, if he like to do neither, let him try whether I can ſatisfie him to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:165675:7"/>1 The Parliament that Enacted this Oath, and all ſubſequent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments who were intruſted with, and moſt able (in all probability) to judge what would be for the Subjects good, and who (without all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie) were more ſufficient and competent Judges thereof then this man, have adjudged it not againſt, but for the Subjects good.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It hath conſiſted with the publick good (yea contributed to it, or els the Papiſts would not have ſo oppoſed it) from the time it was firſt ſet forth, until now, in impartial mens judgments, and no complaint hath been at all heard againſt it from the Kingdom, nor ſcarcely, if at all, from particular men, till within theſe few dayes, what the ſuppreſſing of it on the other hand will tend to, a little time may fully enough manifeſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A thing may be ſaid to be againſt the peoples good in two very far different ſenſes: 1 Either in it ſelf of its own nature, or ſimply conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: of this ſort are injuſtice, impunity of offences, ſedition, conſpiracy, hoſtile invaſion, and the like; ſuch things are in their own nature op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the publick good. 2 Or accidentally and contigently, thus any thing almoſt that fals under a political conſideration, and comes under the dehberation of the Law-givers, though lawful in it ſelf, and for the preſent probably, yea, or neceſſarily good for a Common-wealth, may prove in the event ſomewhat incommodious and hurtful. There is a goodneſs of the end, which is one and the ſame in all States and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, <hi>viz.</hi> The happineſs of the Community, and this is intended, not deliberated on, or choſen by the Law-givers: <note n="*" place="margin">Ac deliberamus quidem non de fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſed de iis quae referuntur ad fines. <hi>Ariſtot.</hi> Eth. l. 3. c. 3.</note> And there is a goodneſs of the means tending to that end, and this is variable in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to times and people; that may be good in the nature of a means for one people, or time, that is not ſo for another. <note n="‡" place="margin">Eſt enim genus hominum natura va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riè comparatum atque affectum, aliud ſervile, aliud colendis regthus accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum; aliud Democraticum &amp; Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare; at que horum generum ſuum cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que eſt ac diſtinctum commodum. <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtot. Polit.</hi> l. 3. c. 12. num. 112. Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que manifeſtum eſt ejuſdem diſciplinae eſſe conſiderare, non ſolum quae ſit, &amp; qualis optima Reſpublica, cujus ſtatus ſi nulla vis obſtiterit, maximè deſidere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; optetur; ſed etiam, quae cuique congrua &amp; conſentanea eſt, permulti enim optimam conſequi nequeunt, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re neque Legiſlator, neque is qui verè civilis habeatur, ignorare debet quae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ub tam abſolutè perfecta ſit, tum pro ſtatu rerum preſaentium maximè lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danda, tum denique quae pro conditione aliqua non ſit improbanda. <hi>Idem</hi> l. 4. c. 1. num. 2. Itaque cognoſcendae erant rerum publicarum ſpecies, ac differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, &amp; quot modis u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter ſe commiſcean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, cumque haec eadem prudentia opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum legum ſcientia &amp; unicuique Reipub. convenientium conjungenda eſt, ad reſpublicas enim leges ſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodandae non autem ad leges res ipſae publicae. <hi>Idem eodem</hi> Nu. 6. 27</note> It is the means and its goodneſs which fals under the conſulation of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlators, and becauſe of the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty thereof, they are occaſioned often to change their adviſements and laws: But by reaſon that in things which approach neer the foundation, or do conſtitute it, changes are very perillous in a State, and in thoſe things it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to bear an inconvemency, then to run the hazard of an in<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ovation; therefore it hath been the honeſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165675:7"/> and neceſſary wiſdome of moſt States, to ſettle them by a firmer Sanction then they uſe in other things, and to ordain a kind of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutability in them, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to ratifie them by Oaths, fore-ſeeing that no inconvenience in the Conſtitution of a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in it ſelf lawful and eligible, can match the miſchief of an-alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and therefore that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain danger of that is rather to be choſen, then the inevitable mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of this: Such things as may by reaſon of their changeable nature prove in the iſſue ſome what diſadvantagious, may yet, if for the preſent good, and probably hopeful ſo to continue, be ſworn to abſolutly, as in voluntary Promiſes, Leagues, and Contracts, both publike and private, among all Nations hath been the practiſe, and by good Scripture-preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents it is juſtified, <note n="‡" place="margin">Gen. 47. 31. Exod. 13. 19. Joſh. 9. 15 14 9. Judg. 21. 5. 18. 15. 12. 13. 1 Sam. 14. 24. 19. 6. 20. 12. 17 1 King. 1. 13. 29. 2 Sam. 29. 23.</note> and the reaſon is, Becauſe if any future prejudice do redound, it can be (the Obligation of the Oath remaining) at the worſt, but an outward incommodity, the which is compenſated by the avoiding of a greater evil, which the leaving of the matter free and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecured would more certainly breed and bring. To apply all this to the caſe in hand: If any impeachment of the Subjects good can be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to reſult out of his ſweating to his Prince abſolutly, whether he Rule well or no, it is but accidental, and ſuch as it is, it is over-ballanced with a greater miſchief which would accrue by leaving the Subjects un-inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: for the ſhuning of which, the leſſer evil, to wit, the being bound to a King, though he ſhould prove a bad Governor, is to be choſen; for that, in compariſon of a greater evil, hath the conſideration of good, and is ſo eligible: It is a leſs evil for a people to be bound to a Prince that poſſibly may prove bad, then to be ſo looſe, as to be at liberty to caſt him off when they ſhall judge him to Rule ill, that is, when they pleaſe; the former doth not ſo neerly and probably tend to the ſubjects hurt as doth the latter: For, firſt, The Prince may prove juſt and vertuous. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, If he degenerates, the Subject is bound to obey him actively, but in lawful things. Thirdly, In his lawleſs Acts there may be a remedy (as the puniſhment or reſiſtance of his bad inſtruments by the Parliament, without whom, though he may Will unjuſt things, yet he cannot Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them) and yet his Government be continued. Fourthly, And ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the caſe that there be no remedy, as when he hath got a party ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then can be reſiſted, or ſubjected to puniſhment, then to caſt off his power and depoſe him (ſuppoſe it lawful to do) will be no relief, his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165675:8"/> ſtrength will command ſubjection. Fifthly, The miſcarriages of a Prince ordinarily (unleſſe it come to publick conteſtation, wherein the Subjects ſworn and unſworn, if their cauſe be juſt, and the Parliameot authorize their ſtanding up, are in the ſame capacity of reſiſtence) extend but to the detriment of ſome particular perſons, rarely doth any <hi>Nero</hi>-like, ſeek the deſtruction of the whole. But on the other hand, ſet the people free to ſhake off the reins of their preſent Government, when they ſhall think it unequal, and, 1 You deſtroy the nature of Government, as will after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be ſhewed. 2 You expoſe the people to an immediate loſſe of the very uſe and enjoyment of any Government, the power of mobility and change being ſure to invite al ill-diſpoſed perſons immediatly to put that power in ure, and hurry all (if they may prevail) into conſuſion. In ſhort, a bad Government is better then none; it is more tolerable for a people that one, or few, then that every man do that which is right in his own eyes. To be bound to Allegiance, may lay the people open to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; to be looſe, will precipitate them into the latter: The former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience cannot be ſo univerſally extenſive, ſpeedily deſtructive, and remedileſs, or unreſiſtible, as the latter.</p>
            <p>2 The latter thing I premiſed, is to give my Reaſons for the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory to his Major Propoſition in that firſt part, <hi>It muſt be Conditional, not Abſolute:</hi> Againſt which I ſay, The oath of allegiance may be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, or unconditional, in the ſenſe before given; and for this Aſſertion, I render theſe Reaſons:</p>
            <p>1 Were there no Oath, the limited obedience which is due to Princes and Magiſtrates, is due to them abſolutly; that is, Whether they Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e well or no; and that which is abſolutly due, may be obſolutly ſworn; The former Propoſition I ground thus;</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Precept of Obedience to Civil Governors, is without any condition or reſerve of a diſingagement of the Subject in caſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors miſcarriage; reade the Fifth Commandement, and thoſe other Injunctions, Rom. 13. 1, 2, &amp;c. Tit. 3. 1. 1 Pet. 2. 13, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2 God commands his people to be ſubject to Heathen Princes, and the moſt abſolute and oppreſſive Tyrants that likely ever have ben, Jer. 27. 12. Mat. 22. 21. 1 Pet. 2. 13. I ſpeak not here of Tyrants, in regard of Title, or Right; that is, Uſurpers: but of Tyrants whoſe Title is juſt, but their Government unjuſt, and oppreſſive.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Servants are to be ſubject to their Maſters, not only that are good and gentle, but thoſe that are froward, and do them wrong, and from whom they ſuffer for wel-doing, 1 Pet. 2. 18, 19, 20. and by Analogy. Subjects are tyed in the ſame terms to their Governors.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>David</hi> would not ſtretch out his hand againſt <hi>Saul</hi> upon this ground, for that he was his Maſter the King of Iſrael, and the Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, though he was then in actual, violent, and unjuſt purſuit of his life, 1 Sam. 24. 5. &amp;c. 26. 9. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:165675:8"/>5 Otherwiſe you leave no place for paſſive obedience to pray for, and patience towards Magiſtrates in caſe of their wrong doing, and your innocency, which yet is generally acknowledged to be a duty <note n="‡" place="margin">Ameſ. Medula Theol. l. 1. c. 17. p. 57. Vrſin. Cat. p. 3. q. 104</note>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 Els you diſſolve all Magiſtracy, it will be impoſſible in mans cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt eſtate to retain or continue any, in as much as no man, or men, can in the vaſt multitude, and difficulty of Magiſtratical affairs avoid offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding every day, 2 Sam. 23. 3, 5.</p>
            <p n="7">7 The Doctrin of orthodox Proteſtant Divines generally is, That obedience is due (in lawful things) to the moſt degenerate, oppreſſing, and tyrannical Princes <note n="‡" place="margin">Calvin. Inſt. l 4 c. 20. §. 24, 25, &amp;c. Pet. Mart. loc. C cl. 4. C. 2. §. 12. 18, 19. Alſ. Theol. C. 17. Reg. 8. Perk C. of Conſ. l. 3 c. 6. §. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Buc. Inſti. Theol. loc. 49. q. 21. Synop. pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Theol. diſ. 50. Theſ. 18. 27. Sharp. ſim. Epoch. 5. Q. 44. 45.</note>
            </p>
            <p>2 We find oaths of Allegiance in Scripture, ſworn to Princes without any Conditions inſerted, Judg. 11. 9, 10. 2 King. 11. 4. 2 Chron. 36. 13. Ezek. 17. 13. &amp; Nehem. 10. 29. Their oath was to obſerve all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Lord, whereof the fifth Commandement, with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to their preſent and future Magiſtrates, was one.</p>
            <p>3 It is a thing within our power to ſettle our Allegiance abſolutly, as well as it is within a mans power to diſpoſe of himſelf to ſervice ſo, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Maſter prove good, or evil, or as it is in a man or womans pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to beſtow themſelves in Marriage, whether the mate be obſervant of duty, or no?</p>
            <p>4 A Conditional oath is not conſiſtent with a neceſſary duty; obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Magiſtrates is no leſs arbitrary, but commanded, and that though they be bad; but now the duty being neceſſary, if you would have it ſworn with a proviſo of the Rulers performing his duty, you nulliſie the end of an Oath, which is to confirm, put out of doubt, and give ſecurity of what is due. A thing ſworn may become due, either by the rule of Equity, or by a voluntary Covenant: That which is due the latter way, if the Covenant be conditional; the Oath that is to ratifie it, may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſo far conditional, but what is due in the former kind, to wit, by abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and unalterable rule, or precept of Juſtice, cannot be ſworn to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally; for that would be no ratification to it, nay it would be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitating, and rendering more inſecure of that which was ſimply due without an oath, a condition being put into your oath, being a very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable <hi>medium</hi> to perſwade the ſwearer that he is no otherwayes bound to the things ſworn, then upon that Condition; which being broken by that party ſworn to, he will eaſily conceive himſelf altogether free: Thus the abſolute Rule will receive impeachment, and not ſtrength in its obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the conditional oath: ſuch an oath therefore is in its end inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with it.</p>
            <p>2 I come to the latter part of his Major which exacteth, <hi>That the Oath be mutual, or taken both by Ruler, and Ruled; not ſingle, or taken only by the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</hi> Some explanation of his terms, more then is here he might have uſed; for lack whereof I ſhall as I go obſerve ſome difference of ſenſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165675:9"/> appliable to his words, and ſo expreſſe how I deny this branch of his Poſition, and why.</p>
            <p>1 His words ſound, as if he would have the ſame oath to be taken mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually both by Prince and Subject, which (if he remember that the oath ſpoken of, is the oath of a Subjects Allegiance, obedience, or ſubjection to be yeelded to his Sovereign, and that the King is the perſon ſworn to) he will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, cannot I ſuppoſe, own to be his ſenſe.</p>
            <p>2 But the apter ſenſe, and that which I ſuppoſe was in his intention, is, That the Ruler and Subject ſhould each ſwear to his reſpective duty; the Prince, That he will Command and Govern lawfully: the Subject, That he will perform all lawful homage, and obedience: And to this I ſay, Although it be true, it in fact, in our caſe, that the King hath ſworn his duty on his part, as well as the Subject doth in this oath ſwear his, yet the Propoſition is falſe in this, and it cannot be ſaid, That thus it univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally ought of neceſſity to be betwixt every Prince &amp; his Subjects, much leſſe can it hold that, unleſſe it be thus mutual, the Subjects oath is not in righteouſneſſe according to Jer. 4. 2. but that for want of this mutua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity it is null. For,</p>
            <p>1 We read of many undoubtedly righteous Oaths in Scripture, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in Covenant betwix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s man and man, wherein one party only ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and not both mutually, Gen 24. 2. 47. 31. Exod. 13. 19. Joſh. 2. 12. 9. 15. 14. 9 Judg. 15. 12. 1 Sam. 19. 6. 1 King. 1. 13. 29. 51. 2 Sam. 19. 23. Neh. 5. 12. Jer. 38. 16.</p>
            <p>2 We find in Scripture, Oaths of Allegiance taken by Subjects to their Rulers, without the reciprocal ſwearing of the Rulers to them <note n="‡" place="margin">2 King. 11. 4. Judg. 11. 10. Ch. 36. 13 Ez. 17. 3.</note>; ſuch was that engagement, Joſh. 1. 16, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>3 Oaths are never to be taken but neceſſarily, that is, When not only the matter is of great weight, but it cannot otherwiſe be ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed or aſſured then by Oath <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Sanderſ. <hi>de</hi> Juram. <hi>ob. prael. 7. §. 12. Thol. ſynt. jur. l. 50. c. 3.</hi>
               </note>, but in ſolemn humane Covenants it comes to paſſe that ſometimes the performance lies only on one party, the other is to receive advantage, but not to do any thing: Sometimes the danger of breach lies only, or more on one part then on another: Sometimes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re is other ſatisfactory aſſurance given beſides ſwearing: and ſometimes there is other remedy, if there ſhould be a breach, then the forfeiture of an Oath: In ſuch, and other caſes, an Oath on the one party may no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> need, and conſequently is not to be exacted.</p>
            <p>4 But ſuppoſe the caſe, that it be as neceſſary for ſecurity that the King ſwear to the people, as that they take an oath to him, yet if through over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much credulity, or otherwiſe it be that the people do ſwear, and not the Prince, this cannot be the leaſt colour for the nullifying of the peoples Oath: For whether the King Swear or no, that which makes the Oath obliging, is, That in a juſt and poſſible matter promiſed, God is invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated as a witneſſe of the promiſe.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:165675:9"/>
            <p>3 There is another ſenſe of mutual ſwearing more ſtrict then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and that is, when not only two parties ſwear to each other their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective parts, but they both ſwear with a mutual reſpect; that is, The obligation of the one party, hath a reſpct to, and a dependance on the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the other party: as when one man ſwears to another to give him ſo much Money for his Land; that other ſwears to convey to him his Land for ſo much Money; in this kind, the breach of the one is a releaſment to the other. And here that Adage holds good,</p>
            <p>
               <q>Frangenti fidem, fides frangatur eidem;</q> And alſo that Rule of the Law, <q>Fruſtra qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fidem poſtulat ſibi ſervari ab eo, cui fidem à ſe praeſtitam ſervare recuſat.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But this ſenſe of mutual ſwearing cannot come in to be meant in our caſe: For, 1 Such an oath is plainly conditional; The one party ſwears not to give the other abſolutly, and cleerly ſo much Money, but to give him ſo much for his Land; the having of the Land then is an expreſſe condition of his oath: but the oath of the Subjects Allegiance is granted to be abſolute, and is as ſuch diſputed againſt by him here; and I have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e proved an oath of Allegiance cannot be Conditional. 2 The Kings cath is alſo abſolute, and binds without dependence on the Subjects loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; no man wil ſay (I think) that the King is diſcharged from ruling juſtly, and may become an abſolute Tyrant, if his Subjects exceed the bounds, or fail of the bonds of their oath, or duty: nay, if the Subject tranſgreſſe his duty, the King is bound by his oath to cauſe Juſtice accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law and Tenor of his Oath, to be done; and cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe eſcape violation of his Oath. 3 Such mutual oathes are entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by both parties at the ſame time, and have their mutual reſpects ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, but neither doth the King and Subjects ſwear to each other at the ſame time; neither is there any ſuch mutual reſpect mentioned, or ſo much as implyed in either of their Oathes. 4 Such mutually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective oathes have only place in matters arbitrary, or that are in mens choice to do, or not to do until they bind themſelves by Covenant, but ſuch are not the relative duties of Kings and Subjects, there being a divine Law obliging each to the Duties of their Offices before they ſwear.</p>
            <p>We ſee no ſenſe imaginable of <hi>Mutual not Single</hi> wil fit this mans turn, but it wil make his Propoſition falſe, either if predicated of the oath of Allegiance at al; So doth the Firſt, and Third acception afore mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; or if predicated with that <hi>modus</hi> of a <hi>neceſſe eſt,</hi> ſo doth the Second. But let us hear his Reaſon for this clauſe of his Major whatever be the ſenſe of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>againſt Equitie and Reaſon, and the good of the Subject, that he ſhould be further, or longer bound to the Prince to ſubmit to him, then the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165675:10"/> Prince is bound to the Subject to Rule wel, and adminiſter juſtice rightlie.</hi> Grant al this, and it wil no way follow; <hi>Therefore the Oath of Allegiance to make it righteous muſt be mutual,</hi> in any ſenſe: for the Prince may be bound, and that as long to his part, as the Subject is to his, (and ſo he is, and it is impoſſible to be otherwiſe for Prince and Subject; his tye to Rule in Juſtice, and his to Obey in juſt things are relatives, and do infer neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily each other) to wit, by the tye of Scripture, Conſcience, and poſitive Laws, and yet not be ſworn at al.</p>
            <p>His Major being thus (I hope) fully Refuted, I need not to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his Conſequences, as he cals them, but in a word I ſhal touch on them.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is nothing but a Hypothetical Repetition of ſome part of the Major Propoſition, which I have been ſo long in diſproving: <hi>If the Oath of Allegiance were in judgement and righteouſneſſe, the King was as ſtronglie bound to the Subjects, as any of them to him:</hi> This therefore I paſſe by, as the ſame that was ſaid before, and no Conſequence from it.</p>
            <p>The Second is, <hi>Then if he break his Oath, al the Subjects are abſolved if they wil.</hi> This Conſequence I deny: I have I think, fully made it cleer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, That the Oath of Allegiance taken by the Subject is abſolute, not depending upon any thing to be performed by the King, whether ſworn, or not ſworn; and that it could not have been otherwiſe. And though the King and People have each ſworn their duties mutually, yet not with<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Doct.</hi> Sanderſ. <hi>de</hi> Juram. <hi>ob. prael.</hi> 4. §. 8.</note> a mutual reſpect, by vertue whereof a breach on one ſide might be a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge on the other, and that neither the tenor of their Oaths hold forth any ſuch thing, neither is the matter of them capable thereof, being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, not arbitrary.</p>
            <p>The Third is, <hi>Then at what time the King Levied War againſt his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, they were diſcharged by that breach of Oath in him of their Allegiance.</hi> This is a Conſequence of the former Conſequence, and ſtands or fals with it: That therefore being Anſwered and Diſproved, this vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth.</p>
            <p>The Fourth thing is no Conſequence, but a Reaſon of the two laſt Conſequences, and in method of arguing is therefore an antecedent to prove them, it is thus, <hi>Elſe the whole Parliament and their partie were perjured perſons, ſo manie of them as have taken this Oath, and are Rebels in taking up Armes againſt the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> If their taking up of Arms againſt the King (as he terms it) were Rebellion, their abſolution from their Oathes (were it ſo indeed) by the Kings breach of his, could not unmake, or make it no Rebellion; for the debt of Obedience is exiſtent in the Subject before any Oath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and it is not founded on ſwearing, but only confirmed by it, and therefore ſurvives after the pretended diſſolution of it; and conſequently makes that taking up of Armes which would have been (if the Oath
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165675:10"/> had not been (as he ſuppoſeth) nullified) Rebellion neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We muſt therefore ſay, as the Parliamentarian party hath beleeved, declared, and in many Treatiſes in Print, maintained al along the late Wars, That the Armes of the Parliament were not againſt any brance of the Subjects Allegiance, or the Oath for it (which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed ſtil to perſiſt in, yea, and in the act of their Armes bearing, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted to yeeld and maintain) but concordant with the ſame. In as much as they enterprized not againſt the Kings Perſon, his State, or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they went not againſt his Majeſty, his Heirs, or Succeſſors, they joyned not againſt his Crown and Dignity, the Rights whereof, and the Bounds of the Subjects Obedience, are prefixed by the Lawes of the Realm, the ultimate interpretation whereof, is in the Parliament which declared their Arms to be for, and agreeable to the Laws. The King, as King, acts only by his Courts and Laws, what he doth beſides, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe, is the mans, not the Kings acting. What is done by Order of the Courts of Juſtice, and by vertue of the Laws, is done (though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his perſonal preſence or command, yet) for the King, his Crown, and Dignity.</p>
            <p>2 His next Exception againſt the Oath of Allegiance is, That it is an unlawful Oath, in that it is ſworn to the Kings Heirs: His Reaſon for this Exception proceeds thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who knoweth</hi> (as Eccleſ. 2. 19.) <hi>whether he will be a wiſe man, or a fool; a juſt, or a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ricked man, and Tyrant? Now if no man know this, then to ſwear to an Heir, is not an Oath in judgment, nor is it righteous: for the Subject may bind himſelf to his own hurt, yea ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſequence. <hi>Then the Oath of Allegiance was in that branch, that reſpected Heirs, an unlawful Oath, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>I admit of the Antecedent, but utterly deny the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</q>
            <p>1 For the whole Conſequence, I Anſwer;</p>
            <p>1 This inference is directly contrary to that which <hi>Solomon</hi> in the place cited, Eccleſ. 2. 19. makes from the words. <hi>Solomons</hi> is, <hi>Yet ſhall he have Rule over all my labours wherein I have laboured, and wherein I have ſhewed my ſelf wiſe under the Sun.</hi> This mans inference is (in effect) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man knows whether he wil be a wiſe man, or a fool; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhal not have Rule, &amp;c. that is, We muſt not Engage before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand that he ſhal Rule, while it is uncertain what he wil prove: though <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, Notwithſtanding that is uncertain, yet he ſhal have Rule.</p>
            <p>2 The ſame Reaſon (if it held) would lie againſt any Oath, or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to any Rulers in being whatſoever they are; for ſay they be come to maturity, and for the paſt and preſent time have given proof;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165675:11"/> yet who knows what they that are now wiſe, and juſt (morally) may hereafter come to be? The Scripture ſuppoſeth, That not only a juſt Father may have a wicked Son, but a righteous man (in profeſſion and external carriage) may turn from his righteouſneſſe, and commit ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, Ezek. 18. 24. <hi>Neroes Quinqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnium</hi> of Reigning wel is generally known, the good beginnings of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſh,</hi> and <hi>Vzziah,</hi> 2 Chron. 23, 24, and 26. and therefore degeneracies are ſufficient inſtances of the lubricity of men in authority. Yea it is wel known how fearfully <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf with <hi>Aſa,</hi> 1 King. 11. 2 Chron 16. and others, fel in divers particulars of a groſſe nature; if we muſt firſt know, and ſwear afterwards, we muſt never ſwear to any promiſſorily.</p>
            <p>3 This Conſequence (were it of force) would equally condemn in general al promiſſory Oathes, and other Covenants, and Engagements, betwixt man, and man; for it cannot be fore-ſeen in any, what the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons contracted with wil prove; or whether the Covenant wil be bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial, ot hurtful; and in particular, the Laws and Sanctions of thoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in al ages, which have ſettled ſucceſſive Regality, or any other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or longer then the preſent poſſeſſors of the power endure, which yet is a way, not only more generally approved, and practiſed, then any other of viciſſitudinary Election, but warranted by the word of God. <hi>Iſrael</hi> offered a ſucceſſive power to <hi>Gideon,</hi> Judg. 8. 22. and God himſelf inſtituted, and bound the People to a lineal Government in <hi>David</hi> and his ſeed, 2 Sam. 12. 15. 2 Chron. 13. 5. The Patriarchal power (which was political) was ſucceſſive, and could not have been caſt off at pleaſure: ſo was the Government of the Jewiſh Nation, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r about an hundred yeers in the lineage of the <hi>Macca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4 We have Scripture examples (of an uncontroverted integrity) of Oathes, and Engagements to Princes and their Heirs; and to Princes in their yong, unripe, and untryed yeers: Take for inſtance that of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſwearing to <hi>Abimelech</hi> King of Gerar, his Son, and Sons Son, 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 23. 29. 22. 29. 1. 22 5. &amp; that of <hi>Davids</hi> making <hi>Solomon</hi> King in his own life time, and engaging the people to him when he was yet yong and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and that of JEHOJADAHS, and the Peoples making <hi>Ioaſh</hi> King, and ſwearing to him when he was but ſeven yeers old, 2 King. 11. 4. 22.</p>
            <p>2 For the two parts of the CONSEQUENCE in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>The Oath is not in judgment, becauſe no man knows what the Heir will prove.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, 1 It may be in Judgment ſo far as a future contigency can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberated on: and this may be concluded on adviſedly (as morally cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain) that it's better to have the Crown ſettled in a line, whereby ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a vicious perſon may be advanced, then to have it under Election
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165675:11"/> at every perſonal change. This hath been the experimented maxime of the wiſeſt States <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Minore diſcrimine ſumi prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip. m qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quaeri.</hi> Tacit. <hi>H. lib. 2.</hi>
               </note>. 2 If it were not in Judgment, this defect makes not an oath Unlawful, as to the nullifying of it. A raſh oath, if of a lawful thing binds (Judg. 21. 7. 15. 1 Sam. 14. 24. 37. Joſh. 9. 14. 15. as before was proved.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Nor is it a righteous Oath, for the Subject may bind himſelf to his own hurt, yea ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Though the Subject may not bind himſelf to what is neceſſarily, or at the time of his ſwearing may appear probably to tend to his hurt, or ruine, yet he may ſwear (intending the publick good) to that which is of a mutual nature, and may in the event turn to his own hurt, and ruine; and might he not ſo ſwear, yet having ſo ſworn, he is bound to ſtand to his Oath, Pſal. 15. 4. Ioſh. 9. 15. Ezek. 17. 13. 1 Sam. 14. 26. 28. 37. Judg. 21. 5. 15. 18. which is contradictory to what this man here ſaith.</p>
            <p>2 If the Heir ſhould miſprove, his power is bounded by the Law, and commixed with the Parliaments: If he vary, the power of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Laws and Liberties of the Subject are the ſame. The late King confeſſed and declared a remedy againſt Tyranny to reſide in the Parliament; there may be a prevention then of the Subjects ruine (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Heir prove) if the KINGDOME be faithful to it ſelf.</p>
            <p>3 His Third Exception againſt the Oath as unlawful, and void, is, <hi>That it is to uphold one kind of Government for continuance, and in a conſtant way without changing.</hi> His Argument to make good this Exception, proceeds thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If of the ſeveral kinds of Government, all are not equally good, nor ſutable to all People: And man may change the Government he is under for his own greateſt good and benefit, and muſt change it when he hath proved any kind of Government inconvenient and hurtful, and muſt not uphold any one kind of Government longer then it continues to be moſt ſafe and profitable; then to ſwear to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold any one Government continually and conſtantly, and not to change it, is ſinful; and in Righteouſneſs and Judgment may not be done. But of the ſeveral kinds of Government, all are not equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good, nor ſutable to all people, and man may change the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he is under for his own greateſt good and benefit, and muſt change it, when he hath proved any kind of Government inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and hurtful; and muſt not uphold any one kind of Government longer then it continues to be moſt ſafe and profitable.</hi> Ergo,</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:165675:12"/>
            <p>For Anſwer hereunto,</p>
            <p>Firſt, I obſerve there is a fault to be found with the whole Argument, as ſomewhat tranſgreſſing the rules of arguing.</p>
            <p>1 In the Conſequence there is ſomething of the error called <hi>Ignoratio Elenchi;</hi> for we ſwear not in the Oath of Allegiance, indefinitly or inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminatly as his words import, to uphold one Government continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not to change.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We ſwear only to <hi>His Majeſty, his Heirs, and Succeſſors:</hi> ſo that when ever they are al extinct, (which may be ſooner or later, as divine Providence diſpoſeth) the Oath of it ſelf ceaſeth and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Notwithſtanding the Allegiance ſworn to the ſaid perſons, their Crown and Dignity, there is power of change in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment left to the mutual conſent of both parties; to wit, Thoſe ſworn to, and them ſwearing, as it is in al humane Contracts and Oaths<note place="margin">Alſ. Theol. Caſ. C. 15. Reg. 2.</note> of this nature ‡.</p>
            <p>2 In the Minor there is ſomewhat of the fallacy called <hi>petitio principii,</hi> namely, That any kind of Government, granted to be lawful, can prove inconvenient and hurtful to the Subjects. The Governors indeed may prove bad and noxious, and ſo the Government comes to be abuſed; but a perniciouſneſſe cannot therefore be charged upon the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelf, nor can that be a neceſſary ground for the change of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: if ſo, you wil bring in a ground for endleſſe Mutations; a change in the perſons, or a regulating of them, is the apt remedy for that hurt: but the Government, the abſtract or eſſence of the thing, never can prove hurtful, becauſe it is an Ordinance of God for mans good, Rom. 13. 12. 4. and that <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> as afterwards wil be ſhewed, and as a Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernment it hath a political goodneſſe ſeated in its being, by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable Law of Nature.</p>
            <p>Secondly, But admit the Argument were not peccant in form, yet the Aſſumption in the main of it, which is, <hi>That man may change the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he is under for his own greateſt good, and muſt change it when he hath proved anie Government inconvenient and hurtful, and muſt not uphold anie one Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment longer then it continues moſt ſafe and profitable;</hi> I muſt flatly deny. What Poſition more Anarchical could be delivered? For the diſproof, I offer thus,</p>
            <p>1 He ſaith, <hi>Man may change the Government, &amp;c.</hi> but the holy Ghoſt ſaith, Prov. 24. 21. <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change:</hi> He alloweth <hi>a change to be for greater good;</hi> but the holy Ghoſt tels us in the next words, Verſ. 22. <hi>For their Calamitie ſhall riſe ſuddenlie, and who knoweth the Ruine of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 If men may change for the better, and muſt change upon a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165675:12"/> hurt, then all Oathes, Engagements, or Promiſes of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Allegiance, or Fidelity to Magiſtrates, are unlawful to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken; for al ſuch Bonds, are in relation to a preſent, and particular Government, the Engagers are under: And they are not for the time preſent, or for an inſtant, but for a future Continuance. And there is in al ſuch Engagements, a making over of the Right which the Enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers have in the matter Covenanted, to the perſons Engaged to; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that known Rule, <hi>Omne promiſſum cadit in debitum:</hi> either then ſuch a change to be made by the perſons under Authority may not, muſt not be; or ſuch Engagements may not, muſt not be by them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken: The former imports a power and duty inherent in the Subjects to reſerve in themſelves a liberty to alter, and to practiſe it when they judge it convenient: The latter ſpeaks a binding out from any ſuch deed, and an abandoning of any ſuch Right; but the Scripture is cleer enough for ſuch Engagements, Eccleſ. 8. 2. 2 King. 11. 4. Joſh. 1. 16, 17, 18 Judg. 8. 9, 10. 2 Chron. 36. 13.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This Poſition not only diſalows all ſuch Engagements, but diſſolves the natural, or moral bond it ſelf of duty, and ſubjection to Magiſtrates, for to be free to change when a man judgeth it beſt, is to be free when he wil, and that is not to be tyed at al; by this means any man is diſingaged from ſubjection, both in <hi>foro interno, &amp; externo,</hi> when he wil ſay, He thinks the preſent Government not ſafe or profitable, or another to be better; and having ſo reſolved, he is abſolved: He may now diſobey the Commands, ſtand our againſt the Judgements, take up Arms againſt the Perſon and Authority, and be exempt from the Sword of the Magiſtrate: yea, although he have ſworn, or ſubſcribed Allegiance: becauſe ſuch an Oath, or Promiſe (ſaith this Doctor) was ſinful, not in righteouſneſſe: But I would fain have him declare, What thing Magiſtracy, and what Subjection is.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This Doctrine wil acquit, and juſtifie al the Conſpiracies, and Treaſons, that ever were enterprized againſt the power of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ſince the World was. Was not the Conſpiracy of <hi>Abſolem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Kin. 11 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 12. 1. &amp;c. Act. 5. 36.</note> and that of <hi>Sheba</hi> againſt <hi>David?</hi> Was not the Rebellion of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Solomon,</hi> and <hi>Rehoboam?</hi> Were not the Seditions of <hi>Thendas</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> the Gaulonite againſt <hi>Caeſar?</hi> Were not al the Treaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt MAGISTRACY that ever have been, attempted for the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rties (yea for the Publique) greater good, as the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors judged?</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, That not particular men or a leſſe party are to judge the expediency, and take in hand the change, but the whole people. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, the people under Authority collectively taken have no ſuch power (as I intend preſently to ſhew) it may be ſaid.</p>
            <p>1 Seldome or never doth a whole Nation under a lawful Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165675:13"/> of themſelves affect or move to a change, it is the flatterers, and deceivers of the people ‡ ordinarily that deſire and miſlead the people to<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ariſt. <hi>poli. lib. 5. c. 5.</hi>
               </note> it.</p>
            <p>2 How the Judgement and Will of the whole Body of a People ſhould be known and declared unto Execution before particular men act to a change of their own private judgement, to me is a thing unimagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, This neceſſity of retaining a power in Subjects to change, and of uſing it for a greater good, or removal of a temporal hurt, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to an Oath ſworn againſt that change, is directly againſt the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, tying men, that ſwear to their own hurt, not to change, Pſal. 15. 4. Joſh. 9. 18, 19. and condemning thoſe that for ſuch ends have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded from their Oathes, Ezek. 17. 13, &amp;c. Joſh. 9. 15. compared with 2 Sam. 21. 2.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, That Poſition ſo much now adayes inſiſted on of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Power to depoſe, aboliſh, and alter the power of their Governors at pleaſure, which is actually ſetled, and both in it ſelf lawful, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſet over them, I hold is a groſſe error.</p>
            <p>Some of my Reaſons in ſhort are,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Such a courſe (ſuppoſing the Governors Diſſent to it al a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long) is no other then that reſiſtance of the Ordinance of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, Rom. 13. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is directly oppoſite to that Subjection commanded e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Soul that is in the relation of a Subject, Rom. 13. 1. and that 2 Pet. 2. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If the People may do it, then it muſt needs be that they have a Civil power and authority over their Magiſtrates; which is contrary to thoſe Scriptures which make the King Supream, and cal the power which the people are ſubject to, The higher Powers; higher in relation to them, who are below, and put in ſubjection to them, 1 Pet. 2. 13. Rom. 13. 1. And indeed, if the People have a power over their Magiſtrates to judge, or diſplace them, How are the Magiſtrates their Superiors, and Rulers? The ſame perſons cannot be under, and over others in the ſame kind of order or power. If the Magiſtrates be under the People, whom are they over? If the People be above the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, whom are they under?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The holy Ghoſt commands the People to render Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, Cuſtome, Fear, Honor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (not at random to a Magiſtracy lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them at liberty to what they pleaſe, but) to whom they are due; they are a debt then, which reſpecteth a determinate object, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Magiſtrate. No Debtor can pay a Debt by transfering it from one to another, or giving what he oweth to another beſides the proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:165675:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Magiſtrares are of God, his Ordinance and Miniſters, and they are Judges for him as his Vicegerents, Rom. 13. 1, 2. 4. 2 Chr. 19. 6. and therefore cannot ſtand at the meer wil of the People. God muſt have a hand in their removal, as he hath in their admiſſion; or elſe it is injurious: he removes, and admits now, but not by immediate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation (as ſometimes in Iſrael) but by the rule of his Word, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by man, He hath given a Rule for the ſetting up of Magiſtrates, but where hath he given any for their depoſing?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly.</hi> If it were in the Peoples power to change at pleaſure their Magiſtracy, then how could it be ſuch a heinous ſin as it is challenged to be for the people to reject <hi>Samuels</hi> Government, and deſire and mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e for a King, 1 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 6, 7, 8. 12. 17?</p>
            <p>But let us next <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear what he alledgeth for this his Aſſertion of Muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
            <p>He ſaith, <hi>Though Civil Government in general be an Ordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce of God tending to mans good, therefore to reject it would be ſinful, yet this or that kind of Government is not an Ordinance of God, but an Ordinance of man,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 13. <hi>and if an Ordinance of man, then man may change it, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Civil Government in the general cannot be ſaid to be Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and therefore unrejectable; but this, or that kind of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is a legitimate &amp; true <hi>ſpecies</hi> of it, muſt neceſſarily be yeelded to be alſo Gods Ordinance, and unrejectable; for it is a ſure rule, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is directly and <hi>per ſe</hi> ſaid of the <hi>genus,</hi> or general nature, muſt be alſo ſaid of the <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar kind: And again, the whole nature of the <hi>genus,</hi> or general, is conteined in every <hi>Species,</hi> or kind <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quicquid predicatur de praedicato praedicetur de ſubjecto,</hi> Reg. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Tota natura generis continetur in una quaque ſpecie.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>2 The Apoſtle cannot be taken to ſpeak of power in general only, and abſtractly, but muſt be underſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d diſtributively of al lawful powers in their ſpecial kinds: When he ſaith, <hi>There is no power but of God; the powers that be, are ordained of God: whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the power, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the Ordinance of God,</hi> Rom. 13. 1, 2. He that ſhal ſay of this or that kind of lawful Government, as of Monarchy, it is not of God, it is not the Ordinance of God; ſpeaks direct contradictories to the holy Ghoſt here. No Subjects obedience, to this or that Government he is under, could be urged upon him by vertue of this reaſon, <hi>There is no power but of God, &amp;c,</hi> if this, or that kind of Government were not of God, and were not his Ordinances.</p>
            <p>3 And for his diſcretive, <hi>but an Ordinance of man,</hi> it is no inference of the former, therefore not the Ordinance of God. For this, or that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, is both an ordinance of God in <hi>Pauls</hi> ſtile, and an ordinance
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165675:14"/> of man in <hi>Peters;</hi> and you cannot ſay theſe two Apoſtles ſpeak of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in two different wayes; the former in general, the latter in particular: for as I have proved, <hi>Paul</hi> muſt be taken of particular kinds. So it is cleer, <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks firſt in general, <hi>Submit your ſelves to everie Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of man, &amp;c.</hi> and then in particular, <hi>Whether it be to the King as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, or unto Governors, &amp;c.</hi> this, or that Government, <hi>Paul</hi> cals an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In that it is inſtituted in its ſpecial nature by God, and warranted for any people, but not commanded or impoſed (as Government in the general is) upon every Nation. For it is with Governments in relation to Nations, as with Callings, in relation to Perſons: every man muſt have a Calling, but it is diſtribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ively this, or that, or the other; al are not neceſſarily to have this one, 1 Cor. 7. 7. 17.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In that it is inveſted in the particular perſons by God, when they are called to the Government according to his Rule, though he doth not point them out immediatly by his own finger, but immediatly by men. In like manner as they are the Miniſters of Chriſt in the Church that are Called according to his appointment, though men in the ſame office ordain them And in this regard, the Magiſtrates (not the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment abſtractly) are called Gods Ordinance, Rom. 13. 2. compared with 3, and 4. <hi>Peter</hi> terms it mans ordinance, either becauſe both the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al form of Government, and the perſons holding it are choſen, and ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly Conſtituted by men. Or rather becauſe it is converſant about humane affairs, and mans benefit. Not as if it were invented by, and had its original from men, for ſo it is of God. As Expoſitors interpret and compare that place of <hi>Peter</hi> with the other of <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <note n="‡" place="margin">Beza. Marlor. <hi>Divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Annotat. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>odat.</hi>
               </note> And that <hi>Peter</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes not, but taketh in the divine authoriration to that Government he treats of, is evident; in that he willeth ſubmiſſion to it, <hi>for the Lords ſake.</hi> How for his ſake, if it be not his Ordinance?</p>
            <p>Having thus anſwered the Premiſes of his Sylogiſm, and what he brings to back the Aſſumption withal. His Conſequence or Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion following goes to the ground, and the lawfulneſſe of the oath of Allegiance remains unſhaken. But he, as his manner is, amplifies his Conſequence with matters altogether inconſequential, and independant on the Premiſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 He ſaith, <hi>Who knoweth not what a plague this kind of Government</hi> (viz. <hi>Kinglie) hath been to this Nation? And that the moſt of our Kings have been Tyrants?</hi> I am one that knows not theſe things, but judge the contrary, and wil be tryed by the Experience, and Voice of this Nation. And in the mean while, I requeſt him to try theſe his words by the Scriptures following, 2 Pet. 2. 10, 11, 12. Jude 8, 9, 10. And to take heed of the Verdict, and Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gement therein given upon Government<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſphemers.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:165675:14"/>2 <hi>Who knows not what a Bleſſing the Change of Government hath brought to the Vnited Provinces?</hi> I am ſure this man knows not, neither can ſay, If thoſe Provinces excel in Bleſſings, that they are brought by a Change of their lawful Government, conſidering what <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerved of old, Eccleſ. 8. 14. 9. 1, 2. concerning the diſproportion of Wordly ſucceſs to mens wayes; and the inevidence of the goodneſſe, or badneſſe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and actions if eſtimated by events. Which every mans experience can ſecond.</p>
            <p>Whether thoſe Provinees have changed or recovered their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; or whether they yet ſtand but as our Parliament did with the late King in the firſt War, defending, and demanding the Security of their juſt Priviledges with the Sword in their hand, I leave him further to conſider: and I aſſure him this, There have been obſervations great ſtore of Gods Judgements up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that have rebelled againſt, caſt off, or murdered their lawful Governors gathered by worthy men <note n="‡" place="margin">Theatre of Gods judgments by D. Beard and Doct. Taylor, lib. 2. chap. 2, 3, 4, 5.</note>. But I never before met with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that made obſervations of divine bleſſings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any of thoſe acts.</p>
            <p>Thus far his EXCEPTIONS by way of proof of his firſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition goes.</p>
            <p>He in the cloſe makes one Objection againſt himſelf, and gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es his Anſwer to it thus;</p>
            <p>Objection. <hi>Suppoſe there was ſome unlawfulneſs in the taking ſuch Oathes, yet is there not a neceſſitie of keeping them being taken?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwer. <hi>If</hi> Herods <hi>Oath againſt the life of one man, being unrighteous and cruel, was ſinfullie taken, and more ſinfullie kept, then theſe of Allegiance which are abſolute, not Conditional, &amp;c. and which are to uphold Monarchie, the woful fruits whereof ſeeing they are dangerous, and may prove, as often they have done, deſtructive to the lives of manie men; they are not onlie unlawful to be taken, but to be kept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not granting any unlawfulneſſe in the taking of this Oath, having (I hope) made good its innocency againſt al that hath been ſaid; yet ſuppoſe I had made this Objection, I would not take this Anſwer. My Reaſon is,</p>
            <p>He cannot paralel <hi>Herods</hi> Oath and ours in the matter wherein <hi>Herods</hi> was unlawful both in the taking and keeping. What was that? to ſhed innocent bloud, to maſſacre a guiltleſſe and holy Perſon. What was ours? To yeeld obedience in lawful things, to a lawful power. Is it any more? and are not the matters of theſe two Oathes as far unlike as light and darkneſſe? That which he heaps np to aggra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e our O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to the height of the unrighteouſneſſe of <hi>Herods,</hi> is nothing but the three ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions which al this while I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e been Anſwering, and therefore ſhal
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165675:15"/> content myſelf with what hath been ſaid to them; only in the cloſe, he tels us,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monarchy is dangerous, and may, as often it hath, prove deſtructive to the lives of many men, and therefore its unlawful to ſwear, or keep the upholding of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is nothing but what may be as truly ſaid of any kind of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how lawful ſoever: none that hath been as much practiſed as it, can be affirmed to have been leſſe deſtructive<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to be leſſe dangerous then it. But the poſſiblity of being, or experience of having been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, is no valid Reaſon why a Government may not be upheld; (if it be, down muſt al Governments fal) and if yet it may be upheld, to ſwear to uphold it, may be an Oath lawful for the matter; and if it cannot in that reſpect be made a Crime, it deſerves not to be paraleld with <hi>Herods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Oath. What paralel in point of unrighteouſnes <hi>Herods</hi> keeping his oath, and others violating theirs; his execution, and theirs, may have; it is not to my pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poſe in hand to ſhew.</p>
            <p>I have done with his Firſt Poſition, and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceed to his Second, which is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suppoſe the Oath of Allegiance to be Lawful, yet the Subject is now abſolved from it by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m that have power to abſolve from it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Poſition of a power in any to abſolve from a lawful Oath is new (as far as I have read, or heard) among Proteſtants, and hath until now been accounted by Papiſts, the Popes and Prelates Prerogative; by us, their Anti-chriſtian preſumption.</p>
            <p>But let us ſee where, and upon what ground he builds ſuch a power:</p>
            <p>Reaſon. <hi>Becauſe Repreſentatives of the People, which in reaſon are the Supream power, impoſed this Oath by an Act of Parliament, this was the Subjects free Act in their Repreſentatives, no Law of God or Nature obliging them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of ſuch a Perſon, and his Heirs, and to ſwear Allegiance to them. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Repreſentatives take away, and repeal this Act (as this Parliament hath done) they thereby ſet the Subjects at libertie from ſuch Allegiance, and from their Oath binding to it, there remains no more Conſcience of it to ſuch as have taken it:</hi> Abraham <hi>that impoſed the Oath upon his Servant, might acquit him of it, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, For the Antecedent, I ſhal only note;</p>
            <p>1 He ſets up a Supream power over us by Reaſon, not by Law, or the Peoples Conſtitution: and this Reaſon is not the Nations, but, 1 Either his own private judgement, and if that may create a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m power to him, then every ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er private mans Reaſon is to ſet up one to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even where there is one already, over the people he is of. 2 Or it is the Common Reaſon that is in all men naturally: and if ſo, how comes it to paſſe, That there is ſo much variety of Kinds of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:165675:15"/> Government, and that Repreſentatives have it not in all times and Nations; yea that ſcarce they ever had it?</p>
            <p>2 That in citing the power that Enacted this Oath, he omits the King, and Houſe or Lords, who in the then Parliament concu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in this Enacting, and Impoſition.</p>
            <p>3 That although the King then was rightſully and actually Enthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Regal power and Dignity, and both the Law, and the Oath of Supremacy obliged the people to him and his Heirs; yet he dares to ſay, <hi>No Law of God, or Nature, obliged them to accept of ſuch a Perſon and his Heirs.</hi> Is not the Fifth Commandement the Law of God, and Nature? and thoſe Precepts, Rom. 13. 1. Tit. 3. 1. 1 Pet. 2. 13. Repe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ions, and divine Ratifications thereof? And doth not that Law command every people and perſon Allegiance to their particular lawful Governors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and was not the King in Being, his Heirs in Capacity, and deſignaton ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, But for the Conſequent there is no Truth in it, nor colour of Reaſon; or inference from the Anteceden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for it. Beſides, That the act cannot (for ought appears to me) be Repealed, but by the ſame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer that made it: and the Allegiance ſworn was not founded upon the Act or Oath, but due, and paid before them both. The Oath in its own words terms it ſelf a Recognition and Acknowledgement; and the firſt words of it are,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>Do trulie and ſincerelie acknowledge, profeſs, teſtifie, and declare in my Conſcience before God and the World, That King</hi> James <hi>is lawful King of this Realm, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe the Repreſentatives to be the Supream power, that the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of this Oath was their Sole Act, and the Subjects in them, and that they did it voluntarily or unobliged to it: doth it thence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. The Repreſentatives repealing that Act, the Subjects that upon their Enacting ſwore it, are now abſolved from their Allegiance, and from the Oath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>1 They that have power to impoſe an Oath were never ſaid (many Divintty extant) to have power <hi>eo ipſo</hi> to abſolve from it, when the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers are alſo the party ſworn to, there it is granted (both by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant<note place="margin">‡ <hi>Doct. Sanderſ. de juram. oblig. prael. 7. §. 8. Theoloſ Syntag. juris, l. 50. c. 12.</hi>
               </note> and Papiſts ‡) they have po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to releaſe from the Oath, not becauſe they are the impoſers, but becauſe they are the party ſworn to, for <hi>omnis qui promittit ſacit jus alteri, cui eſt facta promiſſio,</hi> the right of the thing ſworn is theirs to whom the Oath is made, and therefore they may releaſe from it; and this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e true ground of that power he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth in <hi>Abraham</hi> to acquit his Servant, not his being the impoſer of his Oath: but where the impoſers are a Third party from the perſons ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165675:16"/> and ſworn to, there they have no claim of power of Relaxation. And thus the caſe is here, The Repreſentatives (as he faith) impoſe the Oath, which is ſworn to the King, and bind in Allegiance to him. If they that impoſe an Oath, may Releaſe from it, then may any Court or Magiſtrate Releaſe a Juror or Examinate from the Oath they have gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en him; then it a man impoſe an Oath upon himſelf (as in ſome caſes he may) he may abſolve himſelf when he wil from it, though he therein obliged himſelf to God, or another man. And this is truly the caſe here, as he himſelf ſtates it; The Subjects by their own act in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives impoſe this Oath, and by their own perſonal act ſwear i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and after by their own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctin their Repreſentatives abſolve themſelves i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>2 The Repeal of the act, is no Repeal or diſſolution of the Oath; the Parliament that framed, and by their act impoſed the Oath, did not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by make it an Oath, but it was the Subjects ſwearing which made it an Oath, and an Obligation or Religion to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as the Miniſters rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and dictating the words of Marriage to the Couple Marrying each other, makes not the Marriage, but the parties themſelves declaring in thoſe words. And as the Clerk in a Court reciting the words of a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Oath to him makes not the Oath, but the Jurors aſſent to it. The Parliament can conjoyn, or puniſh the refuſal, or manifeſt breach of an Oath. But a promiſſory Oath being the act and Covenant of him that ſwears, and a part of divine Worſhip, the bond of Conſcience upon the ſwearer, and the validity of Gods Ordinance, and the Obligation that is therein entred into unto God, as the invocated witneſſe, and judge, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be within the Parliaments authority to nullifie in al Subjects Oathes which may be made with, or without their impoſition. There are caſes indeed, wherein a ſuperior, as a Husband, Maſter, Father, Magiſtrate, may make void the Oath of their reſpective inferior by ANALOGY, or equity of that Rule, <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. but thoſe are, 1 In matters that are belonging to the Right, or Power of the Superior to diſpoſe of; as the Repreſentatives may acquit from an Oath in point of their owne Right <note n="‡" place="margin">Animadvertendum tamen eſt penes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os non eſſe facultatem reſcindendi quod libet jus jurandum ſubditorum ſed illud duntaxat cujus materia eſt eorum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> poteſtati ſubjecta. Alſted. Theol. Caſ. Cap. 15. Reg. 2.</note> But the Allegiance in this Oath ſworn is none of theirs, but the Kings, and therefore ſworn to him by the Subjects, and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular by them. 2 By that Law <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. the Superior may inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to nullifie his Inferiors Oath made without his knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and that muſt be done in the day that he hears of it; but there is no further power given by that Law in the matter of Oathes. Now in this our Caſe, the Repreſentatives have been ſo far from being ignorant of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:165675:16"/> the making of this Oath, and diſalowing it as ſoon as it was know to them, that they were the Compoſers and Commanders of it; yea, and have taken it themſelves. Let any the leaſt Warrant, yea or Preſident be brought for Releaſing an Oath in this Caſe, and I ſhal ſit down.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, For a Cloſe of my Anſwer unto this Poſition, I ſhal obſerve what the Tenor of this Oath hath in it:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I do beleeve, and in Conſcience am reſolved, That neither the Pope, nor any Perſon whatſoever hath power to abſolve me of this Oath, or any part thereof. And do renounce all Pardons and Diſpenſations to the contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is not the Swearers Declaration only, but the Parliaments in Compiling, and Impoſing this Oath, and al Repreſentatives have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally thus declared in taking it. Shal we beleeve them concerning their power in this matter, or this man?</p>
            <p>That which follows is no proof of the Poſition, nor any thing to the validity of the Oath.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="reply">
            <pb facs="tcp:165675:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165675:17"/>
            <head>A REPLY <hi>TO AN</hi> ANSVVER Pretending to Refute ſome POSITIONS <hi>Which tended to make the</hi> OATH <hi>of</hi> ALLEGIANCE <hi>Void, and not Obliging.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Anſwerer begins with the Drift of the Firſt Poſition, which he ſaith is, <hi>To ſhew the Oath to be unlawful in the taking of</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The Drift of the Firſt Poſition is to ſhew the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs of the Oath upon a Suppoſition, that the Oath was Abſolute and not Conditional, that it was Single and not Mutual, &amp;c. and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe.</p>
            <p>He falls upon Premiſing ſomething in theſe words: <hi>An Oath may be</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>unlawful, 1 Either in regard of the matter or thing ſworn, as when it is ſome ſinful act: Or, 2 In regard of the manner, as when the thing is unadviſedly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165675:18"/> ſworn: The former way of unlawfulneſs makes the Oath Void in the taking of it, but not the latter: which appears by the validity of that unadviſed Oath of the Princes to the Gibeonites,</hi> Joſh. 9. 15. 18, 19. 2 Sam. 21. 2.</p>
            <p>He erreth at the firſt daſh; That Oath of the Princes was a ſinful Oath <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply. </seg>
               </label> in the matter of it, becauſe expreſly againſt the command of God, <hi>Deut. 7. 2. Exod.</hi> 23. 32. yet it was not void, but was kept by them.</p>
            <p>He falls upon Obſerving, and ſpeaks of <hi>A groſs imputation</hi> that is laid <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> upon very many Worthies of all ſorts and kinds of men, as if they had preſſed, taken, and juſtified an Oath in the matter of it unjuſt and ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul.</p>
            <p>If there be any Charge at all upon any, it is upon thoſe that make the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply. </seg>
               </label> Oath to be Abſolute and not Conditional, &amp;c. But if any perſon hold otherwiſe, that it was a Mutual Conditional Oath that was taken when Allegiance was ſworn, then there is <hi>no imputation</hi> at all upon one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which the Author of the Poſition rather conceives then the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>He mentioneth the general Exception againſt the lawfulneſſe of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Oath, and Objects againſt it in that branch of it that reſpects Judgment, and ſaith, That Defectiveneſſe in that will not invalidate the Oath, <hi>It is but a fault</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the manner, not in the matter; in the Perſon, not in the Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be ſo, Whence is it that the Law provides, That no Vows, Oaths, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply. </seg>
               </label> Deeds, or Acts that are done by perſons in their Nonage (becauſe it is ſuppoſed they are not done in Judgment) ſhall ſtand, but be all invalid, unleſſe ratified afterwards when they come to age. This man (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he be) ſpeaks againſt the Law herein, which is more groſſe then to ſpeak againſt perſons. Notwithſtanding it muſt not be conceived, That the Author of the Poſitions doth intend, That every oath that is defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in judgement, is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> void; but he connects Judgement and Righteouſneſſe together, as adding ſtrength to each other, and making ſuch an oath ſo unlawful, as not to be obligatory.</p>
            <p>He deſcends to particulars, and objects againſt that Conditionality <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> which in the Poſition is made neceſſary unto an oath, that it may agree with Jer. 4. 2. And he diſtinguiſheth in theſe words: <hi>I conceive the words (Conditional and Abſolute) may be taken, 1 Either in reference to the thing ſworn, which is Obedience or Allegiance to the King; and ſo the Condition is, it muſt be Honeſt; Or, 2 In reference to the Tye or Obligation of the Oath:</hi> And of this latter, he makes another diſtinction concerning Conditions, in theſe words: <hi>Some Conditions are general, and ſuch as no promiſory Oath that is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful can be without:</hi> And he makes (Honeſt) this general Condition. 2ly. <hi>Others are ſpecial and proper Conditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He makes, <hi>Honeſt and Iuſt,</hi> to fall under the oppoſite members of his <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply. </seg>
               </label> own diſtinction, and ſo confounds that which he would diſtinguiſh.</p>
            <p>He comes to oppugn the Reaſon, that is brought in the Poſition, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:165675:18"/> the Oath muſt not be Abſolute, but Conditional, <hi>viz. That it is againſt the Ground and Reaſon of the Primitive Inſtitution of Government, which is the good of the Subject, that there ſhould be any Oath to bind him abſolutly whether the Prince Rule for the Subjects good or not.</hi> And his firſt Exception is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That this Reaſon wants proof.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
            </p>
            <p>There was ſuch cleerneſſe in the Reaſon, that it needed not proof. For <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply. </seg>
               </label> if an abſolute Vaſſalage (with firſt or laſt will infallibly be the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of an abſolute Oath) be not for the good of the Subject, and ſo not ſutable to the Primitive Inſtitution of Government, then an abſolute oath cannot be for the good of the Subject, and ſo not ſutable to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Inſtitution of Government.</p>
            <p>His Second Exception is, The Reflection that this Argument in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Poſition would have upon the Parliament (ſhould it be granted to be true) who Enacted the Oath of Allegiance, and all ſubſequent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments confirmed it, which if it were not for the good of the Subject, would call their wiſdom and goodneſſe into queſtion.</p>
            <p>There is ſomething inſerted in this, that is not granted, <hi>viz</hi> That the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply. </seg>
               </label> Parliament intended this Oath to be Abſolute, without implying in it ſo much as this Condition, <hi>While the Prince ſhould rule according to the Laws of the Kingdom.</hi> For, 1 They never declared ſo much, That they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the oath to be abſolute. 2 The Oaths that Kings in this Nation have alwayes taken, ſhew the contrary, and their Oaths to him muſt be interpreted by his Oath to them: Now his Oath to them is, To Rule according to the Laws of the Kingdom, therefore their Oath to him muſt have the ſame reſtriction, and ſo cannot be abſolute. 3 The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is ſharer (at leaſt) by this mans own confeſſion, pag 5. with the Prince in Government. For, he ſaith, It is a mixed Government that is amongſt us in this Nation; and in a mixed Government, the Prince hath his ſhare; and the People, in their Repreſentatives, have their ſhare; therefore the Parliament would never make the Oath abſolute, leaſt thereby they ſhould give away to the Prince that part in Government which is theirs. 4 It was to recover this ſhare in Government, and the Peoples Liberties thereby out of the hand of the Prince, that this WAR was undertaken againſt him. Which if they had never Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioned with the Prince for, in their Oath to him, (neither expreſly, nor implicitly) had not been juſtifiable upon this mans Aſſertion, That an abſolute Oath is lawful.</p>
            <p>His third Exception is ſetcht from Experience, <hi>His words are,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It hath conſiſted with the publick good (yea contributed to it, or elſe the Papiſts would not have ſo oppoſed it) from the time it was firſt ſet forth, until now, and no complaint at all hath been heard againſt it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill now.</p>
            <p>1 It had been neceſſary that he ſhould have ſhewed what good it <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply. </seg>
               </label>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:165675:19"/> hath contributed to it, and how it hath been conſiſtent with it, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as abſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, as now he and many more do underſtand it, and hold themſelves ſtill obliged by it.</p>
            <p>2 The Papiſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad reaſon to oppoſe it, becauſe it was given out to be intended principally (if not ſolely) againſt them. And their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in reference to their Religion (which ſubjected them to a forreign power) tell juſtly under ſuſpition, to engage them therefore more firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Prinee, this oath was contrived and Enacted.</p>
            <p>3 Many precions conſcientious men were long ſince (much more then Papiſts) offended at it, foreſeeing that there would be a great ſnare in it, as it was urged without an explication, Yea, It was preſſed more upon them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then upon the Papiſts; and the Papiſts (moſt of them) knew how to get off from it, and to avoid it, but not they. When the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution was ſo ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt <hi>Inconformiſts</hi> that many thouſands were forced to fly the Land; then was there a command, That all Ports and Havens ſhould be narrowly looked unto, that none might be ſuffered to paſſe out of the Nation, till they had firſt taken this Oath; and my ſelf hardly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped at that time.</p>
            <p>4 It might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave proved fatal to this Nation, had this Parliament underſtood it as this man doth in an abſolute ſenſe, and not according to the Laws of the Land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For then had the Deſign of the late King and his Father (to make themſelves abſolute Mona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chs, and to bring the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into an abſolute ſubjection to their arbitrary Government) been accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, and there had been no place ſo much as for a Defenſive War, but abſolute ſlaves the Kingdom muſt have been, as they were ſeveral yeers before this Parliament ſate.</p>
            <p>He comes to diſtinguiſh of things that are againſt the peoples good; and, <hi>ſaith he,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That ſome things are againſt the peoples good in their own nature, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> other things accidentally<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſaith, That any thing almoſt that falls under a Political conſideration may be againſt the peoples good in the latter Conſideration though unlawful, and for the preſent, probably (yea neceſſarily) for the peoples good: and of this ſort (I ſuppoſe) he makes this abſolute oath of Allegiance to be. It is but by accident that it proves hurtful, but it is good in it ſelf.</p>
            <p>He might and muſt diſtinguiſh of things accidentall; ſome things are <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply. </seg>
               </label> accidental in reference to the time when, and yet ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ain that they will be, in reference to the Cauſes whence they come, and the Courſe of Gods Providence: other things are ſo accidental, as that it is contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, whether they will be at all. Chriſt ſpeaks of offences, That it is neceſſary that they ſhould come: and the Apoſtle of Hereſies, That there muſt be Hereſies, and yet both the one and the other are acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, in reference to the perſons by whom, and the time in which they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165675:19"/> ſhould come: So it is in Common-wealths, there are many things that are againſt the good of the people, which though accidental in reference to the perſons and time, yet certain and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>allible, in reference to the Cauſes, and the courſe of Gods Providence; and when there is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion againſt ſuch evils, but rather a door ſet open for them, by either perſons or things done, 'tis againſt the good of the people, becauſe all knowing men may eaſily foreſee ſuch things, though they cannot ſo pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually diſcern the times and ſeaſons of them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall give ſome inſtances: Wars, are things accidental, yet certain, at one time or another; and that Government that provides not againſt it, but rather invites it by ſecurity and negligence, is againſt the good of the people, and ought to be either redreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, or removed: Murthers, Rapes, Fellonies in a Common-wealth are accidental, yet they will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be, and thoſe States-men, and L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>giſla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors that provide not againſt them, are againſt the good of the people.</p>
            <p>There may be Inſtances of other kinds: Wolves amongſt the Flock are accidental, yet they will be, and thoſe Shepherds that provide not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, by feeding the Church of God with wholſome ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, are againſt the good of the Flock. Storms and Tempeſts at Sea are accidental, yet they will certainly come; and thoſe Ship-maſters and Marriners that go to Sea without good Tacking, they are againſt the good of their Principals, and thoſe that fraught them, and againſt their own lives alſo. And ſo it is with Tyrants in Government, they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental in a Common-wealth, yet it is certain ſuch there will be, ſince ſo great corruption ſell upon mankind, and thoſe Oath-impoſers, and Oathes that are impoſed, that provide not againſt ſuch, but rather invite and ſet open a door to Governors to be ſuch, are againſt the good of the Common-wealth, and people; and ſuch is that Oath of Allegiance, if it be abſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and not conditional, as this man would have it.</p>
            <p>2 He diſtinguiſheth again of the goodneſſe of the End, and of the means tending to that End; and he makes the happineſſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity to be the goodneſſe of the End; and this to be intended and not deliberated on, or choſen by the Law-gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers. The means he makes va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable, in relation to times and people, and ſaith. That that may be good in the nature of a means, for one people or time, that is not good for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I allow of the Diſtinction in the former branch of it fully, and ſay with him, That the happineſſe of the Community is the goodneſſe of the End. And I ad this, <hi>That the juſt freedom o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Subject is the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Communitie, which an abſolute Oath of ALLEGIANCE fights againſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I alſo concur with him in the ſecond branch of the Diſtinction of the goodneſſe of the means, that it is that which falls under Deliberation and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165675:20"/> Counſel: but that all means is variable and changable after Counſel hath found it out, I deny: For the goodneſſe of the means may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered Generally, or Specifically. Conſider it in its general nature, and it admits not of any ſuch variation according to times and places: but conſider it in its ſpecial nature, and then it may admit of variation. For Example, Government in general, is a good of the means, reſpecting the happineſſe of the Community, and yet is neceſſary for all Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, that they may be happy: but this, or that ſpecial kind of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis not necſſary for all Communities, in all places and at all times, but there may be ſome change and variation. So to Govern according to Laws, and to obey according to Laws, is neceſſary, and admitts of no variation, becauſe it conduceth abſolutly to the good of the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: but to govern and obey according to the ſame Laws, is not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but variable, according to places and times.</p>
            <p>Unto this head of the goodneſſe of means conducing to ſuch an End, <hi>viz.</hi> The happineſſe of the Community, he makes a firm Sanction by an abſolute Oath (that there may be a kind of immutability in States and Governments thereby) to appertain. And ſaith, It is the wiſdom of moſt States ſo to ſetle them, to prevent the danger of Innovation and changes. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e makes this to be a better means of the Communities happineſſe, then the other of Conditional parts and Covenants with the Prince. For he ſpeaks of the evil of ſwearing to a Prince abſolutly, to be but incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, diſadvantagiouſneſſe, prejudice, outward incommodity, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment of the Subjects good: but the evils of a Conditional, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abſolute Engagement, he ſpeaks of them, as Miſchief and Miſery: and when the other is in his accompt but uncertain danger, he makes this inevitable hurt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> If all this be true, then the Conſtitution of our State, was not ſo prudently conſidered by our fore-Fathers, when they Eſtabliſhed a mixt Government, as might have been; and ſo much expence of Bloud to recover the Subjects Liberty and Propriety, was a great ſin. For it had been better for the Subject (if he have ſaid truth) to have yeelded themſelves up to the Will of their Prince, to have ſubmitted quietly to an arbritrary power, and to have borne an Iron yoke for ever, then to have contended with him: and our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> did ill to give us ſuch an Example as firſt to appear in Arms againſt him: But rational men muſt firſt put out their eyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> before they can beleeve ſuch a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox. For can there be a greater Miſchief and Miſery, then thraldom and ſlavery? then loſſe of Religion, Liberty, Propriety, Life it ſelf? For all theſe will lie at ſtake, and be hazarded, by an abſolute Oath firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept and obſerved. War with all the effects of it that can follow ſuch conditional Engagements, is but a ſhort Miſery, and not ſo ignominious as the other, for perſons live and die like men in it; but in the other,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165675:20"/> they live and die like beaſts, and all their life is but a long-lived death. But many in theſe dayes, are like the Iſraelites, who when in bondage and under <hi>Pharoahs</hi> yoke, cryed to God, and ſighed and groaned, and then it was a condition intollerable; but when they were delivered and ſaw War, and found ſome evils they expected not, then they judged it better to be in Egyptagain: and then the ſtate of cruel Servitude was but an inconvenience in compariſon of the other Miſchief. But let the miſchief of a Conditional Engagement be what it will, it muſt be choſen, and the abſolute muſt be avoided, becauſe Liberty, and Propriety, &amp;c. are the happineſſe of a Community, and the end of Government, and the birth-right of all the Subjects which have not forfeited it, and ought not to be given away to the will of the Governor, and a Conditional En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement is the means to preſerve it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He ſaith,</hi> Such things as may by reaſon of their changeable nature prove in the iſſue ſomewhat diſadvantagious, may yet, if for the preſent good, and probably hopeful ſo to continue, be ſworn to abſolutly, as in voluntary Promiſes, Leagues, and Contracts, both publike and private, among all Nations hath been the practiſe, and by good Scripture-preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent it is juſtified, <note n="‡" place="margin">Gen. 47. 31. Exod. 13. 19. Joſh. 9. 15 14 9 Judg. 21. 5. 18. 15. 12. 13. 1 Sam. 14. 24. 19. 6. 20. 12. 17 1 King. 1. 13. 29. 2 Sam. 19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 23.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 Allegiance (which is the thing that he would have abſolut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſworn unto) may not only prove through the changable nature diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious, but alſo hath, and doth often, and will certainly at one time or other prove pernicious, not to perſons only, but to Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths.</p>
            <p>2 An abſolute Contract of Allegiance, ſets up the Prince too high, and puts down the Subject too low: The one is made by ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract more then a man, the other is rendered leſſe then a man, and more like unto a Beaſt. And it is neither for the preſent good, nor hopeful to continue ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to put ſuch a diſtance betwixt them. For abſolute Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty is Gods Prerogative, whoſe Will is perfectly holy, and juſt, and good, and not to be attributed to the Creature, ſo full of imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and corruption; and it layes a temptation before him to miſcarry in his Office.</p>
            <p>3 Some voluntary Promiſes and Contracts are <hi>diſſimilia,</hi> things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, holding no proportion to the thing in Controverſie, <hi>viz.</hi> To the Oath of Allegiance, the abſolutneſſe whereof is by him Aſſerted, and the Inſtances or Examples in Scripture carry not any kind of Analogy. Let them be pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſed, and rational men will wonder, that ever they were produced. 1 Some of them, are not Oaths made to men at all, but to God, as that in Judg. 21. 5. 18. and ſome others. 2 Others of them are Oathes, the performanee whereof lies only on one Party; the other is to receive advantage, but to do nothing, as that in Gen. 47, 31. Exod. 13. 19. Joſh. 9. 15. &amp; 14. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3 Others of them were Oathes of things, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165675:21"/> were in their nature pernicious and ſinful to be ſworn to, as that in 1 Sam. 14. 24. <hi>Ionathan</hi> ſpeaks of it, That his Father had troubled <hi>Iſrael</hi> and hindred the Lords Work by that Oath of not touching any food till evening. And when <hi>Saul</hi> would have had <hi>Ionathan</hi> put to death in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his violation of that Oath, the people reſcued him, and did well in it. And there is none that comes ſo neer the caſe, as <hi>Ionathans</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Oath, which was not abſolute, but conditional, ſo as that if the one had broken it, the other would have been abſolv'd upon it. But this Oath of Allegiance is an Oath betwixt perſons, that owe reſpective du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to each other, and the Obligation of the one, hath a reſpect unto, and a dependance on the performance of the other; and ſo is an Oath of another kind, then thoſe mentioned in his Scriptures, and cannot be abſolute, as he from theſe patterns would prove.</p>
            <q>But he gives his <hi>Reaſons,</hi> why abſolute Allegiance doth not ſo neerly and probably tend to the Subjects hurt, as the Conditional doth.</q>
            <p>1, <hi>He ſaith,</hi> The Prince may prove juſt and vertuous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 The Conditional Engagement is the beſt way to make him prove ſuch, when he Rules upon his good Behaviour, he is more likely to Rule well. 2 Moſt Princes prove not ſuch but unjuſt and vitious. 3 To be left to his own arbitrary Will in Governing, is like to prove a temptation and ſnare to him. A lawleſſe Liberty to do what he liſteth many times corrupteth the Prince.</p>
            <p>2, <hi>He ſaith,</hi> If he degenerates, the Subjects are bound to obey him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, but in lawful things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> What then? If the Oath be abſolute, they are bound to obey him paſſively in all other things, wherein they cannot obey him active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, even to the loſſe of Life, Limb, Liberty, and Eſtate, which will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly bring calamity enough upon them. Nor were the Children of Iſrael bound to obey <hi>Pharaoh</hi> actively, ſave only in lawful things; and yet they were miſerable enough for all that. And the Condition of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject may be no better then the Condition of Gally-ſlaves, if this be all the comfort that the Subject hath, that he is bound to obey actively but in lawful things,</p>
            <p>3, <hi>Heſaith,</hi> In his lawleſs Acts there may be a remedy (as the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or reſiſtance of his bad inſtruments by the Parliament, without whom, though he may Will unjuſt things, yet he cannot Execute them) and yet his Government be continued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 What Juſtice is in this, To reſiſt, and puniſh his bad Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and not him who is the principal efficient? For if they be in fault, he that ſets them on work much rather. And uſually it hath been ſaid, <hi>The Meſſenger bears no blame,</hi> but if there be a fault, his it is that ſent him, and certainly the Servant is in leſſe fault. 2 This reſiſting of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165675:21"/> bad Inſtruments, is a reſiſting of him, as Chriſt ſpeaks to his Apoſtles whom he ſent forth, <hi>He that receiveth you, receiveth me; and he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth you, deſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeth me:</hi> So it may be ſaid of Reſiſting, in reference to the Inſtruments of the Prince, He that puniſheth, or reſiſteth them, pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſheth and reſiſteth him in them; and this is abſolutly againſt the Oath of abſolute Allegiance. 3 This reſiſting and puniſhing of the Princes Inſtruments, is as unſafe and dangerous, as the not continuing of his Government when it is degenerated to Tyranny; for it will inevitably bring on a War betwixt the Prince and People: For the Prinee, if he be able, will maintain his Inſtruments in what he ſetteth them about, and vindicate their Cauſe, while they do nothing but what they have his authority for; and this is the evil that this man declines ſo much, that to prevent it, he pleads for an abſolute Engagement, whatever the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief be to the Subject; and yet in this place he brings this in as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to prevent the danger of the other. 4 This Remedy begins at the wrong end, goes not the next way, but far about to work redreſſe, and reacheth not the end, nor effects any cure; for a corrupt Prince will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver want bad Inſtruments, his greatneſſe will have a corrupting influence upon thoſe about him; and like Prince, like Officers and Servants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him. But let the Prince be fettered by wholſome Laws, tending to his own juſt Honor, and the Subjects juſt Freedom, and the Miſchief will not only be redreſſed, but might be pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ented, and with leſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>azard alſo. 5 The Parliament are Subjects, in this mans account, as well as other men; and therefore by his Aſſertion, muſt be abſolutly engaged to the Prince; and wherein they cannot obey actively, they are bound to obey paſſively, and therefore may not actively appear againſt his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in his Inſtruments, for where is then Allegiance, which an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Oath will alwayes bind too?</p>
            <p>4, <hi>He ſaith,</hi> And ſuppoſe the caſe that there be no remedy, as when he hath got a party ſtronger then can be reſiſted, or ſubjected to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then to caſt off his power and depoſe him (ſuppoſe it lawful to do) will be no relief, his ſtrength will command ſubjection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 The way to prevent the getting of this ſtrong Party, is to keep the Subject from the ſnare of abſolute Oathes, and to let them know their Liberty, and that their Allegiance is but Conditional. 2 Concerning depoſing (if an abſolute Oath be once taken, and be lawful both to be taken, and kept when taken) it cannot be lawful; no nor yet the putting of his Perſon into hazard by War, pretended to be underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt his Miniſters and Servants under him. 3 When the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject hath a juſt Cauſe to contend for; <hi>viz.</hi> For Covenanted Rights, they may caſt themſelves upon God; for God hath made it to appear, not by Might, nor by Arms, but by his Spirit, great things have been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:165675:22"/>
            <p>5, <hi>He ſaith,</hi> The miſcarriages of a Prince ordinarily extend but to the detriment of ſome particular perſons, rarely doth any <hi>Nero</hi>-like, ſeek the deſtruction of the whole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 Let the Declarations which have been ſet forth by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (when both Houſes ſate, and were moſt full) be viewed, and it will appear, That the Miſchiefs and Miſeries that came by the corrupt Mind and Will of the Prince, were general, and reached the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: What can be ſaid of Ship-money, and multiplicity of Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies? Did they not, one way or other, reach all? Were ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſons only annoyed by them? 2 If at firſt few be like <hi>Nero,</hi> to ſeek the deſtruction of the whole; yet being croſſed, and thereby incenſed and vexed, if it come to a publick Conteſtation, almoſt every one will chuſe to deſtroy all, rather then to miſſe of their Will, and fall ſhort of their Deſign.</p>
            <p>6, <hi>He ſaith,</hi> In that caſe Subjects ſworn, and unſworn, (if their Cauſe be good, and the Parliament authorize their ſtanding up) are in the ſame capacity of Reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 Not ſo, if their Oath be abſolute and obligatory, (as this man will have it) for an abſolute obligatory Oath to obey actively or paſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yet a capacity of Reſiſtance (if the Parliament warrant it) are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory one to the other. 2 Nor can the Parliament authorize it, if themſelves have abſolutly, and irrevokably, and lawfully alſo ſworn Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, and in ſuch ſort alſo impoſed it upon the Subject.</p>
            <p>7, <hi>He ſaith,</hi> Set the people free to ſhake off the reins of their preſent Government, when they ſhall think it unequal, and, 1 You deſtroy the nature of Government; and, 2 You expoſe the people to an immediate loſſe of the very uſe and enjoyment of any Government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 The People act all in, and by their Repreſentatives, who are ſo wiſe and faithful to the Common-wealth, that they wil not ſleightly ſhake off the preſent Government; but when it is to preſerve the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, after they have had long patience, and plentiful experience that there is little hope of good whilſt it ſtands, much leſſe wil they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Common-wealth to be without a Government, and to lie in Confuſion; the proof of both which we have had amongſt our ſelves. 2 How the change of Government ſhould be againſt the nature of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, I cannot apprehend; and he ſhewes no Reaſon for it</p>
            <p>What is ſpoken by him, in way of Compariſon, betwixt a bad Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and no Government; betwixt one, or a few, doing that which is right in their own eyes; and every mans doing ſo, the one he makes an accidental effect of abſolute Allegiance; the other he makes an inevitable effect of conditional Allegiance, becauſe they be naked unconfirmed Aſſertions, and experience amongſt our ſelves hath ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently confuted them, I ſhal therefore paſſe over them.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:165675:22"/>
            <p>Afterwards in the Second place he layes down a contradictory Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in theſe words, <hi>The Oath of Allegiance may be Abſolute, or unconditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal:</hi> And he renders <hi>Reaſons</hi> for it:</p>
            <p>1 <hi>He ſaith,</hi> Were there no Oath, the limitted obedience which is due to Princes and Magiſtrates, is due to them abſolutly, whether they Rule well, or no; and that which is abſolutly due, may be abſolutly ſworn.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This is only true while they acknowledge them to be their <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> and do continue them in thoſe Offices and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and it is as true of every Conſtable, what miſdemeanour ſoever he be guilty of, yet he muſt have that obſervance of his Place from all, while in his Place: But the Queſtion is, When Princes and Magiſtrates Rule amiſſe, not to the welfare, but ruine of the people over whom they are Magiſtrates, Whether the People be not (in that caſe) abſolved from al Tye and Obligation to them, as Magiſtrates, if they will: that is, Whether the Repreſentatives of the People, which have the Peoples power, for the Executive part of it, may not if they wil, (yea, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Caſes are bound in faithfulneſſe to the People, and for their good, to) declare ſuch Princes and Magiſtrates, in reference to ſuch miſcari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, to be no longer Governors, and ſo therein to free the People from their Allegiance to them. And it is aſſerted in the Poſition, That they may if they wil. A Paſtor of a Church miſcarries in the execution of his Office, and becomes a Wolf to devour, rather then a Paſtor to feed the Church of Chriſt, Is not his Flock notwithſtanding bound to obey him in the Lord, and according to Rule, whileſt he remains a Paſtor to them? But the Queſtion is, Whether it be not the Duty of ſuch where the Power is, To Depoſe him from his Office, and therein to abſolve the People from ſuch Duty as ſuch an Office cals for? And ſo it is in this Caſe of a Prince or Paſtor to a Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>But he Confirms this <hi>REASON,</hi> by Seven other <hi>Reaſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. The Precept of Obedience to Civil Governors, is without any condition or reſerve from a diſingagement of the Subject in caſe of the Governors miſcarriage, reade the 5th Commandement, and thoſe other Injunctions, Rom. 13. 1, 2, &amp;c. Tit 3. 1. 1 Pet. 1. 13. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> It is to be underſtood whileſt they are Governors, and whileſt they are Fathers: and the ſame may be ſpoken of Paſtors of Churches, for they are Fathers; and there is no reſerve for a diſingagement from duty towards ſuch, whileſt the office of ſuch laſts. But the Queſtion is, Whether there be no Reſerve for a diſingagement from the Office it ſelf, and the Relation in reference to that Office, as it reſpects ſuch a perſon who hath miſcarried in it? If that be aſſerted, the Fifth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wil not prove it, not thoſe places quoted. For there are Two ſorts of Fathers included in that Commandement; there is a Natural Father,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165675:23"/> whoſe relations is indiſſolvable, what ever the miſcarrying be: and there is an Inſtituted Father, which originally the People both in Church and Common-wealth were wont to create, for the Common good of them all. And ſuch a Father as the People make, or their Elders, or Patriots for them, the People may lay aſide; or their Repreſentatives on their behalf, upon miſdemeanors in Government, the relation in this Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is not indiſſolvable; and thoſe Scriptures quoted, contradict not this; For it is known wel, That in thoſe times there were great Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Chief Magiſtrate, which took off the People, and freed them from their duty, when their relation ceaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands his people to be ſubject to Heathen Princes, and the moſt abſolute and oppreſſive Tyrants that likely ever have been, Jer. 27. 12. Mat. 22. 21. 1 Pet. 2. 13. I ſpeak not here o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tyrants, in regard of Title, or Right; that is, Uſurpers: but of Tyrants whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itles a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e juſt, but their Government unjuſt, and oppreſſive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 But did God ever Command the Heads of the people, who had the power of al the people, to continue ſuch in their Places, if they had power to remove them? It is one thing what God Commands particular parſons to do, that have no Power no manner of way, and what the duty of the Chief of al the people (who repreſent them) is to do. 2 Were not thoſe very perſons many of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in Title, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel as in Government, concerning whom God Commands his People, That they ſhould be ſubject to them? Did not the Emperors advance themſelves by the power of their Armies that they commanded, to whom the Senate was forced to yeeld, and yet ſubjection is required whilſt they were in Place? What can be ſaid of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? Was his Title good, getting all by the Sword as he did? and yet Subjection is commanded to him, as his own quotation proves. So that it is manifeſt, That al the Scriptures which he produceth, are as ſtrong to prove that which he diſapproves of, as they are to prove that, which he would prove by them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. Servants are to be ſubject to their Maſters, not only to them that are good and gentle, but thoſe that are froward, and that do them wrong, 1 Pet. 2. 18, 19, 20. and by Analogy Subjects are tyed in the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erms to their Governors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Servants in thoſe dayes were ſuch who were bought with their Moneis, and were their Slaves, as now many Chriſtians are to the Turks; therefore in ſubjection they muſt be, both to the Good and Froward, and could not help themſelves; and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhorts them to be contented, and patient in their condition for the Lords ſake: But yet elſewhere he exhorts them, That if they could be free, they would chuſe it rather. Now I hope this mans ſcope is not, To put Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealthes into this Condition of Servility and Slavery to Princes. Nor
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165675:23"/> will he grant ſuch an abſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ute Dominion to Princes, as to Maſters over ſuch Servants. Such Servants were for their Maſters, when their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters had bought them: But Common-wealths are not for Princes, but Princes for Common-wealths; therefore there is no parity betwixt the one and the other. The ſubjection of Common-wealths, muſt not be a bondage, as the ſubjection of ſuch Servants was, unleſſe it be that ſom people have forfeited their freedom by ſome Rebellion, or wicked bloudy hoſtile acts, as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> have done. The yoke may be hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie on ſuch juſtly, and yet they have no cauſe to kick againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ. 4. David</hi> would not ſtretch out his hand againſt <hi>Saul</hi> upon this ground, for that he was his Maſter the King of Iſrael, and the Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, though he was then in actual, violent, and unjuſt purſuit of his life, 1 Sam. 24. 5, &amp;c. 26. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply. David</hi> at that time was but a private man, and <hi>Saul</hi> was King unqueſtioned by the Heads of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Sauls</hi> perſecution was but of one private mans life, it appears not that he was a Tyrant unto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. However it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ident that he was given of God immediatly, without the interpoſition of the people, and therefore it might be, that he muſt be taken away by God, though he had been a Tyrant. But what is this to Princes in theſe times, that have no ſuch immediate Cals to Kingdoms?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5. Otherwiſe you leave no place for paſſive obedience to, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for, and patience towards Magiſtrates in caſe of their wrong doing, and your own innocency, which yet is generally acknowledged to be a duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> There will be particular wrongs enough, to exerciſe the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of particular perſons, before it come to be miſcarriage againſt the Common-wealth: and there will be miſcarries enough through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and invigilancy againſt the Common-wealth which will exerciſe the patience of all the people, and yet at laſt, if the miſchief grow very high and threaten ruine; ſubjection is not ſo abſolute, but that the Heads of the people may free themſelves, and the people, from ſuch a yoke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 6. Els you diſſolve all Magiſtracy, it wil be impoſſible in mans cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt eſtate to retain or continue any, in as much as no man, or men, can in the vaſt multitude, and difficulty of Magiſtratical affairs avoid offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding every day, 2 Sam. 23. 3, 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> If the people themſelves were ſuch Ideots and Children as to expect a Government that ſhould be perfect, yet I hope it wil hardly be aſſerted of their choſen men, whom they make their Repreſentatives, that they are ſuch; and therefore I wonder that ever ſuch a Reaſon ſhould be produced. The High COURT where Wiſdome ſhould be ſeated (if any where) wil not run ſtark mad, to diſplace the Supream
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165675:24"/> Governor for infirmity and weakneſſe, which (as a man) he is incident unto every day, and ſo therein overthrow al Government: No, no, there hath been experience enough of their long ſuffering. But when a Prince to maintain his Luſt, wil raiſe a War, to endanger the deſtruction of al his Subjects; then let the REPRESENTATIVES of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple know their Priviledg and Duty, which is to ſerve the People, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it goes with the Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> The Doctrin of orthodox Proteſtant Divines generally is, That obedience is due (in lawful things) to the moſt degenerate, oppreſſing, and tyrannical Princes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Theſe orthodox Divines ſpeak of ſubjection of particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to ſuch Princes while they are in place and power; but they ſpeak not of States which are ſet up to be (at leaſt) ſharers in Government with the Prince. Nor do they preſſe obedience upon them, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny allowance to help themſelves, by calling him to an accompt in the peoples name.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>He ſaith,</hi> We find oaths of Allegiance in Scripture, ſworn to Princes without any Conditions inſerted, Judg. 11. 9, 10. 2 King. 11. 4. 2 Chron. 36. 13. Ezek. 17. 13. &amp; Nehem. 10. 29. Their Oath was to obſerve all the Commandements of the Lord, whereof the fifth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, with application to their preſent and future Magiſtrates, was one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 If there be no Condition inſerted, it wil not follow, That therefore there was no Condition; but the juſtice and equity of the thing is to be conſidered, whether i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth not require a Condition; and the Rules of general Equity are to be followed, which is conſonant to, yea, commanded in the Scripture, <hi>viz. To do, as one would be done unto.</hi> 2 The places quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, prove not the thing; That in <hi>Iudges,</hi> of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Oath to <hi>Iepthah</hi> may well be underſtood with this reſtriction, <hi>Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Laws of the Lord, and of the Land:</hi> for <hi>Iepthah</hi> was a Beleever, and a Judge whom God raiſed up; and it is probable, that he would not deſire Headſhip over them upon other terms. They were alſo an unfree people when they Covenanted with <hi>Iepthah</hi> to advance him to Government: and if their Oath were abſolute, they did not put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a worſe Condition thereby, but might think it better to be ſervants to him, then ſlaves to the <hi>Ammonites:</hi> and if it were an abſolute Rule which he had, he muſt Merrit it before he had it, and was to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their Saviour, before their Ruler: ſo that this Inſtance is not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to the thing in Controverſie. That place in 2 King. 11. 14. muſt be interpreted by Verſ. 17. where it is ſaid, That <hi>Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ada made a Covenant betwixt the King and the People,</hi> which implyes, that he mutually engaged them, and ſo it was not an abſolute Oath. That in 2 Chron. 36. 13. ſpeaks of <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> breach of oath, but nothing of any abſolute Oath.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165675:24"/> That in <hi>Ezek.</hi> may receive the ſame Anſwer with the former, becauſe it belongs to the ſame thing. That in <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> which reſpects the Obſervation of the Fifth Commandement, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th had its Anſwer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>3 <hi>He ſaith,</hi> It is a thing within our power to ſettle our Allegiance ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutly, as well as it is within a mans power to diſpoſe of himſelf to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, whether his Maſter prove good, or evil; or as it is in a man or womans power to beſtow themſelves in Marriage, whether the Mate be obſervant of duty, or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The Queſtion is not whether it be in our power to ſettle our Allegiance abſolutly, but whether it be in our lawful power to do it or no; and the doubt is not the leſſe in reference to theſe Inſtances which he produceth of a Servant his giving of himſelf up to his Maſter irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kably, whether good or bad; and of a Man or Woman giving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up in Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riage, whether the Mate be obſervant of duty or no, but the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er? For it perſons be bound to be wiſe, and juſt, and merciful to themſelves, then they cannot do ſuch a thing without ſin: and it would be counted a deſparate wicked part in a man, to bind himſelf to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to be ſervant for ever, whether he be kind or cruel; whether he give him any thing or nothing; yea, though he take from him that which he hath. And the unrighteouſneſſe of the thing is the ſame, in the caſe of an abſolute Oath to a Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>4 <hi>He ſaith,</hi> A conditional oath is not conſiſtent with a neceſſary duty; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to Magiſtrats is not left arbitrary, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, &amp; that though they be bad; but now the duty being neceſſary, if you would have it ſworn with a proviſo of the Rulers performing his duty, you nullifie the end of an Oath, which is to confirm, put out of doubt, and give ſecurity of what is due. A thing ſworn may become due, either by the rule of Equity, or by a voluntary Covenant: That which is due the latter way, if the Covenant be conditional<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Oath that is to ratifie it, may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſo far conditional, but what is due in the former kind, to wit, by abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and unalterable rule, or precept of Juſtice, cannot be ſworn to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally; for that would be no ratification to it, nay it would be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitating, and rendering more inſecure of that which was ſimply due without an oath, a condition put into your oath, being a very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable <hi>medium</hi> to perſwade the ſwearer that he is no otherwayes bound to the things ſworn, then upon that Condition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which being broken by the party ſworn to, he will eaſily conceive himſelf altogether free: Thus the abſolute Rule will receive impeachment, and not ſtrength in its obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the conditional oath: ſuch an oath therefore is in its end inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 This Reaſon is much like to the Firſt, and hath its Anſwer there: But, 2 It may be demanded, Whether obedience to Magiſtrates,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165675:25"/> be more neceſſary, or due by more abſolute unalterable Rule and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Juſtice, then obedience from Servants (which came free, and upon Covenant to their Maſters) is? If not, then, Whether obedience to Maſters may not (and ought not to) admit of a Conditional promiſe or oath to the performance of it, without any inconſiſtency with the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of ſuch a duty: and if, in the neceſſary obedience of Servants, ſuch a Conditional promiſe or oath may be admitted, Why not in the neceſſary obedience of Subjects to Magiſtrates? And, 3 It may be asked how, and when obedience to Magiſtrates came to be neceſſary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He wil not ſay, That before Magiſtrates were, obedience was neceſſary to them; but Magiſtrates, and obedience to them, came in together. But how came Magiſtracy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (I ſpeak of individual perſons put into the Office of Magiſtracy) Not by an immediate cal from God, as <hi>David</hi> did and ſome few others which Scripture mentioneth: nor were they (ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally) born to that ſuperiority over the people, but were firſt exalted to that power by the Choice of the People: then there was a voluntary Covenant at firſt betwixt them: then (if the people looked at their own good) the Covenant was Conditional, and ſo their Oath (which was to confirm it) was Conditional, and ſo their obedience (which is the thing ſworn to) was Conditional, and ſo it was neceſſary not otherwiſe but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Condition. And ſo it's commanded in Scripture, not otherwiſe but upon the Condition it was firſt grounded on, and in that way it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and unalterable, the Condition being obſerved upon which it was built and bottomed; and more then this cannot be inſerted by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Precept. And whereas he makes this diſtinction, <hi>A thing ſworn may become due either by rule of Equitie, or by a voluntary Covenant:</hi> It appears by what hath been preſented, That both members of the diſtinction without jarring meet in this. 1, There is a voluntary Covenant which is Conditional; and 2, There is a Rule of Equity neceſſitating upon that Covenant and Condition; ſo that obeying comes to be due both wayes. 4 A Conditional Oath doth not weaken, but ſtrengthen ſuch obedience which is neceſſary and unalterable upon ſuch a Condition. For the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate comes to be aſſured by ſuch an Oath, that he ſhall be obeyed, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his good behaviour, and juſt, and upright carriage in his Office, and that the people wil not be fickle to him, if he be faithful in Government to them. After his large diſpute againſt the Conditionality of the Oath, he proceeds to arguing againſt the Mutuality of it; and Firſt he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth ſo me of the words in the Propoſition, and blames them for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiveneſſe in point of cleerneſſe, in reference to the Senſe in which the Poſition is to be underſtood, and takes occaſion thereupon to ſpeak of different ſenſes, and gives one ſenſe which he ſuppoſeth will not be ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by me; and then an apter ſenſe, which he ſuppoſeth was in my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: For thus he ſpeaks;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:165675:25"/>1, His words ſound, as if he would have the ſame oath to be taken mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually both by Prince and Subjects, which he will not, cannot (I ſuppoſe) own to be his ſenſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2, But the apter ſenſe, and that which (I ſuppoſe) was in his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is, That the Ruler and Subject, ſhould each ſwear to his reſpective duty; the Prince, That he will Command and Govern lawfully: the Subject, That he will performe all lawful Homage, and Obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> And what needed ſo much ado? Was the Propoſition ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what defective in words? And was it not immediatly made full in the Reaſon which followed the Poſition? So that he needed not to have ſaid, For <hi>want of Explanation</hi> he muſt obſerve ſome different ſenſes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyable to my words; nor needed he to have ſaid, (<hi>I ſuppoſe</hi>) for he might have been at a certainty, what my ſenſe was; For my words in the Reaſon are theſe, <hi>It is againſt the good of the Subject that he ſhould be further, or longer bound to the Prince, or Ruler, to ſubmit to him, then the Prince or Ruler is bound to the Subject to Rule well, and to Adminiſter Iuſtice rightly.</hi> Let the Reader judge, whether he needed to have come with his diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſenſes: or, whether the different ſenſes that he brings were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyable to my words, when theſe words were before him.</p>
            <p>After he pretends to have found out the ſenſe of the Propoſition, he concludes it falſe. But how doth he make it out?</p>
            <p>1 <hi>He ſaith,</hi> We read of many undoubtedly righteous Oaths in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, undertaken in Covenants between men and men, wherein one party only ſweareth, and not both mutually, Gen. 24. 2. 47. 31. Exod. 13. 19. Joſh. 2. 12. 9. 15. 14. 9 Judg. 15. 12. 1 Sam. 19. 6. 1 King. 1. 13. 29. 51. 2 Sam. 19. 23. Neh. 5. 12. Jer. 38. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The Scriptures that he quotes to prove undoubtedly righteous ſingle Oaths, taken by one party, and not by both parties, are Oaths moſt of them of another kind then that which the Poſition ſpeaks of, <hi>viz.</hi> Oathes, the performance whereof lies only on one party, the other is to receive advantage, but not to do any thing: but the Oaths that the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion ſpeaks of to be Mutual, are of things and duties which both parties are equally with reſpect to their ſeveral places bound to by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God: For the Command to Obey, lies no more ſtricktly upon the Subject, then the Command to Rule, lies upon the Prince; and theſe Scriptures have been moſt of them Anſwered before: Only in Joſh. 2. 12. and Jer. 38. 16. the performance whereof lies on both ſides, and whether the Oath were reciprocal, is not ſo cleer; but conditional it was, as from Joſh. 2. 17, &amp;c. Jer. 38. 24. appears; and conditional in the very ſenſe I have urged: So as that they were diſcharged if the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition were not kept; and they aſſented to the Condition whether they ſwore, or not; and they are full againſt him as any text in Scripture.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>He ſaith,</hi> We find in Scripture, Oaths of Allegiance taken by Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165675:26"/> to the Rulers, without the reciprocal ſwearing of the Rulers to them <note n="‡" place="margin">2 King. 11. 4. Judg. 11. 10. Ch. 36. 13</note>; ſuch was that engagement, Joſh. 1. 16, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 To the Scriptures in the Margent, I have Anſwered before, yet this may be added, That if there be ſome examples of Oathes of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance without reciprocal ſwearing through over much credulity of the Subject, or becauſe in a neceſſitous condition, yet the equity and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the thing, <hi>viz. That the Oath ought to be reciprocal,</hi> is nothing leſſe by ſuch examples. 2 That in Joſh. 1. 16, 17, 18. which he ſeems to lay moſt weight upon, is rather againſt him then for him, for it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional as the laſt words in Verſ. 18. ſhew, <hi>Only</hi> (ſay they) <hi>be ſtrong and of good courage:</hi> It is as if they ſhould have ſaid, Upon this Condition we wil harken unto thee as unto <hi>Moſes</hi> before, if thou be ſuch as <hi>Moſes</hi> was, if thou be ſtrong and of a good courage to do the work of the Lord in thy Place and Office; they require as much from him in his Place, as they promiſed to him in their places: for there is not any thing ſpoken of an Oath, on either ſide.</p>
            <p>3 <hi>He ſaith,</hi> Oathes are never to be taken, but neceſſarily.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>When the matter is of great weight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Is there not as much neceſſity for the Prince to ſwear, as the People? Is not Ruling wel as weighty, if not much more weighty then Obeying? Hath not faithfulneſſe in Ruling, begotten Loyalty? Hath not a wiſe, juſt PRINCE, made an obedient, upright Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?</p>
            <p>2 <hi>When it cannot otherwiſe be ſufficientlie confirmed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This Reaſon of an Oath is much more ſtrong in reference to the Prince, then to the People: For when once the Prince hath the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Kingdom in his hand, What can be better ſecurity of his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, then his Oath? As for the people, if they ſwear not, yet if they be diſloyal, their lives, and al they have, are in the Princes hands. But it is nor ſo with the Prince, til there hath been a Conteſtation firſt, and his power is broken.</p>
            <p>3 <hi>It comes to paſſe ſometimes, That the Performance is onlie on one Partie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> But that is not the caſe betwixt Prince and People, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance muſt be on both ſides, elſe the Common-wealth is miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>4 <hi>Sometimes there is other Satisfactorie Aſſurances given beſides an Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> But what is that the Prince can give to ſatisfie the People be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſwearing, and yet the People cannot give the ſame, but they muſt needs ſwear?</p>
            <p>5 <hi>Sometimes the danger of the breach lies onlie, or more on one Partie then another.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:165675:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> So much more need hath the Prince to ſwear then the People, becauſe the danger of the breach lies moſt on his part. For, for one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that can be given of the Peoples diſloyalty to a juſt Prince, there may be twenty given of the Princes unjuſt oppreſſive carriage to an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient People.</p>
            <p>6 <hi>Sometimes there is other remedies, if there ſhould be a breach, then the forfeiture of an Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I hope the Remedy whatever it be beſides an Oath, may be applicable to the People, if they break, as to the Prince, if he break.</p>
            <p>4 <hi>He ſaith,</hi> But ſuppoſe the caſe, that it be as neceſſary for ſecurity, that the King ſwear to the people, as the people to the King; yet if (through overmuch credulity, or otherwiſe) it be that the people do ſwear, and not the Prince, this cannot be the leaſt colour of the nullifying of the peoples Oath: For that which makes the Oath obliging, is, That in a juſt and poſſible matter promiſed, God is invocated as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the promiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Grant it be as neceſſary, that the King ſwear as the People, and that through the credulity of the people the King ſwear not, or that through fear of incenſing him, they dare not demand an Oath from him, and yet through his power and wrath they are forced to ſwear to him, (and this is the caſe many times) and ſuppoſe that the King after this Oath of the People to him turn Tyrant, and prey upon them, Is this Oath of the people obligatory, or is it not? I have Aſſerted that it is not, and for this Reaſon, Becauſe whether the King ſwear, or ſwear not, he ought to do the thing that he ſhould ſwear, or elſe not expect that which he makes the People ſwear to, becauſe the juſtice of the thing in the peoples Oath, depends upon a Condition, that the King perform his duty. For its impious and wicked for a people to promiſe, much more for a people to ſwear, that though it ſhould come to paſſe, that the King ſhould turn all his power and force againſt them to deſtroy them, yet he ſhal be their King, and they will obey him ſtill, while any of them are le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t alive. And this man himſelf, ſaith nothing in his Reaſon which he renders Contradictory to this, but what rather ſerves to confirm it. For he ſaith, <hi>That which makes the Oath obliging is, that in a juſt and poſſible matter promiſed, God is invocated, as a witneſſe of the Promiſe:</hi> He ſaith, The matter muſt be juſt that is promiſed and ſworn to, or the Oath is not obliging: now the juſtneſſe of ſuch a promiſe and oath, is the Condition upon which it is made, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Prince Rule for their welfare, and not for their Ruine, otherwiſe the Subject is moſt inhumanly unjuſt againſt himſelf, and God is invocated to ſuch wickedneſſe, which is high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in thoſe perſons that do it: and the thing is not ratified there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, but repentance ought rather to be ſhewed. But (indeed) it is to be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165675:27"/> ſuppoſed, that the people ſwear not at any time, but that at leaſt this Condition is tacite, in the Oath; and that the King is engaged unto his part with the people in the ſame oath. And if any man argue otherwiſe and ſay it is not ſo; I ſay then, <hi>Such</hi> an Oath is unlawful, and holds not longer, then in the true ſcope and extent of it, it ought to hold.</p>
            <p>After that apter ſenſe of (<hi>Mutual</hi>) which he ſaith is my ſenſe, he comes to give another ſenſe of (<hi>Mutual ſwearing</hi>) which he ſaith is ſtricter then the former, and that is ſaith he, <hi>When not onlie two perſons ſwear to each other their reſpective parts, but both ſwear with a mutual reſpect; that is, The Obligation of the one partie, hath a reſpect to, and a dependence upon the performance on the other partie: as when one man ſwears to give another ſo much for his Land, the other ſwears to convey to him his Land for ſo much Money, in this kind the breach of the one, is the releaſment of the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This is not another ſenſe, but the ſame with the former; for this is in al mutual Oathes that are made by two perſons to each other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally, they are Oathes made with mutual reſpect; that is, The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of the one party, hath reſpect to, and dependence upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the other partie, as in Gen. 21. 31, 32. betwixt <hi>Abimel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch</hi> and <hi>Abraham.</hi> Gen. 31. 52, 53. betwixt <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Laban.</hi> Joſh. 2. 12. 17. to 21 betwixt <hi>Rahab</hi> and the <hi>Spies.</hi> 1 Sam. 30. 15. betwixt <hi>David</hi> and the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekite.</hi> 1 Sam. 20. 16. 17. betwixt <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Ionathan.</hi> 1 King. 2. 42, 43. betwixt <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Shimei.</hi> 2 King 11. 17. betwixt <hi>Ioaſh</hi> and the <hi>People.</hi> And where wil it be found otherwiſe, but ſtil in mutual Oathes of two perſons to each other, they are with mutual reſpect, and the obligation of the one, hath reſpect to, and a dependence upon the performance of the other, ſo as the breach of the one, is the releaſment of the other, as in the Oath betwixt the <hi>Spies</hi> and <hi>Rahab</hi> is moſt cleerly manifeſt. For there it is expreſſed in ſo many words, and it is perpetually imply'd in al other ſuch like Oathes which we reade of in the Scripture, where it is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Of this nature are Oathes betwixt Prince and People if they be mutual, (as (by the grant of this man) in <hi>Englands</hi> caſe they be) then they be with reſpect: for the Prince doth not ſwear to give himſelf up for the Peoples good, to be ſhepheard of them, and Captain over them for nought, but for ſuch homage, obedience, fear, duty, tribute, cuſtome, revenue, to be performed and given by the People uuto him: So the People do not ſwear to give unto the Prince ſo much fear, obſervance, ſubjection, revenue, abſolutly and cleerly, but for ſuch a work of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ruling and Governing them. And it is yet more cleer in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation betwixt Paſtor and People, the Covenant betwixt them is with reſpect, and the obligation of the one party, hath reſpect to, and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon the performance of the other. The People do not promiſe or engage to give ſo much of their Eſtates for the maintenance of him abſolutly and cleerly, but with reſpect to his labouring in the Word and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:165675:27"/> Doctrine among them; neither doth the Paſtor engage abſolutly and cleerly ſo to labour amongſt them, and give out his ſtrength in ſuch ſort for their good, but with reſpect to ſuch double honor, as the Scripture obligeth them to give him. And yet it cannot be denied but that (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this mutual reſpect that ſuch an Engagement hath to each other, and dependence which the one hath upon the performance of the other) both of them are tyed and engaged to God, and that the duties which they do performe are duties to God, becauſe God hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them ſuch duties, but not without, but upon ſuch mutual reſpect to each other, and it is no duty to God without this reſpect, for a people to give this double honor to him, that wil not Rule wel, and labour in the Word and Doctrine among them, but they ought rather in diſcharge of their duty to God, to remove, or cauſe to be removed ſuch a perſon from his office, and ſo to with-draw their double honor from him: and ſo it is in theſe relative duties betwixt Prince and people. And ſo let this man (if he can) or any other, ſhew by divine Rule a more abſolute en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement betwixt Prince and people, then betwixt Paſtor and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>But he ſaith, <hi>This ſenſe of ſwearing cannot come in to be meant in the point of Controverſie:</hi> But why ſo?</p>
            <p>1 Saith he, <hi>Such an Oath is plainlie Conditional, as when one gives ſo much Monie for ſo much Land, he gives it not cleerlie and abſolutlie, but for ſo much Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> So it is in this caſe plainly Conditional, perhaps not alwayes expreſly Conditional: If a people ſhould ſay nothing to him that is to be their Paſtor of any duty that he is to perform to them, but only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſuch maintainance to him, the Condition of Preaching to them is plainly enough imply'd though not expreſſed. It cannot rationally be conceived, that they would give ſo much to him, as being their Paſtor, for doing nothing: ſo of the People it may be ſaid, in reference to their Allegiance to their Prince, that there is no abſolute neceſſity that the Condition ſhould be expreſſed, eſpecially in the caſe of the Subjects of this Kingdom, becauſe the King was ſworn to Rule according to the Laws, and that was the Condition of al after Oathes taken by the people to him.</p>
            <p>2 He ſaith, <hi>The Oath of Allegiance is granted to be abſolute by the Author of the</hi> POSITIONS, <hi>and diſputed againſt by him, as ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> It is a miſtake to ſay ſo: The Diſpute was to prove, That ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Oath was Conditional, or ought to be; was Mutual, or ought to be; if lawful: And therefore if broken on the Kings party, then the people are abſolved. And though he himſelf was ſatisfied that it was Conditional, and Mutual, and with Reſpect; yet becauſe others did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165675:28"/> it, therefore he expreſſed himſelf in a disjunctive [either was mutual or ought to have been.]</p>
            <p>3 But ſaith he, <hi>The Kings Oath is abſolute, and binds without depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on the Subjects Loyaltie; no man will ſay, That the King is diſcharged from Ruling juſtlie, and may turn Tyrant, if the People fail in their Oath to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> It is denyed, That the Kings or Peoples Oathes bind without dependence any more then Paſtors and Peoples Engagements do: and though no man wil ſay, That the King is diſcharged from Ruling juſtly, and may turn Tyrant; yet rational men wil ſay, That he may ceaſe his Ruling, and lay down his Office of Government, if the People generally with-hold their Subjection, and his Revenue from him. Nor can any one rationally think, That the Governor ſhould ſtil carry the weight of ſuch a Truſt over ſuch a People, who do with-draw their fear, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and obedience from him, and wil pay him no tribute, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enue, and abuſe his perſon: but that he may in ſuch a caſe, be abſolved from all engagement in reference to ſuch a Function over ſuch a People, and ſo the caſe is with the Subject. There is difference betwixt <hi>non adjuration,</hi> and <hi>male adjuration,</hi> the latter is in no caſe warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but the former is juſtifiable upon the breach of the people in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſloyalty to him.</p>
            <p>4 <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſuch mutual Oathes are entred into by both Parties at the ſame time, but neither doth the King nor Subjects ſwear to each other at the ſame time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This is not neceſſary in mutual Oathes betwixt two parties which are with reſpect; ſuch mutual Oaths may be betwixt two Princes of divers Nations, and ſo depending the one upon the performance of the other; that if there be a breach on either ſide, the other is free upon it from ſuch obligation, and yet theſe Princes not meet together, nor ſwear at one time.</p>
            <p>5 <hi>Such mutual reſpective Oathes, have onlie place in matters arbitrarie, which are in mens choice to do, or not to do before they ſwear, but not ſo in theſe relative duties betwixt Kings and Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> It is arbitrary (though not in reference to Government it ſelf, yet) in reference to the diſignation of the perſon or perſons that are to be put in place of Government, before there be a Pact or Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſuch perſon or perſons, and ſuch a people whom they are to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern. And though there be a neceſſity after ſuch Pact and Covenant, yet ſuch neceſſity is bottom'd on ſuch a Pact or Covenant, and ſo it is not an abſolute neceſſity, but a neceſſity upon ſuch a Condition. The duties of Maſters and Servants, are neceſſary in the general, but particularly conſidered in reference to this or that perſon giving up themſelves to be Servants unto ſuch and ſuch Maſters, it is meerly arbitrary before the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:165675:28"/> Pact, and there is place for ſuch reſpective Oathes betwixt them, and that the one breaking, the other is free upon it.</p>
            <p>But he goes on to conſider of the Reaſon of the Poſition, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is againſt Equitie and Reaſon, that the one ſhould be further or longer bound to the other, then the other is bound to him:</hi> And he ſaith, <hi>That if that be granted, yet there is no neceſſitie that the Oath be mutual, for the Prince may be bound, and is bound, and it cannot he otherwiſe, but that he ſhould be bound to his dutie as long as the Subject is to his, by Scripture, Conſcience, and poſitive Laws, and yet not ſworn at al.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> If al be granted that he ſaith, let the Reader judge whether if the Subject be bound to the Prince by Scripture, Conſcience, and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Lawes, and by an Oath to the Prince over and above al the other, and the Prince be bound to the Subject by Scripture, Conſcience, and poſitive Laws, but not by an Oath; Whether the Subject be not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bound to the Prince, then the Prince to him. But in this particle (<hi>further</hi>) he meddles not, which yet was in the Reaſon of the Poſition: but ſaith, <hi>The Prince is bound (and that as long)</hi> but he ſaith not (<hi>and that as far</hi>) and yet he would ſeem to grant the whole Reaſon, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding deny the mutual Oath, but it is without Reaſon.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition remaining ſtil in ſtrength (as I ſuppoſe) and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it alſo, notwithſtanding al that hath been endeavoured by him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; the Conſequence remains firm alſo. And as he diſables them not, ſo need not I to confirm them.</p>
            <p>Only in the end of the Conſequences there was (for further illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion rather then confirmation) the Parliaments Fact, in taking up Arms produced as ſutable to thoſe inferences, and ſerving to cleer the Oath of Allegiance to be Conditional, and not Abſolute; to be Mutual, and not Single; in the very accompt of the Parliament it ſelf, who beſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it. For had not they in that Oath of Allegiance ſworn with this limitation in their own underſtandings, (<hi>viz. According to the Laws of the Kingdom</hi>) as the Condition whether expreſſed or not, and had they not known that the King was ſworn to them, to Govern according to the Laws, and that theſe two Oathes had mutual reſpect to each other, this Oath of Allegiance in an abſolute ſenſe Conſidered, had they not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced it as unjuſt and wicked, would have made them guilty of diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and Rebellion in taking up of Arms, which I am ſure my <hi>Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt</hi> (whoever he might be) would not charge them with.</p>
            <p>Now unto this he Anſwereth two things:</p>
            <p>1 <hi>He ſaith,</hi> If their taking up of Arms againſt the King were Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, their abſolution from their Oathes by the Kings breach of his, could not unmake, or make it no Rebellion; for the debt of Obedience is exiſtent in the Subject before any Oath taking, and it is not founded on ſwearing, but only confirmed by it, and therefore ſurvives after the Oath ſhould be diſſolved.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:165675:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> But in this argumentation, he builds upon that which I have oft deſtroyed, and takes that for granted, which I have oft denyed, <hi>viz. (That there is an abſolute debt of Obedience to this or that Magiſtrate</hi>) which is not ſo, ſave only upon mutual Covenant, which comes afterwards to be confirmed by Oath, and from which by the breach of Covenant and Oath upon the Magiſtrates ſide, the Subject is acquitted, <hi>viz.</hi> From his Oath and Covenant together; ſo that the one doth not ſurvive the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as in al mutual Oathes it is; there is an abſolution from the oath, and from the thing (of which the oath is) together; as in Joſh. 2. 20. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears: they would be quit of the oath, and not only ſo, but of the thing alſo, if ſhe kept not within, or ſhould diſcover.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>He ſaith,</hi> We muſt therefore ſay, as the Parliamentarian party hath beleeved, declared, and in many Treatiſes in Print, maintained al along the late Wars, That the Armes of the Parliament were not againſt any brance of the Subjects Allegiance, or the Oath for it (which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed ſtil to perſiſt in, yea, and in the act of their Armes bearing, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted to yeeld and maintain) but concordant with the ſame. In as much as they enterprized not againſt the Kings Perſon, his State, or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they went not againſt his Majeſty, his Heirs, or Succeſſors, they joyned not againſt his Crown and Dignity, the Rights whereof, and the Bounds of the Subjects Obedience, are perfixed by the Lawes of the Realm, the ultimate interpretation whereof, is in the Parliament which declared their Arms to be for, and agreeable to the Laws. The King, as King, acts only by his Courts and Laws, what he doth beſides, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe, is the mans, not the Kings acting. What is done by Order of the Courts of Juſtice, and by vertue of the Laws, is done (though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his perſonal preſence or command, yet) for the King, his Crown, and Dignity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> In this ſenſe that he puts upon the taking up of Arms, there is enough to ratifie and confirm that which al along I have been conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for; and there is nothing that contradicts me, but what contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts it ſelf. I ſhall take up ſome paſſages in the Relation which he makes:</p>
            <p>1 He ſaith <hi>The King, as King, acts onlie by his Courts and Laws, and what he doth beſides, or againſt, theſe is the mans, not the Kings acting:</hi> It is as much as if he ſhould ſay, The King fals under a double conſideration, as a man, and ſo when he departs from Laws, and from Juſtice, he is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be lookt upon as ſuch, and as a King, and ſo only when he keeps to his Laws, and to his Courts of Juſtice. Now we know that the oath of Allegiance was made to the King, as King; and ſo the Subject hath nothing to do with him in point of obedience or Allegiance, ſave only as King; that is, When he Rules according to Law. Again, The oath of Allegiance being to a legal King, when the perſon of the King is a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:165675:29"/> Tyrant, and breaks al Laws and overthrowes al Courts of Juſtice, where is then this legal King? and if there be none, the ſubject is then diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from their oath of Allegiance.</p>
            <p>This diſtinction betwixt the man and the King, is but a notional con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit; for take away the man, and where is then the King? and ſure I am, that God wil make no ſuch diſtinction when he ſhal come to judg Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but al their miſcarriages in Government, &amp; irregularities in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aging of their Offices ſhal be charged upon them as Princes ſet over the People: then it wil not be ſaid, What he doth beſides, or againſt the Laws and Courts of Juſtice, is the mans, not the Kings acting; it wil appear then, That Kings, as Kings, have offended, and been unjuſt and tyrannous.</p>
            <p>2 He ſaith, <hi>That the Parliament hath declared their Arms to be for, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Laws;</hi> that is, for the King ruling by Laws: and againſt the King; that is, the perſon that carrieth that name, which is indeed but the man, when he violates al Laws in Ruling; for they were only ſworn to the King, acting by his Courts and Lawes; and what is this, but the ſame that I have aſſerted in the Poſitions, <hi>viz.</hi> That if the Subject were abſolutly engaged by oath to the perſon of the King, whether he Rule wel or il, and that this oath were lawful, the PARLIAMENT muſt needs be diſloyal in taking up Armes againſt the perſon of the King.</p>
            <p>3 He ſaith, <hi>That which is againſt the Kings perſonal Preſence, or Command, is not againſt the King:</hi> that is, is not againſt the King in Law, or againſt ſuch a one as the King ought to be according to Law. So that he grants, That Allegiance is not to a perſonal King, or his Commands, unleſſe he be a legal King, and a King according to Law; for things may be done againſt his perſonal Preſence and Commands, wherein he concurs with the Poſitions, but contradicts himſelf: For, where is any place for paſſive obedience, if that be true, which yet is one of his Reaſons of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conditional, or abſolute Allegience.</p>
            <p>4 Now whereas he ſaith, <hi>The Parliamentarie Partie enterprized nothing againſt his Perſon, &amp;c.</hi> There ſeems to be a contradiction in it; For he ſaith, <hi>They declared their Arms to be for the Laws,</hi> and ſo againſt al that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them, which his Perſon, perſonal Preſence, and Commands often did. And (indeed) did they not make his Perſon flye from place to place? And was not his Perſon often in danger, as the perſons of thoſe that fought under him were? And was not his Perſon ſecured in <hi>Holmeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by-Houſe?</hi> And had their Allegiance been to his Perſon as diſtinct from the Laws, they had violated it.</p>
            <p>And whereas there is mention made of the Covenant which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into to preſerve his Perſon, and that in the very times of their Arms bearing: It is manifeſt, That they bind themſelves firſt to maintain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:165675:30"/> and the Liberties of the Kingdom; and then in Religion and Liberties to preſerve his Perſon and Honor, and no further, but as might ſtand with them; which ſhews that they were bound to them firſtly by Law, and not to any Allegiance to his Perſon againſt them, but ſo far as they might preſerve them: and therefore in the very time of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, they are found in wayes of chaſtizing him, though with a ſcope of preſerving him, if poſſibly Religion and the Subjects Liberty may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with it. And firſt, they correct him in his Inſtruments, and then in Perſon in ſecuring him, which was not very honourable unto him, but the preſervation of Religion, and Liberty of the Subject forced them to it. At laſt their Counſels were to make no more Addreſſes to him, but to lay him aſide, and to ſettle Religion and Liberty without him, and this was more diſhonarable to him; but their Covenant which bound them firſt to Religion, &amp;c. compelled them to it: and there was yet further liberty in the Covenant left for them to cut him off, and his alſo, if the neceſſity of the preſervation of Religion and Liberty of the Subject ſhould require it. And indeed it is not rational to think, That they could have a lawful power, without contradicting the oath of allegiance or the Covenant, of inflicting leſſer Cenſures and Penalties upon him, and yet want power to inflict higher and greater puniſhments if the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Crime deſerved them, and the neceſſity of conſerving Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Liberty required them.</p>
            <p>But he comes to conſider of the Second Exception againſt the Oath of Allegiance which the Poſition mentions, <hi>viz.</hi> as there is in it, <hi>A ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Kings Heirs,</hi> he mentions my words in the Reaſon that I lay down of my Exception againſt it, <hi>viz. Who knows whether he will be a wiſe man or a foole, &amp;c.</hi> And he mentions my Conſequence, <hi>viz. The Oath of Allegiance was in that branch of it an unlawful Oath.</hi> And he makes this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer;</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>I allow of the Antecedent, but utterlie denie the Conſequence of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> But it muſt be underſtood that I mean it (as it is now made uſe of, and inſiſted upon, and urged by many who have taken it) of an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Oath to them whatſoever they prove to be. For the ſtrength of the Reaſon which I bring againſt it, lies in theſe words, <hi>They may bind themſelves therebie to their own hurt and ruine;</hi> which if it be not abſolute they cannot do: therefore I diſpute againſt it, as abſolute as I did againſt the other branch of it.</p>
            <p>But let his Reaſon of the whole CONSEQUENCE be weighed.</p>
            <p>1 Saith he, <hi>This Inference is directlie contrarie to that which</hi> Solomon <hi>in the place cited,</hi> Eccleſ. 2. 19. <hi>makes from the words:</hi> Solomons <hi>is, Yet ſhall he have Rule over all my labour, wherein I have laboured, and wherein I have
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:165675:30"/> ſhewed my ſelf wiſe under the Sun; This mans is, (in effect) becauſe no man knows, whether he will be a wiſe man or a foole, therefore he ſhall not have Rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 Let the text be weighed and truly examined, and it wil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks not of the kingdom which he was to leave to his Son, whether a wiſe man or a fool, but he ſpeaks of his labour, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he had laboured in getting Riches, in gathering Wealth, in building Houſes, in planting Vineyards, in improving of his earthly Eſtate in the World. He ſhewes there is a vanity in it, His Son ſhal have Rule over al. In Verſ. 18. he ſaith, <hi>He hated all his labour becauſe of this;</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be meant of his labor in the Kingdom in Government: and it is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to that in Job 14. 21. Pſal. 49. 10.</p>
            <p>2 If <hi>Solomon</hi> ſhould mean it of the Rule of the Kingdom, yet he ſpeaks not of it as a thing that he did approve of, but of it as that which he coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vanity.</p>
            <p>2 He ſaith, <hi>The ſame Reaſon if it hold, would be againſt anie Oath or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to anie Rulers in being whatſoever they are, for ſay they become to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turitie, and for the paſt and preſent time have given proof, yet who knows what they that are now wiſe and juſt (morallie) may hereafter come to be? The Scripture ſuppoſeth, That not onlie a juſt Father may have a wicked Son, but a righteous man (in Profeſſion and External carriage) may turn from his carriage, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 This Reaſon of his wherewith he diſputes againſt the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception that I make, <hi>viz. Of Oathes to Heirs;</hi> is very ſtrong againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in reference to abſolute Oathes which he would maintain, and ſhews how dangerous abſolute oathes to Princes or other Governors are, and how deſtructive they may become, if not only a juſt Father may have a wicked Son, but a righteous man (Prince or other) may turn away from his Righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>2 Notwithſtanding there is this difference betwixt the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that whilſt a man ſwears Allegiance to a Prince, at preſent wiſe, and juſt, and pious in profeſſion, but mutual and changable he ſwears in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him, he exerciſeth his underſtanding and beſt abilities in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, beyond which a man cannot go, nor doth God require him to go: but in the other, he exerciſeth not his judgment at al, but ſwears hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over-head to a thing he doth not know what, and to a perſon he knoweth not whom. And I would ask this man, Whether (if it were ſo) in al the under-Offices in the Kingdom, That perſons ſhould come by Succeſſion to their Places? If all Judges ſhould, and al Magiſtrates and other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in office ſhould, whether there were not like to be a miſerable Common-wealth? And whether he durſt reaſon after this manner, and make a parity, betwixt chuſing men juſt at preſent and wiſe men, and men of truth to ſuch places, and making ſuch places Hereditary; <hi>becauſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:165675:31"/> if there be an Election, the perſons that are good and able for ſuch places may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, and if it be Hereditarie, they may be good, and can be but naught as the other may prove to be.</hi> I would ask him alſo, Whether there be the like caſuality in reference to the one as to the other? Though there be a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilty in reference to both. And if this Reaſoning be ſhameful in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renee to under Officers, then, Why is it not ſo in reference to the ſupream Officer? Beſides, there is an expreſſe Command for the one in Exod. 18. 21. 23. campared with Numb. 11. 16, 17. but where is there any Command for the other?</p>
            <p>3 He ſaith, <hi>This Conſequence were it of force, would equallie condemn all promiſorie Oathes, and other Covenants and Engagements between man and man; for it cannot be foreſeen in anie, what the perſons contracted with will prove.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This Reaſon of his (thus far of it) is of the ſame nature with the former, and receives its Anſwer in the former; But he goes on, and ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is alſo againſt the Laws and Sanctions of thoſe Nations in all ages, which have ſettled ſucceſſive Regalitie, or other Governments for longer then the preſent poſſeſſors of the power endure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Nations have ſo done, and they have been plagued in doing ſo alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>its warranted by the Word of God. Iſrael offered a ſucceſſive power to</hi> Gideon, Judg. 8. 22. <hi>God himſelf inſtituted and bound his people to a lineal GOVERNMENT, in</hi> David <hi>and in his Seed,</hi> 2 Sam. 12. 15. 2 Chron. 13, 5. <hi>The Patriarchs power which was political, was ſucceſſive; ſo was the Government of the</hi> Jews <hi>for a hundred yeers, in the linage of the</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabees.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 The inſtance in <hi>Gideon</hi> proves nothing; though <hi>Iſrael</hi> offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, being deeply affected with the greatneſſe of the deliverance of which he was inſtrumental, (and it was only a ſudden expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their love, and not ſo deliberatly done) yet <hi>Gideon</hi> accepted it not.</p>
            <p>2 As for Gods inſtituting it lineally in <hi>David:</hi> 1 God raiſed up <hi>Saul</hi> to the Kingdom, but ſettled it not lineally in him; let the one be ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the other. 2 It appears not that God ſettled it in the next of bloud in <hi>Davids</hi> lineage, or that the next of bloud had it; for <hi>Solomon</hi> was not his eldeſt Son living, but <hi>Adonijah</hi> was before him, yet God gave it to <hi>Solomon</hi> not to <hi>Adonijah;</hi> therefore this ſetting it in <hi>Davids</hi> ſeed, is not pattern for ſucceſſion among us. 3 It was done in reference to Chriſt, who was to come from <hi>Davids</hi> loines, and was to have his Throne, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 32.</p>
            <p>3 The Patriarchal Government, whatever it was (for we are left much in the dark about it; and this man makes uſe of it, but holds not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:165675:31"/> out any light concerning it) the Law of Nature inſtituted it, for the Father is greater then the Child, and his Governor, from that act of his in begetting of him; as God is Governor of the World, by that act of his in Creating it: but mixed Families, as in Common-wealths, the People make their own Father, that is, their own Governor. And they ought to do it with the beſt underſtanding they have.</p>
            <p>4 The example of the <hi>Maccabees</hi> proves nothing. For they were Saviours whom God raiſed up ſucceſſively, and therefore they might wel Rule ſucceſſively; but for the thing it ſelf, God ſeems to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alow it, for Iſrael had a Government ſetled by God amongſt them, before <hi>Sauls</hi> time, but not Kingly, nor in Succeſſion, but of another kind. And this Government they liked not, but would have a Government according to the Nations, <hi>viz. Kinglie</hi> Government in Succeſſion; but God was diſpleaſed with it, and ſaid they had rejected him in it.</p>
            <p>4 He ſaith, <hi>We have Scriptural examples of an uncontroverted integritie, of Oathes to Princes and their Heirs, and to Princes in their yong<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> unripe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryed yeers. Take</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that inſtance of</hi> Abrahams <hi>ſwearing to</hi> Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech, <hi>his Son, and his Sons Son,</hi> Gen. 21. 23, 24. <hi>And that of</hi> Davids <hi>making</hi> Solomon <hi>King in his own life time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when he was yong and tender, 2 Chron. 23. 1. &amp; 29. 1. And that of</hi> Jehojada's <hi>and the Peoples making of</hi> Joaſh <hi>King, and ſwearing to him when he mas but ſeven yeers old, 2 King.</hi> 11. 4. 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply. 1, Abraham</hi> ſwore to <hi>Abimelech,</hi> and to his Son, and to his Sons Son, not to deal falſly with them, but according as <hi>Abimelech</hi> had dealt kindly with him. This was not only a ſafe oath without da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger in <hi>Abraham,</hi> but a juſt Oath, and of a thing neceſſary in it ſelf to be done; and of an unchangable nature ſo far as concerns falſneſſe, and it was a mutual oath, and alſo therein conditional ſo far as concerns kindneſſe, and therefore no way applicable to the oath of Allegiance in reference to Heirs which (as was ſaid in the Reaſon) may bring Ruine, and is like to prove ſooner or later, pernicious. 2 That inſtance of <hi>David</hi> in making <hi>Solomon</hi> King in his life time while yong and tender, hath little ſtrength in it. <hi>Solomon</hi> was the perſon appointed thereunto of God, and therefore he was ſure to be competently furniſhed with abilities for it from God, what ever his age might be; and he grown up to ſuch yeers, that excellent Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and an excellent Spirit fit for Government appeared in him. 3 That of <hi>Ioaſh</hi> hath more in it in reference to unripe yeers, but reacheth not the caſe, becauſe he was al that was left of thoſe Heirs that were to ſucceed in <hi>Davids</hi> linage in the Kingdom, which God had eſtabliſhed by Covenant upon <hi>David</hi> and his ſeed.</p>
            <p>2, He denyeth the two parts of the Conſequence, 1 That part, <hi>viz. The Oath is not in judgment, becauſe no man knows what the Heir will prove.</hi> But what are the words wherein he denyes it?</p>
            <p>1 <hi>It may be</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in judgment ſo far as a future contigencie can be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berated
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:165675:32"/> upon, and this may be concluded on adviſedlie (as morallie certain) that it is better to have the Crown ſetled in a Line wherebie ſometimes a vitious perſon may be advanced, then to have it under Election at everie perſonal change: This hath been the experimented Maxime of the wiſeſt States.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The true ſenſe of this Anſwer is, That there is no place for deliberation in ſwearing to Heirs, of whom we can know nothing how they wil prove, ſave only how to prevent a greater miſchief which is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed wil come by new Elections upon every change, which wiſe States do decline: but what evil there is at al in a wel Governed State by new Elections at every change I am not able to reach, but experience wil inſtruct, That the greateſt, and longeſt laſting Wars have been, where Competitors in point of Title, have contended for the Crown. And how frequently one hath ſupplanted another to obtain the Kingdom, Stories do plentifully ſhew.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>If it were not in judgment</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>this defect makes not an Oath unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as to the nullifying of it, a raſh Oath (if of a lawful thing) binds, as before was proved,</hi> Judg. 21. 2. 7. 1 Sam. 14. 24. 37. Joſh. 9. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 Nor did I ever aſſert, That an Error in Judgment when the Oath is righteous in the nature of it, might be broken, though there are caſes which are very dubious. 2 The Scriptures which he cites are none of them in a righteous thing, nor did they al of them bind, nor ought they to have done, therefore he mentioneth them improperly. For, Firſt, That Oath which the Tribes did make, of not giving their Daughters to the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> after they had cruelly cut off al the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men appertaining to that Tribe, was an unrighteous and cruel Oath, and ſhould not have bound them. Secondly, That <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould lay a Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe upon the People, that taſted any thing til evening, was alſo not only a raſh, but an unmerciful, and unjuſt Oath; and <hi>Ionathan</hi> ſaid as much of it when he heard of it, ſo far was he from being troubled that he had broken it, and he thought not himſelf guilty of death, <hi>Shall I die</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for this?</hi> And the People reſcued him, and the Oath ſtood not in that branch of it. And that of Joſh. 9. reſpecting the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> was a ſinful Oath in the matter of it, as it proved though they knew it not, as wel as a raſh Oath; and there was <hi>Error perſonae</hi> in it alſo, which is enough to break any Oath, and therefore there was ſpecial reaſon why it held, and it reacheth not to us. And it is againſt this mans own Poſition, That an unrighteous oath in the matter of it ſhould hold; now this oath to Heirs is of this nature, not only raſh, and not in judgment, but unrighteous, and therefore ought not to hold.</p>
            <p>2 He denies that part of the Conſequence, which concerns righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in an oath, which I lay down in the Poſition thus, <hi>Nor is it a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Oath for the Subject may bind himſelf to his own hurt, yea ruine.</hi> His words are theſe;</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:165675:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Though the Subject may not bind himſelf to what is neceſſarilie, or at the time of his ſwearing may appear probably to tend to his hurt or ruine; yet he may ſwear (intending the publick good) to that which is of a mutual nature, and may in the event turn to his own hurt and ruine. And might he not ſo ſwear, yet having ſo ſworn he is bound to ſtand to his Oath, Pſal. 15. 4. Ioſh. 9. 15. Ezek. 17. 13. 1 Sam. 14. 26. 28. 37. Iudg. 21. 5. 15. 18. which is contradictorie to what this man here ſaith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> He ſtates the Queſtion amiſſe, and puts the caſe ſo, as that it is not the caſe, for to ſwear to Heirs from generation to generation, though it be uncertain which Heirs, and at whattime ſuch Heirs wil prove cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and unjuſt in adjuration, yet it is more then probable (even as certain as that there wil be change of weather, when yet for the preſent it is fair and pleaſant) that ſuch Heirs wil ſtand up in enſuing generations.</p>
            <p>2 Though there may poſſibly be caſes in which oathes that were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with a good intent, but proving accidentally pernicious to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, muſt be kept: yet if this be aſſerted by the Anſwerer, That meer voluntary arbitrary oathes made without any Condition, and at the beſt (if not forced) in favour of ſuch a Family, and intended for mutual good, but proving ruinous to the makers, and ſerving only to ſtrengthen cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and unrighteouſneſſe in the perſons to whom made, that ſuch oathes ought to be kept, hath neither the colour of Reaſon nor Scripture for it; and this is the caſe directly in ſuch abſolute oathes to Heirs: Nay, in the caſe which himſelf makes, it wil not hold that ſuch an oath ſhould be kept: For ſuppoſe a man ſhould ſwear to another to go to ſuch a City for him at ſuch a time, to effect ſuch a buſineſſe; but he afterwards comes to underſtand, That at his return there are perſons that wil be in ambuſcado to take away his life; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this man bound to keep his oath, if the other wil hold him to it?</p>
            <p>3 As for the Scriptures, they are not pertinent, and ſome of them have been oft Anſwered: That in Pſal. 15. 4. is meant of an oath that is made to another, by which that other may be profited, and the perſon himſelf that ſweirs, comes at unawares to be thereby damified; ſuch an oath oug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to be kept, though it be to a mans loſſe: but the oath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we are diſcuſſing, is of another nature, an oath by which not one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but a Nation, not diſadvantaged ſomewhat, but even ſold (as it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> times) to ruine, or (what is worſe, even) vaſſalage, by which not the perſon to whom the oath is made is profited, but his baſe luſts ſatisfied, to his own ruine at the laſt. That in Joſh. 9. 15. is not exemplary, as I have often ſaid before; For I would ask, Whether if a Counterfeit Prince (as ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries make mention of many) had under pretence of being ſuch a one (<hi>viz.</hi> The right Heir to the Crown) gained an oath of Allegiance, would that oath have ſtood againſt the right Heir? I am ſure this man wil not aſſert it. The other Scriptures have been anſwered already, therefore I paſſe them over.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:165675:33"/>
            <p>
               <hi>If the Heir</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhould miſprove, his power is bounded by the Law, and commixed with Parliaments if he vary, the power of Parliament, the Lawes and Libertie of the Subject, are the ſame. The late King confeſſed and declared a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie againſt Tirannie to reſide in the Parliament, there may be prevention then of the Kingdoms ruine, whatever the Heir prove, if the Kingdom be faithful to it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> But what are Parliaments, if the Prince wil not cal them, or may ſpeedily diſſolve them? Or what are Laws, if the Prince wil not keep them? Or what are the Liberties of the Subject, if the Prince wil overthrow them? As the late King gave out, <hi>He would never have anie more Parliaments.</hi> And if the <hi>Scots</hi> had not frighted and forced him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably he would have made his ſaying good. What are al theſe, if the People be abſolutly bound to Alleg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance, whether the Prince Rule wel or il, and muſt obey in lawful things, and be paſſive in al the reſt? And ſuppoſe they may oppoſe, Wil it not engender a War? and how that War may iſſue, who can foretel? It may be a Kingdoms Ruine: here is then but a poor Remedy, ſuch an oath then as endangers al this cannot be lawful, nor is it fit to be kept.</p>
            <p>But he comes to examine my Third Exception againſt the Oath of Allegiance, <hi>Which is againſt ſwearing to anie one kind of Government abſolut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie wiihout admitting of a change, for a greater good and benefit, and to prevent inconvenience and hurtfulneſs, which hath been obſerved to come through ſuch a Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, 1 He blames the form of arguing in theſe words;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I obſerve</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there is a fault to be found with the whole Argument as ſomewhat tranſgreſſing the Rules of Arguing: 1 In the Conſequent, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Error called</hi> Ignoratio Elenthi, <hi>for we ſwear not in the Oath of Allegiance indefinitlie or indeterminatlie to uphold one Government continuallie and not to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1, <hi>We ſwear onlie to his Majeſtie, his Heirs, and Succeſſors, ſo that when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they are extinct (which may be ſooner or later as divine Providence diſpoſeth) the Oath of it ſelf ceaſeth and determineth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſwearing to Heirs, we ſwear to al that are of the blood, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Heirs in Law, and while any of them are alive, the oath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ceaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; and the blood hath laſted neer 600 yeers already, and may laſt probably enough til <hi>Doomes Day.</hi> 2 Swearing to Succeſſors (though not of bloud, though al the bloud ſhould be extinct) is a ſwearing that there ſhal be Succeſſors, and that we wil obey them; And is not this to ſwear indefinitly to uphold one kind of Government, where is then that fault, <hi>viz. Ignoratio Elenchi?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>Notwithſtanding the Allegiance ſworn to the ſaid perſons, there is power of change in the Government left to the mutual Conſent of both parties, to wit, thoſe ſworn to, and them ſwearing, as it is in al humane Contracts and Oathes of this nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:165675:33"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 But this man hath ſure forgotten, that which he hath often aſſerted, <hi>viz. That the Precept of Obedience to Civil Governors was without anie Condition, or reſerve of a diſingagement, or that it was due by abſolute and unalterable Rule, and without dependance upon another, and not with mutual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</hi> Which (if he have ſpoken the truth) wil be an impediment to this power of change by mutual conſent. However it be, its very palpable that he hath contradicted himſelf in his Aſſertions.</p>
            <p>2 If the Oath be to Heirs and Succeſſors, and binding, how can he ſay, They may be diſcharged through mutual conſent from that part of it which concerns Heirs, without Contradiction again to himſelf, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to what he aſſerts afterwards in pag 8. His words are theſe, <hi>Is not the Fifth Commandement the Law of God? And thoſe Precepts, Rom. 13. 4. Tit. 3. 1. 1 Pet. 2. 13. Repetitions and divine Ratifications thereof? And dotl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not that Law Command everie People and Perſon Allegiance to their lawful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors? And was not the King in Being, and his Heirs in Capacitie and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation ſuch?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus he Diſputes againſt abſolution from the Oath of Allegiance, not only in reference to the King in Being, but alſo in reference to his Heirs in Capacity and Deſignation, as a breach of the Law of God: and yet it ſeems by mutual Conſent, the King in Being, and the People may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence with this Law of God, and may cut off the Heirs from Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy, and change the Government, and not be guilty of breaking this Law of God.</p>
            <p>3 This grant that he makes of a power of change through conſent, is as good as nothing, for how unreaſonable wil it be to conceive, That a Perſon in Poſſeſſion of a Kingdom, wil conſent to looſe it, and alter the Government?</p>
            <p>The Second fault he finds in the form of Arguing, is in the Minor: <hi>There is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſomewhat of the fallacie called</hi> Petitio principii, <hi>namelie, That anie kind of Government granted to be lawful can prove inconvenient and hurtful to the Subjects. The Governors (indeed) may prove bad, and ſo (indeed) a change in the perſons, or a regulating of them, is the apt remedie for that hurt: but the Government is the Ordinance of God, and hath a political goodneſs ſeated in its being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> But he forgets himſelf again, and makes that to be <hi>Petitio Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipii,</hi> which he had before granted; and doth afterwards grant in that compariſon which he makes betwixt ſeveral kinds of Governments, and ſeveral Callings. He had ſaid, pag. 2. in that diſtinction of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of means tending to the happineſſe of a Community, <hi>That it was va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable in relation to times and people, and that that may be good in the nature of a means for one people or time, that is not ſo for another.</hi> And he cites out of <hi>Ariſtotle Pol. Lib.</hi> 3. theſe words, <hi>Eſt enim genus hominum naturâ varia com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratum atque affectum, aliud ſervile, aliud colendis Regibus accommodatum, aliud
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:165675:34"/> timo craticum &amp; populare, atque horum generum ſuum cuique, eſt ac diſtinctum commodum.</hi> And more there is exſerted by him out of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> to this purpoſe. And then afterwards, in comparing diverſity of Governments to diverſity of Callings, he doth by Conſequence ſpeak the ſame thing again, <hi>viz.</hi> That though al Governments be according to God, warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Scriptures, and in that ſenſe Gods Ordinance, as al lawful Callings are, (for there is no difference, but what may be ſaid of the one in this reſpect, may be ſaid of the other) yet al Governments are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good and profitable, alike congruous and agreeable, alike ſafe and ſutable to al people; nay, there may be a comparative evilneſſe and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in ſome Governments to ſome Common-wealths; ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths know how to put a bridle upon Kings better then others can: and ſo it is in Callings, which is his own Compariſon, ſome Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings though good in themſelves and Gods Ordinance in the ſenſe before expreſſed, yet hurtful to ſome perſons, and pernicious alſo; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to bind up to one Calling is unlawful, eſpecially when by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence it hath been found hurtful, through the unſutableneſſe thereof; and ſo it is of Governments: and ſo he cavils againſt that as not granted, which yet is granted by himſelf more then once.</p>
            <p>Having done with the form of Arguing, he comes to conſider of the Argument it ſelf, which is, <hi>That man may change Government for his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt good, and muſt change it, upon experience of the hurtfulneſſe of it.</hi> And he flatly denyes it, and ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No Poſition is more Anarchical then this is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 But it was neceſſary, that firſt he ſhould have done me right, and taken up my words in a right ſenſe, and then have ſhewed the <hi>Anarchie</hi> in them; but he puts a falſe ſenſe upon my words, and then diſputes againſt them. It is ſaid in the Argument, That man may change Government; he takes it up for every particular man, and then cryes out of <hi>Anarchie,</hi> but without al reaſon, for this word [<hi>man</hi>] is frequently in common phraſe of Speech, and in Scripture acception, the ſame with [<hi>men] Let not (man) prevail,</hi> is the ſame with <hi>Let not (men) prevail. Vain is the help of (man)</hi> is al one with <hi>Vain is the help of (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en)</hi> and ſo here, <hi>man</hi> is put for <hi>men.</hi> And (<hi>man</hi>) is ſometimes in Scripture put for Rulers, and the great ones amongſt men; <hi>Who art thou, that thou ſhouldeſt be afraid of a (man)</hi> that is, a <hi>man</hi> in power and authority, who is wont to be a terror unto other men; and ſo here, (<hi>man</hi>) is put for the principal Men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the People, and my inference which I make from 1 Pet. 2. 13. ſhews the ſenſe in which I underſtood it as he might eaſily have concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (if he had pleaſed) It is this, <hi>If an Ordinance of man, then man may change it;</hi> that is, If it be not expreſly commanded of God, but left to the liberty of man at the firſt, to eſtabliſh what form of Government he liketh beſt, then man, that is, ſuch men which at firſt Erected it, may
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:165675:34"/> change it. Now theſe are chief men choſen out of al the People (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe al the people cannot meet together conveniently, nor without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion act) and which have the peoples power, if theſe ſet up Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, they may upon experience of the hurtfulneſſe of it, change it, and eſtabliſh another, which they apprehend more ſafe and profitable: And where is the <hi>Anarchie</hi> in this Poſition or Aſſertion? And what is become of al his Diſproofs which he offers? Are they not Shafts ſhot againſt the wal, and break themſelves?</p>
            <p>2 He himſelf confeſſeth man may change it; For doth he not ſay, That the perſons ſwearing, and the perſons ſworn to, may by mutual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent change it? And are not theſe [<hi>man</hi>]? And is not he become <hi>Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical</hi> now in his own Poſition?</p>
            <p>But let the ſtrength of his Diſproofs be weighed.</p>
            <p>His Firſt Diſproof is from <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 21. His words are theſe:</p>
            <p>1, <hi>He ſaith man may change the Government, &amp;c. but the holie Ghoſt, Prov. 24. 21. ſaith, My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, &amp; meddle not with them that are given to change. He alloweth a change to be for greater good: but the holie Ghoſt tels us in the next words, verſ. 22. For their Calamitie ſhal riſe ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denlie, and who knoweth the ruine of them both?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The ſenſe that he puts upon this Scripture is abuſive to the place, and a wronging of the holy Ghoſt therein: For the firſt words, <hi>Fear the Lord and the King,</hi> ſerve to give light to al the reſt, and the ſenſe of the after words, muſt carry reſpect unto thoſe former words, <hi>Meddle not with thoſe that are given to change:</hi> It is as if he ſhould ſay, Meddle not with thoſe that wil change the Decrees and Precepts of God and the King, and ſo neither fear God nor the King. The wife man admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that we would abſtain from the fellowſhip of thoſe which detract from the Commands of God and the King, ſpeaking evil of them, and bringing others to the contempt of them; So <hi>Ianſenius</hi> upon the place. And <hi>Wilcock, Such as varie,</hi> viz. <hi>from the Command of God and the King, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing together, are the perſons that are given to change.</hi> And <hi>Tremelius</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the place, underſtands it of perſons violating the Commands of God and of the King, and departing from the reverence of God and of the King, in the diſobedience of their Life and Converſation; the Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch ſhal riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the Ruine of them both? that is, of ſuch who do ſo contemn God and the King, and others who are aſſociated with them. And what is this againſt changing the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, when it is (by the Governors breaking of Gods Laws and the Laws of the Land) become hurtful and ruinous.</p>
            <p>2, He ſaith, <hi>If men may change for the better, and muſt change, then are all Oathes, Engagements, Promiſes of Obedience to Magiſtrates unlawful to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken; for all ſuch Bonds are in relation to a preſent and particular Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Engagers are under, and they are not for the time preſent, or for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:165675:35"/> but for a future Continuance. And there is in all ſuch Engagements a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king over the right, which the Engagers have in the matter Covenanted, to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons engaged to: either then ſuch a change may not, muſt not be; or ſuch Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may not, muſt not be by them undertaken. But the Scripture is cleer enough for ſuch Engagements, Eccleſ. 8. 2. 2 King. 11. 4. Ioſh. 1. 16, 17, 18. Iudg. 8. 9, 10. 2 Chron.</hi> 36. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 All ſuch Oathes ſhould be Conditional, and then they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be unlawful, as hath often been ſhewed: and as for the perſons, where the chief Power reſides, <hi>viz.</hi> The Repreſentatives of the people, they ſhould never abſolutly bind their own hands in Engaging to any Governors or Magiſtrates whatever; for they ſel away the peoples Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and betray their truſt in ſo doing. But they are to be the Eyes of the People, to ſpie out the wayes of the Peoples ſafety, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elicity. No more then the preſent Parliament ought to make any abſolute En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to any Councel of State, but with Limitation of the good of the Subject of which they muſt be Judges: and yet it will not follow tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch an Engagement would be only for an inſtant, but it may be for long Continuance, if the good of the Subject wil permit it. And as for the People, their ſwearing ought to be with Subordination to their Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees which Repreſent them. There is therefore no ſtrength in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, <hi>viz. If there be a libertie to Change, there muſt be no Engagement.</hi> There may be liberty of Change in Servants that live with ſuch Maſters, yet there may be an Engagement to them. There may be liberty of Change in people in reference to Paſtors amongſt them, and yet there may be Engaging alſo. And as for the Scriptures that are brought to prove the lawfulneſſe of Engaging they might have been ſpared; for the lawfulneſſe of it is not denyed, Provided, That ſuch Engaging be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional: and therefore they need no Anſwer.</p>
            <p>3, <hi>This his Poſition not onlie diſaloweth all ſuch Engagement, but diſſolves the Natural and Moral Bond it ſelf of Dutie and Subjection to Magiſtrates; For to be free to Change when a man judgeth it beſt, is to be free when he wil; and that is, Not to be tyed at all, &amp;c. and then a man may diſobey Commands, and take up Arms, and be exempt from the Sword of the Magiſtrate, becauſe ſuch an Oath to continue anie Government longer then he thinks it ſafe, ſaith this Doctor, is ſinful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> It is not my Poſition, but his own Fiction, that diſſolves al Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: For I have not aſſerted [but he hath imagined ſo much] That any man may be free to Change when he judgeth it beſt, but I place the power of erecting, and plucking up, and changing for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths Good, where it ought to be of right, in the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the People. As for that Title, which in ſcorn he puts upon me, I paſſe it over, knowing, That it is more his ſhame to do it, then mine to ſuffer it.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:165675:35"/>
            <p>But ſaith he, <hi>I would fain have him declare what thing Magiſtracie and Subjection is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The Apoſtle hath declared, Rom. 13. 1, &amp;c. Tit. 3. 1. 1 Pet. 2. 13. to which I adhere: Magiſtracy is a Principallity or higher Power ordained of God, and (yet in reference to the ſpecial form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the perſons holding it) choſen, and immediatly conſtituted by men, for their good; And Subjection, is the Peoples acknowledging and obeying for their own good this Principallity, to ordained of God,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 15 20. 1 Kim. 11. 26. 1. 12. &amp;c. Act. 5. 36.</note> and ſo conſtituted by men.</p>
            <p>4, He ſaith, <hi>This Doctrine wil acquit, and juſtifie all the Conſpiracies and Treaſons that ever were enterpriſed againſt the power of the Magiſtrate ſince the World was, for all will be pretended to be for the great good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This is a great ſlander that is caſt upon this Doctrine ſo far as it is mine, for ſeeing that it only reſerves a liberty in Common-wealths, to change upon weighty Cauſes which their Repreſentatives are Judges of, and Agents in; it juſtifies no particular perſons, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> particular par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Riſings, but it may be truly ſaid, That this Doctrine cuts the comb of al Tyranny, and wil force, and conſtrain Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernors to a good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
            <p>But after he had ſo greatly aſperſed and vilified this Doctrine (as he cals it) which (indeed) was formed in his own heart; he approacheth ſomewhat neerer to the truth of my Aſſertion by way of Objection, but reacheth not fully the ſenſe in which I intended it; His words are theſe, <hi>But it may be ſaid, Not particular men, or a leſſer partie, are to judge of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncie, or take in hand the change, but the whole People.</hi> And he argues againſt it thus,</p>
            <p>1 He ſaith, <hi>Seldo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e or never doth a whole Nation under a lawful Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of themſelves, affect, or move to a Change, it is the flatterers and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceivers of the people that lead the people to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> If they do not affect, and move to a Change, yet if their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives do it, who are not (I hope, in this mans accompt) the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers and deceivers of the People, but the Truſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es or t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e people for their good, the people do it in them, unleſſe they do in their Petitions generally appear againſt it.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>How the judgement and will of the whole Bodie of the people</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhould be known and declared unto execution, before particular men Act to a Change of their own private judgement, is to me a thing unimaginable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> When the whole Body of a people have entruſted certain Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected ones with their Power, their Truſtees meeting together, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Coreſpondence with the ſeveral Counties, and Places that Choſe them; and ſent them out in their Name, mav act for a Change for the peoples good. And is this unimaginable? Beſides, If this were not,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:165675:36"/> yet the Common-wealth conſiſts of rational, ſociable Creatures, which meet at Church and Market (as the ſaying is) that is, have occaſions of the Communication of Councels; and ſo it comes to paſſe, That the apprehenſions of ſome men comes to be the Spirit of the moſt of the People, nor is there any indirectneſſe or unlawfulneſſe in this.</p>
            <p>5, He ſaith, <hi>This neceſſitie of retaining a power in Subjects to Change, and of uſing it for a greater good, or removing of a temporal hurt, in oppoſition to an Oath ſworn againſt that Change, is directlie againſt theſe Scriptures, tying men that ſwear to their own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urt not to Change, Pſal. 15. 4. Ioſh. 9. 18, 19. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning thoſe that for ſuch ends have receded from their Oathes, Ezek. 17. 13. &amp;c. Ioſh. 9. 15. compared with 2 Sam.</hi> 21. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 Theſe Scriptures have been oft made uſe of, and often An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; That in Pſal. 15. 4. ſpeaks of particular mens ſwearing for the ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>age and good of another, and their own diſadvantage; but ſpeaks not of things that have been, and may be pernicious; not to ſingle perſons alone, but to Common-wealths; and not profitable to any, unleſſe to ſaitsfie the luſts of ſome parricular perſons. And I would ask, Whether if a Common-wealth ſhould ſwear Succeſſion of Judges in al the Courts within it ſelf, ſhould ſuch an Oath ſtand or not? Or, whether would not ſuch an Oath, rather fal under his own Exception, That the thing ſworn to muſt be juſt and honeſt, elſe it is not obliging<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And I would know a Reaſon wherefore it ſhould not much rather be aſſerted of the ſupream Judge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>2 If there hath been ſuch a perpetuating Oath to any Family, yet it is Conditional while that Family carrieth it juſtly, and according to the Laws of the Kingdom: and ſo it is, That as a Family advanceth it ſelf ſometimes by vertue over the people, meriting their favour as <hi>Gideon</hi> did, and gaining their Promiſe (yea oath) that they ſhal Rule, and their Son, and their Sons Son: So a Family may by vice, diſhonour it ſelf; and loſe that favour, and be adjudged worthy to be ſleighted, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiered; yea, Cenſured and Puniſhed, as <hi>Sauls</hi> houſe came to reproach and ignominie: And an Oath, or many Oathes, would not have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported it, or confirmed it.</p>
            <p>3 That Oath of Joſh. 9. 18, 19. to the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> was ratified after they knew that they were their neighbors, and after they knew that they had tranſgreſſed the Commandement of the Lord (though unwillingly) by making peace with them; and therefore if they had not had ſome ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al warrant from the Lord for it, it would have been in them double ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity to have confirmed it. But its more then probable, That (being it was in <hi>Ioſhua's</hi> dayes, to whom God did much reveal himſelf, and ſeeing they had miſt it by raſhneſſe before in not enquiring at Gods mouth) they went to God about it, and had his direction in it; therefore the offence of <hi>Saul</hi> became ſo heinous, as 2 Sam. 21. 2. ſhews.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:165675:36"/>
            <p>4 That in Ezek. 17. 13. &amp;c. is not for his turn, but rather againſt him; For, 1 <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> made <hi>Zedekiah</hi> King, who was not King til he made him; and ſo he was of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar's</hi> ſetting up. 2 <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ohadnezzar</hi> took of him an Oath to be faithful, and he brake this Oath. 3 Therefore <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> juſtly came againſt him, and depoſed him, and put out his eyes, and carried him to <hi>Babylon;</hi> and ſo (indeed) origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally it was the Common-wealth in their Repreſentatives, make the King (for their beſt Title was from Parliament) and they take him ſworn to Rule according to the Laws, and he breaks his oath, and they declare the Common-wealth diſingaged from him, and they not not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him, but ſuffer not any of his Seed to Reign. Thus it appears he ſtrengthens that by Scripture which he would invalidate: Other Anſwers have been given beſides this, when this Text hath been urged, to which I refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>6, <hi>That Poſition ſo much inſiſted upon now a-dayes, of the Peoples tower to depoſe, aboliſh, and alter the power of their Governors at pleaſure, which is actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſetled, and both in it ſelf lawful, and lawfully ſet over them, I hold is a groſſe error.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I know no ſuch Poſition inſiſted on in <hi>Terminis,</hi> as he layes down; nay, I know, That al wiſe godly men do abhor ſuch a Poſition, of depoſing, aboliſhing their lawful Governors at pleaſure: But that Parliaments may do it in the Peoples Name, upon juſt, and weighty Cauſes; is aſſerted, and wil be maintained.</p>
            <p>But ſaith he, <hi>Some of my Reaſons in ſhort are:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> His Reaſons might be over-paſſed with out any anſwer, becauſe they be Reaſons of a <hi>Poſition of his own Invention, and will not be owned by them, at whom he ſtrikes at in it;</hi> yet they ſhal be conſidered of.</p>
            <p>1, He ſaith, <hi>Such a courſe (ſuppoſing the Governors diſſent) is no other then that reſiſtance of the Ordinance of God, condemned Rom.</hi> 13. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 This Reaſon ſuits not with the <hi>Poſition,</hi> which he undertakes to Confute, in the limitations that he gives it; For he ſaith, That the Governors muſt be lawfully <hi>ſet over,</hi> but the Governors, Rom. 13. 2. were ſet over the People by the Souldery, by the power of the Sword. And yet he ſaith, To remove ſuch (when their continuance is for the peoples hurt, without their own conſent) is a reſiſting of an Ordinance of God, which (I beleeve) when he conſidereth more ſeriouſly of, wil not appear truth in his own eyes.</p>
            <p>2 The Text of Rom. 13. hath nothing at al to do with (neither meddleth it with) a States Changing his Governors, and altering for the better; but he requires obedience to received Governors in lawful things, while they remain Governors, and are in their Offices. I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he wil not deny, but that the <hi>Senate of Rome,</hi> while the power was theirs (though they obeyed Dictators, and Emperors, whilſt they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:165675:37"/> them) might yet upon juſt cauſe remove them, without falling under the guilt of reſiſting the Ordinance of God, condemned in Rom. 13. 2.</p>
            <p>2, <hi>It is directlie oppoſue to that Subjection commanded every ſoul, that is in relation of a Subject, Rom 13. 1. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This may receive the like Anſwer with the former; and in the inſtance of Paſtors in reference to their flocks may be morefully cleered. Is it required in Heb. 13. 17. <hi>That the People obey them that have the Rule over them in the Lord, and to ſubmit unto them:</hi> but this doth not take away their power of removing them from their Offices, upon their unworthy and un-Paſtor-like carriages; Suppoſe (to prevent controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies) it be in a place where there is no <hi>Claſſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3, <hi>It the People may do it, then it muſt needs be that they have a Civil Power over their Magiſtrates which is contrarie to thoſe Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ures which make the King Supream, 1 Pet. 2. 13. and call the Powers that the People are to be Subject to, Higher Powers, Rom. 13. 1. higher in relation to them, &amp;c. And if the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates be over the People, how are they under them, to be removed or changed by them, &amp;c? If the Magiſtrate be under the People whom are they over? If the People be above the Magiſtrate, whom are they under, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The People may be conſidered, either in Themſelves, or in their Subſtitutes and Repreſentatives; in Themſelves, and ſo they may be taken as they are a Community or Common-wealth collectively; Or diſtributively, as individual perſons and members of the Community or Common-wealth. If they be conſidered as a Community, the Root of al Civil power is in them, and they are Supream, and greater then all the individual members of them, ſo far as concerns right, but not ſo far as concerns the exerciſe of power, for that is in their Subſtitutes, and Truſtees, who have the power of the Community for the exerciſe of it. The Repreſentatives alſo may be conſidered in a two-fold Reſpect; as a Parliament and Court Collectively, and ſo they ſet up Judges, and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and Magiſtrates, both the Superiour and the Inferiour, and are greater then they: Or they are conſidered ſingly, and perſonally, and as out of Courts, and as pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate men; and ſo they are leſſer, and inferior; to the very Officers which they themſelves in Court do make: So any Parliament-man is ſubject to inferiour Courts and the Judges thereof, as other men are. And a King, or any other Chief-Magiſtrate, or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, by what Title ſoever you wil cal them, may be conſidered in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the People, as they are a Common-wealth, Collectively; and ſo he is not Superiour, or greater then they, in the right of Power, though in the exerciſe, he is. But conſider him, in reference to any of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſingly, whether in Office, or Office, he is greater both in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and in the exerciſe of it, then any other, either perſon, or party: So of the Repreſentatives, they are al Subjects ſingly and a part conſidered;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:165675:37"/> and he is ſupream over them al; but Collectively conſidered, they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the power of the Common-wealth, and he ſet up by the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, (or by them in the Common-wealths name) they are greater then he; and he himſelf in that ſenſe is but a Subject, though the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal in reference to that great authority, wherwith he is entruſted. Thus a Prince is <hi>Major ſingulis, &amp; Minor univerſis;</hi> greater then any part, but leſſe then the whole. And (indeed) there is ſound Reaſon for it: Kings are for Common-wealths, and not Common-wealths for them; and therefore Common-wealths are greater. They are Miniſters (ſaith the Apoſtle) as to God; ſo in a ſenſe, to Common-wealths for their good: Common-wealths create them, and impower them, therefore they are leſſe then them. The Repreſentatives alſo, may be conſidered, as Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and then no Magiſtrate is ſupream to them; or as not Sitting, and then the Magiſtrate, King, or other chief Governor, may be called ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream in the exerciſe of Power, though not in the right of it.</p>
            <p>4, <hi>The holie Ghoſt commands the People, To render Tribute, Cuſtome, Fear, Honor, not at random to the Magiſtrate, leaving them at libertie to what they pleaſe, but to whom they are due; which reſpects a determinate object, the preſent Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The whole of this may be granted, for it ſerves only to prove ſubjection to the preſent Magiſtrate, but it hinders not a Change; but that if Reaſon, and the good of the Community require, one may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and another ſet up in his ſtead; and he who is impowered, is to have the tribute.</p>
            <p>5, <hi>Magiſtrates are of God, his Ordinance, and Miniſters, and Iudges for him, and his Vicegerents, Rom. 13. 24. 2 Chr. 19. 6. and therefore cannot ſtand at the meer will of the People; God muſt have a hand in their removal, as he hath in their admiſſion, or elſe it is injurious: he r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moves and admits now, not by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate revelation, as ſometime in Iſrael, but by the rule of his Word, executed by man: He hath given a rule for the ſetting up of Magiſtrats, but where hath he given anie for their depoſing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> As Magiſtrates are Gods Ordinance, ſo they are Mans Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; becauſe man determines both of the kind of Government, and doth alſo deſign the men, but alwayes, according to Gods Word: And as they are Judges for him, and his Vicegerents, ſo they are Judges for the Common-wealth and their Subſtitutes. They Judge for God, <hi>viz.</hi> His Glory: and for the People, <hi>viz.</hi> Their Good, Rom. 13. 4. And it being confeſſed, That their admiſſion and removal is not immediatly from God, but by men, according to Gods Word; it wil follow, That in that way, by which Regularly they enter into Power and Office, by that way, they may be put forth, and removed from Office: For, <hi>Eorum eſt deponere, quorum eſt ponere.</hi> And let me ſee that Rule that God hath given for ſetting up, and I doubt not, but I ſhal make the ſame Rule
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:165675:38"/> ſerve for putting down. Indeed, That Scripture wherein it is ſaid, <hi>That Kings, &amp;c. are the Ordinances of Man,</hi> doth impower man, both to ſet-up, and to pul down.</p>
            <p>6, <hi>If it were in the Peoples power to change their Magiſtrates at pleaſure, then how could it be ſuch a heinous ſin, as it is challenged to be, for the People to reject</hi> Samuels <hi>Government, &amp; deſire, &amp; move for a King, 1 Sam.</hi> 8. 6, 7. &amp; 12. 17?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply. Samuels</hi> Government, was Gods Government; for there were Elders of the People, and Princes of the Tribes, by whom the People were ordinarily Governed; and there were Judges raiſed up by God immediatly, at certain times when they were moleſted by the Nations round about them, of which <hi>Samuel</hi> was one: Now that which God had Conſtituted, That, they might not Change, eſpecially not for a worſe, as they did, when they choſe Kingly Government after the manner of the Nations.</p>
            <p>After al his own Reaſons againſt change of Government, he comes to weigh my Reaſon for the lawfulneſſe of Change; which was this, <hi>That though Civil Government in general be the Ordinance of God for mans good, therefore to reject it would be ſin: yet, this, or that kind of Government is not the Ordinance of God, but an Ordinance of man, and therefore man may change it.</hi> And againſt theſe words (<hi>is not the Ordinance of God, but an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of man</hi>) he bends himſelf by ſeveral Arguments to overthrow it; and yet in the iſſue he eſtabliſheth it. And becauſe my words in point of cleerneſſe were not ſo ful, he takes advantage; but yet opening that text of <hi>Peter,</hi> which I aleadge for the proof of my Aſſertion, he gives my ſenſe wherein I made uſe of it; but I ſhal ſet down his Exception in his own words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Civil Government in the general cannot be ſaid to be Gods Ordinance, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unrejectable; but this, or that kind of Government that is a legitimate, and true</hi> ſpecies <hi>of it, muſt neceſſarilie be yeelded to be Gods Ordinance and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> When I expreſſe my ſelf in theſe words, <hi>This, or that kind of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is not the Ordinance of God, but the Ordinance of man:</hi> my meaning was, This, or that kind of Government, is not in ſuch ſort, or ſenſe, the Ordinance of God, as Government in general is; that is, Is not by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Inſtitution impoſed upon al, or any people, as Government in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral is; is not by Commandement laid upon any people to neceſſitate the receiving of it, as Government in general is: So that it cannot be ſaid of any ſpecial Government, That if a Nation, or People, receive it not, admit it not, it ſins in not doing it; as it may be ſaid of Government in general, That if any People receives it not, that People ſins in not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it. And becauſe I ſpeak of ſinning, in the not-admitting of the one, and not of ſinning in the not-admitting of the other; it is plain, That I meant it in the ſenſe that I have now expreſſed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:165675:38"/> it. And in this ſenſe he concurs with me; his words are, <hi>Government in its ſpecial nature, is Warranted for anie People, but not Commanded, or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed (as Government in general is) upon everie Nation:</hi> and he ſaith after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, That <hi>Peter</hi> terms Government <hi>Mans Ordinance, becauſe both the ſpecial form of Government, and the perſons holding it, are choſen, and ſo imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly Conſtituted by man.</hi> And this is that which I aſſert: So that when I ſaid, That Government in <hi>ſpecie, was not an Ordinance of God;</hi> my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was, It was not an Ordinance by any ſpecial Commandment, as go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in general was; it was not immediatly Conſtituted by God, but by men. God doth not ſo Inſtitute the kinds of Officers in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, as he doth the kinds of Officers in Churches. And in this lay the ſtrength of my Reaſon; <hi>Therefore if the ſpecial kinds of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be not Commanded by God, but choſen, and immediatlie Conſtituted by men, then they may be changed by men; Provided, That their grounds be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to bear ſuch a Change.</hi> And to this he replyeth nothing, nor diſables it at al; ſo that the Reaſon ſtands in ſtrength, and the Conſequence is firm and unſhaken; <hi>viz. That ſuch an Oath, that tends abſolutlie to uphold anie one forme of Government, is unlawful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he urgeth this Argument againſt my words in the ſenſe that he took them; as if I had aſſerted, That they were not the Ordinance of God at al: and ſaith thus, <hi>Whatever is predicated of the</hi> genus, <hi>or general na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; is predicated of the</hi> ſpecies, <hi>or ſpecial nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I appeal to the Reader, Whether he doth not herein Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict himſelf afterwards, when he ſaith, <hi>That of the general nature of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it may be ſaid, That it is the Commandment of God; but of the ſpecial kind of Government (he ſaith) that it cannot be ſaid, That it is the Commandment of God, but warranted onlie by God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is alſo a Second Contradiction in his words, whilſt he proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes againſt my Expreſſion ſo earneſtly; (if my underſtanding fail me not) he ſaith in one place, That <hi>Government is Inſtituted in its ſpecial nature by God;</hi> and afterwards he ſaith, <hi>It is not Commanded by God, and that both the ſpecial forme of Government, and the perſons holding it, are immediatlie Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is alſo a Third Contradiction (which in this bad Cauſe which he manageth) he runneth into; He had ſaid in pag. 5. <hi>The King, as King, Acts onlie by his Courts and Laws, and what he doth, beſides theſe, is the Mans not the Kings; and that things may be done againſt his perſonal Commands.</hi> Yet in this place he ſaith, <hi>The Magiſtrates, not the Government abſtractlie are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gods Ordinance:</hi> the meaning is, The King, not King-ſhip (where Kingly Government is on foot) the perſon of the King, the Man, not the Power (as it ought to be exerciſed according to Law) is the Ordinance of God, and muſt be obeyed.</p>
            <p>After the Conſequence, by way of Illuſtration, I expreſſed my ſelf in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:165675:39"/> ſome words, concerning the heavie plague that hath been upon this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Kingly Government, and of the many bleſſings that have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Change of it, among the United Provinces, which he takes great offence at, wherein I ſhal be juſtified by the Chronicles, that record the Reigns of the Kings of this Nation, and the plentiful experience which many thouſands living have had of the truth thereof in ſome of them. Notwithſtanding leſt I ſhould move his patience further, I ſhal forbear any further Reply. It is enough what the Parliament when the Houſe was ful, and Voted, <hi>NO more Addreſſes to be made,</hi> hath publiſhed to the World concerning the late King.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, in the Cloſe of the firſt Argument, he comes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of the Objection which I (knowing many other would be ready to make it) both framed, and anſwered: The Objection was, <hi>Though the Oath might be unlawful to be taken, yet being taken, it ought to be kept:</hi> The Anſwer was, That <hi>if</hi> Herods <hi>Oath was unlawful to be taken, and much more unlawful to be kept, being only an Oath againſt the life of one man; then this Oath of Allegian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e (if abſolute) was not onlie unlawful to be taken, but alſo to be kept, becauſe verie dangerous to the lives, ſtate, and liberties of a Common-wealth of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Anſwer hereto, in ſubſtance is this;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He cannot paralel</hi> Herods <hi>Oath and ours in the mater, wherein</hi> Herods <hi>was unlawful both in the taking and keeping. What was the matter of that? To ſhed innocent bloud: To maſſacre a guiltleſs and holie Perſon. Now what is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ours? To yeeld Obediance in lawful things, to a lawful power: Is it anie more? And are not the matter of theſe two Oathes, as far unlike as light and darkneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> There's only this difference, That Oath was to kil directly; This conſequently: <hi>That</hi> ſpeedily and out of hand; <hi>This</hi> ſurely and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, though uncertain in reference to the time when. For if the Oath be of abſolute obedience, to the Father, and Son, and Sons Son, and al after-Heirs, then not only active, but paſſive obedience muſt be yeelded; and if the perſon be the power, as he aſſerts from Rom. 13. 2. compared with verſ. 3, 4. (his words are theſe, <hi>The Magiſtrate, not the Government abſtractlie (are called Gods Ordinance)</hi> then the perſon may not be reſiſted in any thing, let him do what he wil; let him become a <hi>Nero,</hi> yet he may not be reſiſted, no not in his Miniſters; For his name and his authority is in them, and it is impoſſible to reſiſt them, but there wil be a reſiſting of him in them. And if this be ſo, then the Floud-gates are ſet open to al Iniquity, and corrupt men which are chief in power, and are ſecure from al oppoſition and reſiſtance, that know that they may have life and ſtate and al at their demand without contradiction, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to al unrighteouſneſſe and oppreſſion. Even as a graceleſſe perſon, that is in want, and knoweth that the Judge wil neither hang him, nor
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:165675:39"/> puniſh him, is invited to rob and ſteal: what an unrighteous Oath then is this, in the very matter of it, that tempts the Prince in ſuch ſort to al lewdneſſe and wickedneſſe, and that wil certainly, either ſooner or later, be deſtructive? And how unmeet is it to be kept? It is as it a Judge ſhould ſwear to al poor perſons that are in want, That whatever they do, he wil not queſtion them: thoſe who are good, would be good ſtill, notwithſtanding this Oath; but yet it would invite naughty minded per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to al diſhoneſty and unrighteouſneſſe, and it would expoſe the lives and eſtates of men that have any thing, to extream danger, though it would be uncertain who the perſons are that would ſuffer, or at what time they might ſuffer violence, but they are not ſecure any moment, ſuch is the Oath of abſolute Allegiance, and ſuch an Oath as this kept, is more murtherous then the Oath of <hi>Herod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Second place he comes to Conſider of the Second Poſition, <hi>viz. That the Repreſentatives of the People, (which in reaſon are the Supream power) impoſed this Oath, by an Act of Parliament, this was the Subjects free Act in their Repreſentatives, no Law of God or Nature obliging them to accept of ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and his Heirs, and to ſwear Allegiance to them; if therefore the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives take away and Repeal this Act, as this Parliament hath done, they thereby ſet the Subject at liberty from ſuch Allegiance, and from their Oath binding to it, there remains no more Conſcience of it to ſuch which have taken it.</hi> Abraham <hi>that impoſed the Oath upon his Servant, might acquit him of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He begins with the Antecedent of this Poſition, and Notes Three things;</p>
            <p>1 He ſaith, <hi>He ſets up a Supream power over us by Reaſon, not by Law or the Peoples Conſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Though it be by Reaſon, yet it is by Law and by the peoples Conſtitution alſo, for the People appoint their Repreſentatives, and the perſons whom they appoint, are the Parliament; and this is according to Law: And this Parliament hath the power of making Laws, and repealing them, and the King by Oath is ſworn to confirme what they conclude on, and preſent unto him; as at the beginning of the War was held out in thoſe Declarations which they put forth for the Kingdoms ſatisfaction. The Parliament then is above the King according to Law, and the peoples Conſtitution: For, he is bound up to their Concluſions which they make for the good of the Kingdom, and they are not bound up to his, yet it is according to Reaſon alſo.</p>
            <p>But he asketh, <hi>What Reaſon? Private, or Common Reaſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 Common Reaſon ſhewes that in the mixture of Families in one Common-wealth, where there is no natural headſhip (as in one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily there hath been) there, without conſent, there can be no headſhip, or power, or Government; And thoſe that muſt Conſent, are the Root of that power or Government that comes to be amongſt them.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:165675:40"/>
            <p>2 Common Reaſon ſhews alſo, That al the people that give this Conſent unto a power or powers to be over them, cannot act this power which is founded in their Conſent.</p>
            <p>3 Common Reaſon ſhews, That thoſe whom they Subſtitute for the acting of their power in matters of Supream concernment, are the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream power.</p>
            <p>4 Common Reaſon ſhews, That if theſe Subſtitutes or Truſtees for the people do chuſe one Stateſman to Rule over al, or a Councel of State to do it, yet they that chuſe and ſet up ſuch perſons, are greater in power then they that are choſen.</p>
            <p>5 Common Reaſon ſhews, That if ſuch Princes who have gotten Poſſeſſion of the Kingdom by the Sword, have yet Complyed with the Parliament to obtain a ſure Title, then the power of putting in and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing ſuch Chief Commanders, appertaineth to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But how comes it then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that there is ſuch variety of kinds of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Government?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This hath come to paſſe ſometimes becauſe the peoples Right hath been invaded by force and power, and ſo the people hath not acted freely; and ſometimes by the intereſt of ſome perſons in the people, they have been wrought up to give conſent to this or that kind of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Government, or it may come from the variety of apprehenſions in ſeveral Common-wealths, affecting and chuſing rather this then that kind of Government. Notwithſtanding, in thoſe Common-wealths where the people chuſe their Repreſentatives to act their power for them, Common Reaſon ſaith that ſuch Repreſentatives are the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream power.</p>
            <p>2 He ſaith, <hi>In citing the power that Enacted this Oath, he omitts the King and Houſe of Lords, who in the then Parliament Concurred in this Enacting, and Impoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Neither King, nor Houſe of Lords had power to make a Law, that was the Prerogative of the peoples Repreſentatives, and the King muſt confirm what they did. Herein was the Repreſentative Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy above the other.</p>
            <p>3 He ſaith, <hi>That although the King was then rightfully and actually En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned in the Regal Power and Dignitie, and both the Law, and the Oath of Supremacy obliged the People to his Heirs, yet he dares to ſay, That no Law of God or Nature obliged them to except of ſuch a Perſon and his Heirs. Is not the Fifth Commandement the Law of God and Nature? And thoſe Precepts, Rom. 13. 1. Tit. 3. 1. 1 Pet. 2. 13. Repetitions and divine Ratifications thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 I ſpeak of things Originally as they were at firſt, himſelf ſpake a little before, That Government in the ſpecial forme of it, and the perſons holding it, was Choſen and immediatly Conſtituted by men; Where then is either Law of God or Nature, determinatively binding
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:165675:40"/> to it? Therefore what Right any ſuch Family hath, it was Originally by the Peoples receiving ſuch a Family, and therefore it was free and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary. 2 The 5 Commandement, Rom. 13. 1. Tit. 3. 1. 1 Pet. 2. 13. exalts not any Family to the Throne, nor doth require the people to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of ſuch and ſuch a Family to be over them; but being accepted, and while continued, requires ſubjection, but no further. 3 The Kings Anceſtors came by Conqueſt, and if rightfully Enthroned in Regal Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, then the Title by Conqueſt it ſeems is good by his Aſſertion, which yet in the preſent change, I beleeve he wil not acknowledge, nor dare I grant it without the conſent of the Repreſentatives in Parliament. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore it is that Kings themſelves, when they have got the Crown by the Sword, have deſire to hold it by Conſent of Parliament, and their Acts for it. 4 What Right came Originally by Parliament, and the Acts thereof, and not by any expreſſe Law of God or Nature, cannot be an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Right, but may be with-drawn, together with al the Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of it, if the Cauſes be juſt, by the ſame power that ſet it up.</p>
            <p>But for the Conſequence, he ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It hath no Truth in it, or colour of Reaſon, nor Inference from the Antecedent.</hi> But what Reaſon ſhews he for blaſting the Conſequence, and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in ſuch ſort?</p>
            <p>1 He ſaith, <hi>The Act cannot (for ought appears to me) be Repealed but by the ſame power that made it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> If he mean by the ſame power, the Repreſentatives in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then the ſame power that made the Act, hath Repealed it; but if he mean, by the ſame power, the King and Houſe of Lords, together with the Repreſentatives in Parliament, I have ſhewed, That the King and Houſe of Lords have no Legiſlative power at al, and that it is the Repreſentative ſole priviledge to make Laws, and the King muſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, therefore they could do it without him.</p>
            <p>2 He ſaith, <hi>The Allegiance ſworn was not founded upon that Act, or Oath, but due before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I have not Aſſerted, That the Allegiance is founded upon that Act or Oath, but I hold the contrary, <hi>viz</hi> That the Oath is founded upon Allegiance that was due before. But this I Aſſert, That Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance was never abſolutly but conditionally due: 1 While the Prince keeps his Oath in the Coronation, taken to adminiſter Juſtice. 2 While the Parliament have not declared him to have broken his Oath, and ſo that relation ceaſe betwixt him &amp; the people, &amp; conſequently the Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to be at an end, and conſequently the Oath of it to be extinct. This is cleerly my Tenant, That while Allegiance is due to any Governor whatever, the Oath that hath been taken of it is binding, and that al per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and powers in the World, are never able to abſolve or acquit the perſons that have taken it, from it: But yet withal this I hold, That
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:165675:41"/> 1 Allegiance may expire, 2 That it then expires when the Condition of it is not kept. 3 That the Parliament is the Supream power, and ſo the Judge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this when the Condition is broken. 4 When they declare that the Condition is broken (unleſſe there be a palpable unrighteouſneſs in their Declaration) and when they by their Acts do diſcharge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their Allegiance, and do Repeal the Act for the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, then the people are free, firſt, of their Allegiance, and then of the Oath which they took of it. And this is that which I further hold, That the People or Common-wealth are firſtly and principally ſubject to the Parliament their Repreſentatives, for they have put their whole power into their hand, ſo far as concerns the exerciſe of it, and have put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into ſubjection under them, and therefore their Allegiance is firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly due to them, and through them to any Governor or Governors, Prince or other Magiſtrate or Magiſtrates, whom they ſhal either ſet up and entruſt with the exerciſe of Supream power when they Sit not, or whom they ſhal confirm finding in that power, when they came to Sit. Why elſe have perſons who have come to the Throne by Conqueſt, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly called Parliaments to ratifie and confirme their Title, which they foreſaw might be juſtly queſtioned without ſuch ratification. And in this ſenſe it is, That the Parliament it ſelf hath taken the Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to Princes, not Collectively as an Houſe ſitting in power and authority of Parliament; for in that ſenſe themſelves were Supream, but as ſingle perſons and members of the Common-wealth, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are ſubject to the power that as a Parliament themſelves erect and confirm. And I alſo conceive, That hereupon there is no Allegiance to any Magiſtrate againſt the Parliament, but that the Parliament may make it void, while they remain the Peoples Repreſentatives, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in that place and power. As now in this Change of things, the Councel of State, is the Supream power of the Nation, at al times when there ſhal be no Parliament ſitting; but in the time of Parliament, the Parliament it ſelf is Supream, and not they. And though the perſons of al Parliament men, and al the Nation with them, ſhould ſwear Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to that Councel, yet it is in, and not againſt the authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they ſo ſwear; and if the Councel of State ſhould miſcarry in point of Government, and the Parliament ſhould declare them to be no Councel of State, both themſelves who in their perſons were ſworn, and al the people who have taken that Oath with them, are acquitted from it. For the Allegiance it ſelf and the Oath to confirme it, are firſt due to the higher power, who hath power over both the Councel of State (and for maleadjuration may cal them to accompt) and the people alſo, and ſo may diſcharge the one of Government, and the other of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to them. And ſo I look upon the Parliament, as the principal party in the Oath of Allegiance to any Prince, and the Oath to the Prince is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:165675:41"/> through them, and in them, and not againſt them; and ſo the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (the Cauſes being juſt and weighty) have power to acquit from it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And in that ſenſe it was that I produced the inſtance of <hi>Abraham<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> So if a Magiſtrate ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a Conſtable, to obey <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is lawful Commands, according to his place; a ſuperior power to the Magiſtrate, who hath power over them both, by removing the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate from his Truſt, abſolves the Conſtable from the Allegiance, and from his Oath alſo. And this is ſo cleer, that none can rationally deny it. Yea, he himſelf grants it, in his firſt Argument againſt my Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, only he denies that this is the Caſe in Controverſie, (but it is but a bare denial) for he ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where the impoſers are alſo the partie ſworn to, there it is granted that there may be abſolving from the Oath, or a diſpencing with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the Caſe becauſe an Oath to an inferior power is made in and not againſt the ſuperior power, in and through whom, Duty and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance is due to the inferior power, I hope then there is both Truth, and colour of Reaſon, and good inference in the Conſequence. He grants further, and ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are Caſes wherein a ſuperiour, as a Husband, Maſter, Father, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, may make void the Oath of their reſpective inferior, by an Analogie or equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of that Rule: but theſe are</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in matters belonging to the right and power of the Superiour to diſpoſe of, as the Repreſentatives may acquit from an Oath in point of their own right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This is the very Caſe, it is the right of the Repreſentatives to be Supream; therefore any Oath of the Subject, to any Magiſtrate, (ſuppoſe a Prince) is not againſt them, bnt in them, and they are the principal party; it is to the other in them, they may therefore abſolve from it, by taking Rule from the one, and Duty from the other, becauſe both are ſubordinate unto them, and they are principally concerned in the Oath that paſſeth betwixt them.</p>
            <p>Thus I have endeavoured to maintain the Truth of the Poſitions: Let the Reader judge betwixtus.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:165675:42"/>
            <head>There is one thing more which I think good to annex to what I have held forth in this Reply, <hi>viz.</hi> My <hi>Anſwer</hi> to a <hi>Querie,</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion</hi> rather, which is drawn from my <hi>Poſitions,</hi> and is late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to my hands, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Querie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHAT may Conſcientiouſly be reſolved upon, in relation to the late Enacted</hi> Engagement, <hi>from the Principles and Premiſes laid down by me in the proſecution of my firſt Poſition? And whether I have not damned it, as to my ſelf, and to all thoſe who are of my mind, and perſwaded (fo far as my Poſition may prevail) all others not to take it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For thus he Argues from my Poſitions;</p>
            <p>If an Oath, or Promiſe, or Engagement, failing in any of thoſe Rules which in the Poſition are laid down, be unlawful, then the Enacted En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement muſt needs be unlawful, becauſe firſt it is abſolute, without any Proviſo of their Ruling wel, that are, or may be in power. 2 It is ſingle, or without the Rulers Engaging to the Subject to Rule wel and juſtly. 3 It is to thoſe of whom we may be as much unſatisfied, how they wil prove hereafter, as we can be of an Heir. 4 It is to one kind of Government, called, The Common-wealth, as it is now Eſtabliſhed, and that deſcribed with contradiſtinction from, and Excluſion of King and Lords. It is alſo to continue in a conſtant way, for the words run, [<hi>I will be true and faithful.</hi>]</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>If I ſhould look upon the Engagement, under ſuch apprehenſions as he hath looked upon the Oath of Allegiance, and pleaded for it, I ſhould not think it tolerable to be taken by any Conſciencious man. But I have other Conceptions of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1 I deny, That the Engagement is Abſolute, or that any ſuch En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement can be abſolute, but that at leaſt there wil be a tacite Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therein, for the Equity and Juſtice of the thing wil require it perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually; and that (however it would be more ſatisfactory if the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:165675:42"/> were expreſſed, yet it is palpable enough that the Condition is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, though not one word ſhould be ſpoken. I have given Inſtance in Paſtor and People: If the people ſhould not indent with their Paſtor to Preach the Goſpel, but ſhould accept of him to be their Paſtor, and promiſe ſo much Maintenance unto him, yet it is implyed that it is upon the Condition of his Preaching to them; for no rational man wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that they promiſed ſuch Maintenance in reference to ſuch an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, without performing the work of the Office: So it is betwixt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate and Subject.</p>
               <p n="2">2 I deny, That the Engagement is ſingle; for long ſince there came forth a Declaration from the Parliament, wherein they Engaged to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the Nation according to known Laws of the Land. And this Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative was purpoſely ſet forth to ſatisfie the Nation, in reference to Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies that the people lay under. And it makes the Engagement mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual betwixt the Magiſtrate and the People. And if it be mutual, then it cannot be abſolute, as he aſſerted. For I have ſhewed, That in a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Engagement the Obligation of the one, hath reſpect unto, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence upon the performance of the other, ſo that if the one violate the Engagement in his part, the other is diſcharged upon it.</p>
               <p n="3">3 I deny, That it is to thoſe of whom we may be as much unſatisfied how they wil prove hereafter, as we can be of an Heir; for the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to the Repreſentatives of the Nation, of whom we were ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when we Choſe them, and we exerciſed our judgement when we Choſe them; and if otherwiſe, it was the Common-wealths fault. And we know what they have been, they have ſought the Nations welfare; and time wil declare what they wil be, and let them not be prejudged. However, they are but temporarie Rulers, and not ſo much as for term of life, much leſſe are their Heirs to be chief Rulers after them.</p>
               <p n="4">4 I deny, That the Engagement is to one kind of Government ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutly, whether hurtful or profitable, for the Repreſentatives of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have power to change it, when they ſee cauſe, for the good of the Nation, and they neither have, nor intend to tye their own hands abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutly, but that if they ſhould prove it to be pernicious, they might change it.</p>
               <p>So that it is apparent, by what I have preſented, That he hath totally miſtaken the buſineſs of the Engagement.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
